<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="startup.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <title>Startup</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Server Startup">

<p>
This page describes how the Tomcat server starts up.  There are several
different ways to start tomcat, including:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>From the command line.</li>
  <li>From a Java program as an embedded server.</li>
  <li>Automatically as a Windows service.</li>
</ul>

<p>
A series of UML diagrams have been created to document the start-up process for
Tomcat.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/1_overview.png">Diagram 1</a> shows an overview of how Tomcat
start, serves requests and then stops. Once the class loaders have been
initialized, Tomcat parses server.xml using the Digester and the Digester
creates the objects defined in server.xml, configures them using the property
values defined in server.xml and the starts the Server. The main Java thread
waits in the await() method for a shutdown signal. Once a shutdown signal is
received, the Server object is stopped and then destroyed. The JVM then exits.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/2_catalina_init.png">Diagram 2</a> shows how Tomcat initalizes
the objects created by the Digester in the previous step and when additional key
objects are created. A Server may have several Services although it typically
only has one. Each Service may have multiple Connectors. A Connector instance is
associated with a single Protocol instance and a single CoyoteAdapter instance.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/3_catalina_start_1.png">Diagram 3</a> shows how Tomcat starts
the objects created by the Digester that were initialized in the previous step.
This diagram also shows when lifecycle events are fired. There is more detail to
the starting of the Engine (and other Containers) which is shown in the
following diagram.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/4_catalina_start_2.png">Diagram 4</a> shows how Containers
(Engines, Hosts, Contexts and Wrappers) start along with any supporting
Clusters, Realms and Valves.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/5_catalina_start_3.png">Diagram 5</a> shows the start process
for Context elements as it is rather more involved that the other Containers.
</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/6_catalina_host_config.png">Diagram 6</a> shows how the
HostConfig component responds to lifecycle events triggered by the Host to
deploy web applications to the Host.</p>
<p>
<a href="startup/7_catalina_context_config.png">Diagram 7</a> shows how the
ContextConfig component responds to lifecycle events triggered by the Context to
parse the global and application provided configuration files to create a merged
web.xml file that is then used, along with other settings, to configure the web
application.
</p>

<p>
The startup process can be customized in many ways by implementing your own
LifecycleListeners which are then registered in the server.xml configuration
file.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
