<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

    &project;

    <properties>
      <author>Remy Maucherat</author>
      <title>Building Tomcat</title>
    </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>
Building Apache Tomcat from SVN is very easy, and is the first step to contributing to
Tomcat. The following is a step by step TODO list.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Download a Java Development Kit (JDK) release (version 1.6.x or later)">

<p>
The Sun JDK can be downloaded <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
<b>IMPORTANT</b>: Set an environment variable JAVA_HOME to the pathname of the 
directory into which you installed the JDK release.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Install Apache Ant 1.6.5 or later">

<p>
Download a binary distribution of Ant 1.6.5 or later from 
<a href="http://ant.apache.org/bindownload.cgi">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
Unpack the binary distribution into a convenient location so that the
Ant release resides in its own directory (conventionally named
"apache-ant-1.6.x").  For the purposes of the remainder of this document,
the symbolic name "${ant.home}" is used to refer to the full pathname of
 the release directory.
</p>

<p>
Create an ANT_HOME environment variable to point the directory ${ant.home}, 
and modify the PATH environment variable to include directory
"${ant.home}/bin" in its list.  This makes the "ant" command line script
available, which will be used to actually perform the build.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Checkout or obtain the source code for Tomcat 7.0">

  <p>
  Tomcat SVN repository URL:
  <code>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/tc7.0.x/</code>
  </p>
  
  <p>
  Download a source package from:
  <code>http://tomcat.apache.org/download-60.cgi</code>
  </p>
  
  <p>
  Checkout the source using SVN, selecting the desired version or
  branch (current development source is at 
  <code>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/tomcat/tc7.0.x/trunk/</code>), or 
  unpack the source package. The location where the source has been
  placed will be referred as ${tomcat.source}.
  </p>

</section>

<section name="Building Tomcat">

<p>
Use the following commands:
<code><br/>
    cd ${tomcat.source}<br/>
    ant download<br/>
    ant<br/>
</code>
</p>

<p>
NOTE: Users accessing the Internet through a proxy must use a properties
  file to indicate to Ant the proxy configuration. Read below.
</p>

<p>
WARNING: Running this command will download binaries to the 
  <code>/usr/share/java</code> directory. 
  Make sure this is appropriate to do so on your computer. On Windows, 
  this usually corresponds to the <code>C:\usr\share\java</code> directory, 
  unless Cygwin is used. Read below to customize the directory used 
  to download the binaries.
</p>

<p>
The build can be controlled by creating a ${tomcat.source}/build.properties
  file, and adding the following content to it:
<code><br/>
    # ----- Proxy setup -----<br/>
    # Uncomment if using a proxy server.<br/>
    #proxy.host=proxy.domain<br/>
    #proxy.port=8080<br/>
    #proxy.use=on<br/>
<br/>
    # ----- Default Base Path for Dependent Packages -----<br/>
    # Replace this path with the directory path where<br/>
    # dependencies binaries should be downloaded.<br/>
    base.path=/usr/share/java<br/>
</code>
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building with Eclipse">

<p>
<b>Important:</b>
This is not a supported means of building Tomcat; this information is
provided without warranty :-).
The only supported means of building Tomcat is with the "ant build"
described above.
However, some developers like to work on Java code with a Java IDE,
and the following steps have been used by some developers.
</p>

<p>
Note that you <b>must</b> complete all the above steps to fetch
the repositories and build some JAR files the first time.
After you have completed the above steps, you can set up a
series of Eclipse 4 projects.
<b>Note</b> that this will not let you build everything under Eclipse;
the build process requires use of Ant for the many stages that aren't
simple Java compilations.
However, it will allow you to view and edit the Java code,
get warnings, reformat code, perform refactorings, run Tomcat
under the IDE, and so on.
</p>

<p>
Use Windows-&gt;Preferences and then Java-&gt;Build Path-&gt;Classpath
Variables to add two new Classpath variables:
</p>

<p>
<table border="1">
 <tr><td>TOMCAT_LIBS_BASE</td><td>the base path where the binary dependencies have been downloaded</td></tr>
 <tr><td>ANT_HOME</td><td>the base path of Ant 1.6.5 or later</td></tr>
</table>
</p>

<p>
Use File-&gt;Import and chose &quot;Existing Projects into Workspace&quot;.
From there import the root directory where you have checked out tomcat.
</p>

<p>
Eclipse .project and .classpath files are provided in to root directory of tomcat repository
should allow Eclipse to find all source trees and jars, and
hopefully compile without problems. <b>Note</b> that these
files assume you are using Eclipse with a 6.0 or later JDK.
</p>

<p>
To run Tomcat without a special IDE plug-in, you can simply use Run-&gt;Run...
enter "org.apache.catalina.startup.Catalina" as the main class,
"start" as program arguments, and
"-Dcatalina.home=..." (with the name of your build directory) 
as VM arguments.
</p>

<p>
Note also that due to the way the Tomcat source is assembled
from several SVN projects, you may not be able to use the Eclipse
SVN client to update (nor to commit, if you are a committer).
Use the external SVN client of your choice, then use the
Eclipse PackageExplorer or Navigator "Refresh" context menu item
to tell Eclipse that you've updated the files.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building with other IDEs">
<p>
The same caveats apply as for Eclipse, above.
</p>

<p>
The same general idea should work in most IDEs; it has been reported
to work in Idea, for example.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
