<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues to not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.11 (markt)">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56658</bug>: Fix regression that a context was inaccessible after
        reload. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56710</bug>: Do not map requests to servlets when context is
        being reloaded. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56712</bug>: Fix session idle time calculations in
        <code>PersistenceManager</code>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56717</bug>: Fix duplicate registration of
        <code>MapperListener</code> during repeated starts of embedded Tomcat.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56724</bug>: Write an error message to Tomcat logs if container
        background thread is aborted unexpectedly. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When scanning class files (e.g. for annotations) and reading the number
        of parameters in a <code>MethodParameters</code> structure only read a
        single byte (rather than two bytes) as per the JVM specification. Patch
        provided by Francesco Komauli. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow the JNDI Realm to start even if the directory is not available.
        The directory not being available is not fatal once the Realm is started
        and it need not be fatal when the Realm starts. Based on a patch by
        Cédric Couralet. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56736</bug>: Avoid an incorrect <code>IllegalStateException</code>
        if the async timeout fires after a non-container thread has called
        <code>AsyncContext.dispatch()</code> but before a container thread
        starts processing the dispatch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56739</bug>: If an application handles an error on an application
        thread during asynchronous processing by calling
        <code>HttpServletResponse.sendError()</code>, then ensure that the
        application is given an opportunity to report that error via an
        appropriate application defined error page if one is configured. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56784</bug>: Fix a couple of rare but theoretically possible
        atomicity bugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56785</bug>: Avoid <code>NullPointerException</code> if directory
        exists on the class path that is not readable by the Tomcat user.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56796</bug>: Remove unnecessary sleep when stopping a web
        application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56801</bug>: Improve performance of
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.file.Matcher</code> which is to filter JARs
        for scanning during web application start. Based on a patch by Sheldon
        Shao. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56815</bug>: When the <code>gzip</code> option is enabled for the
        <code>DefaultServlet</code> ensure that a suitable <code>Vary</code>
        header is returned for resources that might be returned directly in
        compressed form. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not mark threads from the container thread pool as container threads
        when being used to process <code>AsyncContext.start(Runnable)</code> so
        processing is correctly transferred back to a genuine container thread
        when necessary. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add simple caching for calls to <code>StandardRoot.getResources()</code>
        in the new (for 8.0.x) resources implementation. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56825</bug>: Enable pre-emptive authentication to work with the
        SSL authenticator. Based on a patch by jlmonteiro. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56840</bug>: Avoid NPE when the rewrite valve is mapped to
        a context. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle multiple <code>accept-language</code> headers rather
        than just using the first header to determine the user&apos;s preferred
        Locale. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56848</bug>: Improve handling of <code>accept-language</code>
        headers. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56857</bug>: Fix thread safety issue when calling ServletContext
        methods while running under a security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix NIO2 sendfile state tracking and error handling to fix
        various corruption issues. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Missing timeout for NIO2 sendfile writes. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow inline processing for NIO2 sendfile and optimize keepalive
        behavior. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix excessive NIO2 sendfile direct memory use in some cases, sendfile
        will now instead use the regular socket write buffer as configured.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56661</bug>: Fix <code>getLocalAddr()</code> for AJP connectors.
        The complete fix is only available with a recent AJP forwarder like
        the forthcoming mod_jk 1.2.41. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use default ciphers defined as
        <code>HIGH:!aNULL:!eNULL:!EXPORT:!DES:!RC4:!MD5</code> so
        that no weak ciphers are enabled by default. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56780</bug>: Enable Tomcat to start when using SSL with an IBM JRE
        in strict SP800-131a mode. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56810</bug>: Remove use of Java 8 specific API calls in unit tests
        for OpenSSL to JSSE cipher conversion. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56709</bug>: Fix system property name in a log message. Submitted
        by Robert Kish. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56797</bug>: When matching a method in an EL expression, do not
        treat bridge methods as duplicates of the method they bridge to. In this
        case always call the target of the bridge method. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56746</bug>: Allow secure WebSocket client threads to use the
        current context class loader rather than explicitly setting it to the
        class loader that loaded the WebSocket implementation. This allows
        WebSocket client connections from within web applications to access,
        amongst other things, the JNDI resources associated with the web
        application. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct the label in the list of sessions by idle time for the bin that
        represents the idle time immediately below the maximum permitted idle
        time when using the expire command of the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>53088</bug>: More identifiable thread name. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>53200</bug>: Selective logging for slow versus failed queries.
        (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>53853</bug>: More flexible classloading. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54225</bug>: Disallow empty init SQL. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54227</bug>: Evaluate max age upon borrow. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54235</bug>: Disallow nested pools exploitating using data source.
        (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54395</bug>: Fix JDBC interceptor parsing bug. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54537</bug>: Performance improvement in
        <code>StatementFinalizer</code>. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>54978</bug>: Make sure proper connection validation always happens,
        regardless of config. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56318</bug>: Ability to trace statement creation in
        <code>StatementFinalizer</code>. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56789</bug>: getPool() returns the actual pool, always. (fhanik)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>56788</bug>: Display the full version in the list of installed
        applications when installed via the Windows installer package. Patch
        provided by Alexandre Garnier. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>56829</bug>: Add the ability for users to define their own values
        for <code>_RUNJAVA</code> and <code>_RUNJDB</code> environment
        variables. Be more strict with executable filename on Windows
        (s/java/java.exe/). Based on a patch by Neeme Praks. (markt/kkolinko)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.10 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>44312</bug>: Log an error if there is a conflict between Host and
        Alias names. Improve host management methods in <code>Mapper</code>
        to avoid occasionally removing a wrong host. Check that host management
        operations are performed on the host and not on an alias. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>56611</bug>: Refactor code to remove inefficient calls to
        <code>Method.isAnnotationPresent()</code>. Based on a patch by Jian Mou.
        (markt/kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Fix regression in
        <code>StandardContext.removeApplicationListener()</code>, introduced by
        the fix for bug <bug>56588</bug>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56653</bug>: Fix concurrency issue with lists of contexts in
        <code>Mapper</code> when stopping Contexts. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56657</bug>: When using parallel deployment, if the same session id
        matches different versions of a web application, prefer the latest
        version. Ensure that remapping selects the version that we expect.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Assert that mapping result object is empty before performing mapping
        work in <code>Mapper</code>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove <code>context</code> and <code>wrapper</code> fields in
        <code>Request</code> class and deprecate their setters. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56658</bug>: Avoid delay between registrations of mappings for
        context and for its servlets. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56665</bug>: Correct the generation of the effective web.xml when
        elements contain an empty string as value. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix storeconfig exception routing issues, so that a major problem
        should avoid configuration overwrite. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add configuration fields for header names in SSLValve. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56666</bug>: When clearing the SSO cookie use the same values for
        domain, path, httpOnly and secure as were used to set the SSO cookie.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56677</bug>: Ensure that
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getServletContext()</code> returns the correct
        value during a cross-context dispatch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56684</bug>: Ensure that Tomcat does not shut down if the socket
        waiting for the shutdown command experiences a
        <code>SocketTimeoutException</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56693</bug>: Fix various issues in the static resource cache
        implementation where the cache retained a stale entry after the
        successful completion of an operation that always invalidates the cache
        entry such as a delete operation.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When the current PathInfo is modified as a result of dispatching a
        request, ensure that a call to
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getPathTranslated()</code> returns a value that
        is based on the modified PathInfo. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56698</bug>: When persisting idle sessions, only persist newly idle
        sessions. Patch provided by Felix Schumacher. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56663</bug>: Fix edge cases demonstrated by ByteCounter relating
        to data available, remaining and extra write events, mostly occurring
        with non blocking Servlet 3.1. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid possible NPE stopping endpoints that are not started (stop
        shouldn't do anything in that case). (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56704</bug>: Add support for OpenSSL syntax for ciphers when
        using JSSE SSL connectors. Submitted by Emmanuel Hugonnet. (remm)
      </add>
      <update>
        Allow to configure <code>maxSwallowSize</code> attribute of an HTTP
        connector via JMX. (kkolinko)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56543</bug>: Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.4. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56652</bug>: Add support for method parameters that use arrays and
        varargs to <code>ELProcessor.defineFunction()</code>.(markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add support for the <code>permessage-deflate</code> extension. This is
        currently limited to decompressing incoming messages on the server side.
        It is expected that support will be extended to outgoing messages and to
        the client side shortly. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Attempt to obfuscate session cookie values associated with other web
        applications when viewing HTTP request headers with the Cookies example
        from the examples web application. This reduces the opportunity to use
        this example for malicious purposes should the advice to remove the
        examples web application from security sensitive systems be ignored.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56694</bug>: Remove references to <code>Manager</code> attribute
        <code>checkInterval</code> from documentation and Javadoc since it no
        longer exists. Based on a patch by Felix Schumacher. Also remove other
        references to <code>checkInterval</code> that are no longer valid.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the API stability section of the release notes now that Tomcat 8
        has had its first stable release. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Improve <code>build.xml</code> so that when Eclipse JDT Compiler is
        updated, it will delete the old JAR from <code>build/lib</code>
        directory. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Simplify implementation of "setproxy" target in <code>build.xml</code>.
        (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Update optional Checkstyle library to 5.7. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        <bug>56596</bug>: Update to Tomcat Native Library version 1.1.31 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.1h. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56685</bug>: Add quotes necessary for <code>daemon.sh</code> to
        work correctly on Solaris. Based on a suggesiton by lfuka. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons Pool2 to r1609323 to pick various
        bug fixes. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons DBCP2 to r1609329 to pick up a
        minor bug fix. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons FileUpload to r1596086 to pick
        various bug fixes. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.9 (markt)">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>55282</bug>: Ensure that one and the same application listener is
        added only once when starting the web application. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>55975</bug>: Apply consistent escaping for double quote and
        backslash characters when escaping cookie values. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>56387</bug>: Improve the code that handles an attempt to load a
        class after a web application has been stopped. Use common code to handle
        this case regardless of the access path and don't throw an exception
        purely to log a stack trace. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        <bug>56399</bug>: Improve implementation of CoyoteAdapter.checkRecycled()
        to do not use an exception for flow control. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>56461</bug>: New <code>failCtxIfServletStartFails</code> attribute
        on Context and Host configuration to force the context startup to fail
        if a load-on-startup servlet fails its startup. (slaurent)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>56526</bug>: Improved the <code>StuckThreadDetectionValve</code> to
        optionally interrupt stuck threads to attempt to unblock them.
        (slaurent)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56545</bug>: Pre-load two additional classes, the loading of which
        may otherwise be triggered by a web application which in turn would
        trigger an exception when running under a security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56546</bug>: Reduce logging level for stack traces of stuck web
        application threads printed by WebappClassLoader.clearReferencesThreads()
        from error to info. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor and simplify common code in object factories in
        <code>org.apache.catalina.naming</code> package, found thanks to Simian
        (Similarity Analyser) tool. Improve handling of Throwable.
        (markt/kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Relax cookie naming restrictions. Cookie attribute names used in the
        <code>Set-Cookie</code> header may be used unambiguously as cookie
        names. The restriction that prevented such usage has been removed.
        (jboynes/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Further relax cookie naming restrictions. Version 0 (a.k.a Netscape
        format) cookies may now use names that start with the <code>$</code>
        character. (jboynes/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Restrict cookie naming so that the <code>=</code> character is no longer
        permitted in a version 0 (a.k.a. Netscape format) cookie name. While
        Tomcat allowed this, browsers always truncated the name at the
        <code>=</code> character leading to a mis-match between the cookie the
        server set and the cookie returned by the browser. (jboynes/markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a simple <code>ServiceLoader</code> based discovery mechanism to the
        JULI <code>LogFactory</code> to make it easier to use JULI and Tomcat
        components that depend on JULI (such as Jasper) independently from
        Tomcat. Patch provided by Greg Wilkins. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56578</bug>: Correct regression in the fix for <bug>56339</bug>
        that prevented sessions from expiring when using clustering. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56588</bug>: Remove code previously added to enforce the
        requirements of section 4.4 of the Servlet 3.1 specification. The code
        is no longer required now that Jasper initialization has been refactored
        and TLD defined listeners are added via a different code path that
        already enforces the specification requirements. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56600</bug>: In WebdavServlet: Do not waste time generating
        response for broken PROPFIND request. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Provide a better error message when asynchronous operations are not
        supported by a filter or servlet. Patch provided by Romain Manni-Bucau.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56606</bug>: User entries in <code>tomcat-users.xml</code> file
        are recommended to use "username" attribute rather than legacy "name"
        attribute. Fix inconsistencies in Windows installer, examples. Update
        digester rules and documentation for <code>MemoryRealm</code>.
        (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56518</bug>: When using NIO, do not attempt to write to the socket
        if the thread is marked interrupted as this will lead to a connection
        limit leak. This fix was based on analysis of the issue by hanyong.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56521</bug>: Re-use the asynchronous write buffer between writes to
        reduce allocation and GC overhead. Based on a patch by leonzhx. Also
        make the buffer size configurable and remove copying of data within
        buffer when the buffer is only partially written on a subsequent write.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that a request without a body is correctly handled during Comet
        processing. This fixes the Comet chat example. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix input concurrency issue in NIO2 upgrade. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a copy/paste error and return a 500 response rather than a 400
        response when an internal server error occurs on early stages of
        request processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>56582</bug>: Use switch(actionCode) in processors instead of a
        chain of "elseif"s. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56582#c1</bug>: Implement DISPATCH_EXECUTE action for AJP
        connectors. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        If request contains an unrecognized Expect header, respond with error
        417 (Expectation Failed), according to RFC2616 chapter 14.20. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When an error occurs after the response has been committed close the
        connection immediately rather than attempting to finish the response to
        make it easier for the client to differentiate between a complete
        response and one that failed part way though. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the beta tag from the NIO2 connectors. (remm)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56620</bug>: Avoid bogus access log entries when pausing the NIO
        HTTP connector and ensure that access log entries generated by error
        conditions use the correct request start time. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve configuration of cache sizes in the endpoint. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a new limit, defaulting to 2MB, for the amount of data Tomcat will
        swallow for an aborted upload. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56334#c15</bug>: Fix a regression in EL parsing when quoted string
        follows a whitespace. (kkolinko/markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56543</bug>: Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.4RC4 to pick up
        some fixes for Java 8 support. (markt/kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56561</bug>: Avoid <code>NoSuchElementException</code> while
        handling attributes with empty string value. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Do not configure a <code>JspFactory</code> in the
        <code>JasperInitializer</code> if one has already been set as might be
        the case in some embedding scenarios. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Add a simple implementation of <code>InstanceManager</code> and have
        Jasper use it if no other <code>InstanceManager</code> is provided. This
        makes it easier to use Jasper independently from Tomcat. Patch provided
        by Greg Wilkins. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56568</bug>: Allow any HTTP method when a JSP is being used as an
        error page. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56581</bug>: If an error on a JSP page occurs when response has
        already been committed, do not clear the buffer of JspWriter, but flush
        it. It will make more clear where the error occurred. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56612</bug>: Correctly parse two consecutive escaped single quotes
        when used in UEL expression in a JSP. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Move code that parses EL expressions within JSP template text from
        <code>Parser</code> to <code>JspReader</code> class for better
        performance. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56636</bug>: Correctly identify the required method when specified
        via <code>ELProcessor.defineFunction(String,String,String,String)</code>
        when using Expression Language. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56638</bug>: When using
        <code>ELProcessor.defineFunction(String,String,String,String)</code> and
        no function name is specified, use the method name as the function name
        as required by the specification. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        <bug>56446</bug>: Clearer handling of exceptions when calling a method
        on a POJO based WebSocket endpoint. Based on a suggestion by Eugene
        Chung. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        When a WebSocket client attempts to write to a closed connection, handle
        the resulting <code>IllegalStateException</code> in a manner consistent
        with the handling of an <code>IOException</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add more varied endpoints for echo testing. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56577</bug>: Improve the executor configuration used for the
        callbacks associated with asynchronous writes. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Set the path for cookies created by the examples web application so they
        only returned to the examples application. This reduces the opportunity
        for using such cookies for malicious purposes should the advice to
        remove the examples web application from security sensitive systems be
        ignored. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Attempt to obfuscate session cookie values associated with other web
        applications when viewing HTTP request headers with the Request Header
        example from the examples web application. This reduces the opportunity
        to use this example for malicious purposes should the advice to remove
        the examples web application from security sensitive systems be ignored.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add options for all of the WebSocket echo endpoints to the WebSocket
        echo example in the examples web application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the asynchronous WebSocket echo endpoint in the examples
        web application always waits for the previous message to complete before
        it sends the next. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons DBCP2 to r1596858. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.8 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-05-21">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56536</bug>: Ensure that
        <code>HttpSessionBindingListener.valueUnbound()</code> uses the correct
        class loader when the <code>SingleSignOn</code> valve is used. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
       <fix>
         <bug>56529</bug>: Avoid <code>NoSuchElementException</code> while handling
         attributes with empty string value in custom tags. Patch provided by
         Hariprasad Manchi. (violetagg)
       </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.7 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56523</bug>: When using SPNEGO authentication, log the exceptions
        associated with failed user logins at debug level rather than error
        level. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>56399</bug>: Assert that both Coyote and Catalina request objects
        have been properly recycled. (kkolinko)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56522</bug>: When setting a value for a
        <code>ValueExpression</code>, ensure that the expected coercions take
        place such as a <code>null</code> string being coerced to an empty
        string. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Copy missing resources file from Apache Commons DBCP 2 to packaged
        renamed copy of DBCP 2. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.6 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix extension validation which was broken by refactoring for new
        resources implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix custom UTF-8 decoder so that a byte of value 0xC1 is always rejected
        immediately as it is never valid in a UTF-8 byte sequence. Update UTF-8
        decoder tests to account for UTF-8 decoding improvements in Java 8.
        The custom UTF-8 decoder is still required due to bugs in the UTF-8
        decoder provided by Java. Java 8&apos;s decoder is better than Java
        7&apos;s but it is still buggy. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56027</bug>: Add more options for managing FIPS mode in the
        AprLifecycleListener. (schultz/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56320</bug>: Fix a file descriptor leak in the default servlet when
        sendfile is used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56321</bug>: When a WAR is modified, undeploy the web application
        before deleting any expanded directory as the undeploy process may
        refer to classes that need to be loaded from the expanded directory. If
        the expanded directory is deleted first, any attempt to load a new class
        during undeploy will fail. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56327</bug>: Enable AJP as well as HTTP connectors to be created
        via JMX. Patch by kiran. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56339</bug>: Avoid an infinite loop if an application calls
        <code>session.invalidate()</code> from the session destroyed event for
        that session. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>56365</bug>: Simplify file name pattern matching code in
        <code>StandardJarScanner</code>. Improve documentation. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the static resource cache is able to detect when a cache
        entry is invalidated by being overridden by a new resource in a
        different <code>WebResourceSet</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56369</bug>: Ensure that removing an MBean notification listener
        reverts all the operations performed when adding an MBean notification
        listener. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Improve implementation of <code>Lifecycle</code> for
        <code>WebappClassLoader</code>. State is now correctly reported rather
        than always reporting as <code>NEW</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>56382</bug>: Information about finished deployment and its execution
        time is added to the log files. Patch is provided by Danila Galimov.
        (violetagg)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>56383</bug>: Properties for disabling server information and error
        report are added to the <code>org.apache.catalina.valves.ErrorReportValve</code>.
        Based on the patch provided by Nick Bunn. (violetagg/kkolinko)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56390</bug>: Fix JAR locking issue with JARs containing TLDs and
        the TLD cache that prevented the undeployment of web applications when
        the WAR was deleted. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0119:
        Only create XML parsing objects if required and fix associated potential
        memory leak in the default Servlet.
        Extend XML factory, parser etc. memory leak protection to cover some
        additional locations where, theoretically, a memory leak could occur.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify generic exception handling so that
        <code>StackOverflowError</code> is not treated as a fatal error and can
        handled and/or logged as required. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56409</bug>: Avoid <code>StackOverflowError</code> on non-Windows
        systems if a file named <code>\</code> is encountered when scanning for
        TLDs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56430</bug>: Extend checks for suspicious URL patterns to include
        patterns of the form <code>*.a.b</code> which are not valid patterns for
        extension mappings. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56441</bug>: Raise the visibility of exceptions thrown when a
        problem is encountered calling a getter or setter on a component
        attribute. The logging level is raised from debug to warning. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56463</bug>: Property for disabling server information is added to
        the <code>DefaultServlet</code>. Server information is presented in the
        response sent to the client when directory listings is enabled.
        (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56472</bug>: Allow NamingContextListener to clean up on stop if its
        start failed. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56481</bug>: Work around case insensitivity issue in
        <code>URLClassLoader</code> exposed by some recent refactoring. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56492</bug>: Avoid eclipse debugger pausing on uncaught exceptions
        when tomcat renews its threads. (slaurent)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the <code>org.apache.naming</code> package to the packages requiring
        code to have the <code>defineClassInPackage</code> permission when
        running under a security manager. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Make the naming context tokens for containers more robust by using a
        separate object. Require RuntimePermission when introducing a new token.
        (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56501</bug>: <code>HttpServletRequest.getContextPath()</code>
        should return the undecoded context path used by the user agent. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Minor fixes to <code>ThreadLocalLeakPreventionListener</code>. Do not
        trigger threads renewal for failed contexts. Do not ignore
        <code>threadRenewalDelay</code> setting. Improve documentation. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct regression introduced in <rev>1239520</rev> that broke loading
        of users from <code>tomcat-users.xml</code> when using the
        <code>JAASMemoryLoginModule</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct regression introduced in <rev>797162</rev> that broke
        authentication of users when using the
        <code>JAASMemoryLoginModule</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        More cleanup of NIO2 endpoint shutdown. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56336</bug>: AJP output corruption and errors. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Handle various cases of incomplete writes in NIO2. (remm)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Code cleanups and i18n in NIO2. (remm)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Fix extra onDataAvailable calls in the NIO2 connector. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix gather writes in NIO2 SSL. (remm)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Upgrade the NIO2 connectors to beta, but still not ready for production. (remm)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Fix code duplication between NIO and NIO2. (remm)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56348</bug>: Fix slow asynchronous read when read was performed on
        a non-container thread. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56416</bug>: Correct documentation for default value of socket
        linger for the AJP and HTTP connectors. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix possible corruption if doing keepalive after a comet request. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56518</bug>: Fix connection limit latch leak when a non-container
        thread is interrupted during asynchronous processing. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56334</bug>: Fix a regression in the handling of back-slash
        escaping introduced by the fix for <bug>55735</bug>. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56425</bug>: Improve method matching for EL expressions. When
        looking for matching methods, an exact match between parameter types is
        preferred followed by an assignable match followed by a coercible match.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the handling of back-slash escaping in the EL parser and no
        longer require that <code>\$</code> or <code>\#</code> must be followed
        by <code>{</code> in order for the back-slash escaping to take effect.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove the implementation of
        <code>org.apache.catalina.LifecycleListener</code> from
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.tcp.SimpleTcpCluster</code>.
        <code>SimpleTcpCluster</code> does not work as
        <code>LifecycleListener</code>, it works as nested components of Host or
        Engine. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Remove cluster and replicationValve from cluster manager template. These
        instance are not necessary to template. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for cross context session replication to
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.BackupManager</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove the unnecessary cross context check. It does not matter whether
        the context that is referenced by other context is set to
        <code>crossContext</code>=true. The context that refers to the different
        context must be set to <code>crossContext</code>=true. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Move to <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.ClusterManagerBase</code>
        common logics of
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.BackupManager</code> and
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.DeltaManager</code>. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Simplify the code of <code>o.a.c.ha.tcp.SimpleTcpCluster</code>. In
        order to add or remove cluster valve to Container, use pipeline instead
        of <code>IntrospectionUtils</code>. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        There is no need to set cluster instance when
        <code>SimpleTcpCluster.unregisterClusterValve</code> is called.
        Set null than cluster instance for cleanup. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56343</bug>: Avoid a NPE if Tomcat&apos;s Java WebSocket 1.0
        implementation is used with the Java WebSocket 1.0 API JAR from the
        reference implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Increase the default maximum size of the executor used by the WebSocket
        implementation for call backs associated with asynchronous writes from
        10 to 200. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a warning if the thread group created for WebSocket asynchronous
        write call backs can not be destroyed when the web application is
        stopped. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that threads created to support WebSocket clients are stopped
        when no longer required. This will happen automatically for WebSocket
        client connections initiated by web applications but stand alone clients
        must call <code>WsWebSocketContainer.destroy()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56449</bug>: When creating a new session, add the message handlers
        to the session before calling <code>Endpoint.onOpen()</code> so the
        message handlers are in place should the <code>onOpen()</code> method
        trigger the sending of any messages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56458</bug>: Report WebSocket sessions that are created over secure
        connections as secure rather than as not secure. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Stop threads used for secure WebSocket client connections when they are
        no longer required and give them better names for easier debugging while
        they are running. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Add Support for <code>copyXML</code> attribute of Host to Host Manager.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that "name" request parameter is used as a application base of
        host if "webapps" request parameter is not set when adding host in
        HostManager Application. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct documentation on Windows service options, aligning it with
        Apache Commons Daemon documentation. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56418</bug>: Ensure that the Manager web application does not
        report success for a web application deployment that fails. (slaurent)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Improve valves documentation. Split valves into groups. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56513</bug>: Make the documentation crystal clear that using
        sendfile will disable any compression that Tomcat may otherwise have
        applied to the response. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Review source code and take advantage of Java 7&apos;s
        try-with-resources syntax where possible. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Align DisplayName of Tomcat installed by <code>service.bat</code> with
        one installed by the *.exe installer. Print a warning in case if neither
        server nor client jvm is found by <code>service.bat</code>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56363</bug>: Update to version 1.1.30 of Tomcat Native library.
        (schultz)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons BCEL to r1593495 to pick up some
        additional changes for Java 7 support and some code clean up. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons FileUpload to r1569132 to pick up
        some small improvements (e.g. better <code>null</code> protection) and
        some code clean up. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons Codec to r1586336 to pick up some
        Javadoc fixes and some code clean up. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Switch to including Apache Commons DBCP via a package renamed svn copy
        rather than building from a source release for consistency with other
        Commons packages and to allow faster releases to fix DBCP related
        issues. (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Update package renamed Apache Commons Pool2 and DBCP2 to r1593563 to
        pick various bug fixes. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        In tests: allow to configure directory where JUnit reports and access
        log are written to. (kkolinko)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.5 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-03-27">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Rework the fix for <bug>56190</bug> as the previous fix did not recycle
        the request in all cases leading to mis-routing of requests. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow web applications to package tomcat-jdbc.jar and their JDBC driver
        of choice in the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56293</bug>: Cache resources loaded by the class loader from
        <code>/META-INF/services/</code> for better performance for repeated
        look ups. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix possibly incomplete final flush with NIO2 when using non blocking
        mode. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Cleanup NIO2 endpoint shutdown. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix rare race condition notifying onWritePossible in the NIO2
        HTTP/1.1 connector. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>54475</bug>: Add Java 8 support to SMAP generation for JSPs. Patch
        by Robbie Gibson. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56273</bug>: If the Manager web application does not perform an
        operation because the web application is already being serviced, report
        an error rather than reporting success. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56304</bug>: Add a note to the documentation about not using
        WebSocket with BIO HTTP in production. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.4 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Restore the ability to use the <code>addURL()</code> method of the
        web application class loader to add external resources to the web
        application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the robustness of web application undeployment based on some
        code analysis triggered by the report for <bug>54315</bug>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56125</bug>: Correctly construct the URL for a resource that
        represents the root of a JAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Generate a valid root element for the effective web.xml for a web
        application for all supported versions of web.xml. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make it easier for applications embedding and/or extending Tomcat to
        modify the <code>javaseClassLoader</code> attribute of the
        <code>WebappClassLoader</code>. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Add missing support for <code>&lt;deny-uncovered-http-methods&gt;</code>
        element when merging web.xml files. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve merging process for web.xml files to take account of the
        elements and attributes supported by the Servlet version of the merged
        file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid <code>NullPointerException</code> in resource cache when making an
        invalid request for a resource outside of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove an unnecessary null check identified by FindBugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        In WebappClassLoader, when reporting threads that are still running
        while web application is being stopped, print their stack traces to
        the log. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56190</bug>: The response should be closed (i.e. no further output
        is permitted) when a call to <code>AsyncContext.complete()</code> takes
        effect. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56236</bug>: Enable Tomcat to work with alternative Servlet and
        JSP API JARs that package the XML schemas in such as way as to require
        a dependency on the JSP API before enabling validation for web.xml.
        Tomcat has no such dependency. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56244</bug>: Fix MBeans descriptor for WebappClassLoader MBean.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a work around for validating XML documents (often TLDs) that use
        just the file name to refer to refer to the JavaEE schema on which they
        are based. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add methods of get the idle time from last client access time to
        <code>org.apache.catalina.Session</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56246</bug>: Fix NullPointerException in MemoryRealm when
        authenticating an unknown user. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56248</bug>: Allow the deployer to update an existing WAR file
        without undeploying the existing application if the update flag is set.
        This allows any existing custom context.xml for the application to be
        retained. To update an application and remove any existing context.xml
        simply undeploy the old version of the application before deploying the
        new version. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56253</bug>: When listing resources that are provided by a JAR, fix
        possible <code>StringIndexOutOfBoundsException</code>s. Add some unit
        tests for this and similar scenarios and fix the additional issues those
        unit tests identified. Based on a patch by Larry Isaacs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0096:
        Redefine the <code>globalXsltFile</code> initialisation parameter of the
        DefaultServlet as relative to CATALINA_BASE/conf or CATALINA_HOME/conf.
        Prevent user supplied XSLTs used by the DefaultServlet from defining
        external entities. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In some circumstances asynchronous requests could time out too soon.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56172</bug>: Avoid possible request corruption when using the AJP
        NIO connector and a request is sent using more than one AJP message.
        Patch provided by Amund Elstad. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add experimental NIO2 connector. Based on code developed by
        Nabil Benothman. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0075:
        Improve processing of chuck size from chunked headers. Avoid overflow
        and use a bit shift instead of a multiplication as it is marginally
        faster. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0095:
        Correct regression introduced in 8.0.0-RC2 as part of the Servlet 3.1
        non-blocking IO support that broke handling of requests with an explicit
        content length of zero. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0099:
        Fix possible overflow when parsing long values from a byte array.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change the default compiler source and compiler target versions to 1.7
        since Tomcat 8 requires a minimum of Java 7. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56179</bug>: Fix parsing of EL expressions that contain unnecessary
        parentheses. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56177</bug>: Handle dependency tracking for TLDs when using JspC
        with a tag library JAR that is located outside of the web application.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove an unnecessary null check identified by FindBugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56199</bug>: Restore validateXml option for JspC which determines
        if web.xml will be parsed with a validating parser. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56223</bug>: Throw an <code>IllegalStateException</code> if a call
        is made to <code>ServletContext.setInitParameter()</code> after the
        ServletContext has been initialized. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56265</bug>: Do not escape values of dynamic tag attributes
        containing EL expressions. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make the default compiler source and target versions for JSPs Java 7
        since Tomcat 8 requires Java 7 as a minimum. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56283</bug>: Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler P20140317-1600
        which adds support for Java 8 syntax to JSPs. Add support for value
        "1.8" for the <code>compilerSourceVM</code> and
        <code>compilerTargetVM</code> options. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Avoid a possible deadlock when one thread is shutting down a connection
        while another thread is trying to write to it. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE when flushing batched messages. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>56093</bug>: Add the SSL Valve to the documentation web
        application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56217</bug>: Improve readability by using left alignment for the
        table cell containing the request information on the Manager application
        status page. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed <code>java.lang.NegativeArraySizeException</code> when using
        "Expire sessions" command in the manager web application on a
        context where the session timeout is disabled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Add support for <code>LAST_ACCESS_AT_START</code> system property to
         Manager web application. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56115</bug>: Expose the <code>httpusecaches</code> property of
        Ant&apos;s <code>get</code> task as some users may need to change the
        default. Based on a suggestion by Anthony. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56143</bug>: Improve <code>service.bat</code> so that it can be
        launched from a non-UAC console. This includes using a single call to
        <code>tomcat8.exe</code> to install the Windows service rather than
        three calls, and using command line arguments instead of environment
        variables to pass the settings. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Simplify Windows *.bat files: remove %OS% checks, as current java does
        not run on ancient non-NT operating systems. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Align options between <code>service.bat</code> and <code>exe</code>
        Windows installer. For <code>service.bat</code> the changes are in
        --Classpath, --DisplayName, --StartPath, --StopPath. For
        <code>exe</code> installer the changes are in --JvmMs, --JvmMx options,
        which are now 128 Mb and 256 Mb respectively instead of being empty.
        Explicitly specify --LogPath path when uninstalling Windows service,
        avoiding default value for that option. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56137</bug>: Explicitly use NIO connector in SSL example in
        server.xml so it doesn't break if APR is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56139</bug>: Avoid a web application class loader leak in some unit
        tests when running on Windows. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct build script to avoid building JARs with empty packages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Allow to limit JUnit test run to a number of selected test case
        methods. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update Commons Pool 2 to 2.2. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to the 2.0 release. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56189</bug>: Remove used file cpappend.bat from the distribution.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56204</bug>: Remove unnecessary dependency between tasks in the
        build script. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Add definition of <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.FindLeaksTask</code>.
         (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Implement <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.VminfoTask</code>,
         <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.ThreaddumpTask</code> and
         <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.SslConnectorCiphersTask</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
         Add the option to the Apache Ant tasks to ignore the constraint of the
         first line of the response message that must be "OK -"
         (<code>ignoreResponseConstraint</code> in <code>AbstractCatalinaTask</code>).
         Default is false. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.3 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-02-11">
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix build of Apache Commons DBCP2 classes. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to snapshot 170 dated 07 Feb 2014. This enables
        DBCP to work with a SecurityManager such that only DBCP needs to be
        granted the necessary permissions to communicate with the database.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.2 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56082</bug>: Fix a concurrency bug in JULI&apos;s LogManager
        implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56085</bug>: <code>ServletContext.getRealPath(String)</code> should
        return <code>null</code> for invalid input rather than throwing an
        <code>IllegalArgumentException</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix WebDAV support that was broken by the refactoring for the new
        resources implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Simplify Catalina.initDirs(). (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56096</bug>: When the attribute <code>rmiBindAddress</code> of the
        JMX Remote Lifecycle Listener is specified it's value will be used when
        constructing the address of a JMX API connector server. Patch is
        provided by Jim Talbut. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When environment entry with one and the same name is defined in the web
        deployment descriptor and with annotation then the one specified in the
        web deployment descriptor is with priority. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix passing the value of false for <code>xmlBlockExternal</code> option
        of Context to Jasper, as the default was changed in 8.0.1. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable non-blocking reads to take place on non-container threads.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Simplify the code of
        <code>o.a.c.ha.tcp.SimpleTcpCluster.createManager(String)</code>.
        Remove unnecessary class cast. (kfujino)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In Manager web application improve handling of file upload errors.
        Display a message instead of error 500 page. Simplify. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56104</bug>: Correct the version number on the welcome page of the
        Windows installer. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to snapshot 168 dated 05 Feb 2014. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0050, a denial of service with a malicious, malformed
        Content-Type header and multipart request processing. Fixed by merging
        latest code (r1565159) from Commons FileUpload. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.1 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-02-02">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change default value of <code>xmlBlockExternal</code> attribute of
        Context. It is <code>true</code> now. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct regression in the fix for <bug>55996</bug> that meant that
        asynchronous requests might timeout too early. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change default value of the <code>blockExternal</code> attribute of
        JspC task. The default value is <code>true</code>. Add support for
        <code>-no-blockExternal</code> switch when JspC is run as a
        standalone application. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Do not return an empty string for the
        <code>Sec-WebSocket-Protocol</code> HTTP header when no sub-protocol has
        been requested or no sub-protocol could be agreed as RFC6455 requires
        that no <code>Sec-WebSocket-Protocol</code> header is returned in this
        case. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.0 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 340 - Servlet 3.1. The JSR 340 implementation includes
        contributions from Nick Williams and Jeremy Boynes. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 245 MR2 - JSP 2.3. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 341 - Unified Expression Language 3.0. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 356 - WebSockets. The JSR 356 implementation includes
        contributions from Nick Williams, Rossen Stoyanchev and Niki Dokovski.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        <bug>46727</bug>: Refactor default servlet to make it easier to
        sub-class to implement finer grained control of the file encoding. Based
        on a patch by Fred Toth. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>45995</bug>: Align Tomcat with Apache httpd and perform MIME type
        mapping based on file extension in a case insensitive manner. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Remove duplicate code that converted a Host&apos;s appBase attribute to
        a canonical file. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        <bug>51408</bug>: Replace calls to <code>Charset.defaultCharset()</code>
        with an explicit reference to the ISO-8859-1 Charset. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Refactor initialization code to use a single, consistent approach to
        determining the Catalina home (binary) and base (instance) directories.
        The search order for home is <code>catalina.home</code> system property,
        parent of current directory if boootstrap.jar is present and finally
        current working directory. The search order for Catalina base is
        <code>catalina.base</code> system property falling back to the value for
        Catalina home. (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        <bug>52092</bug>: JULI now uses the <code>OneLineFormatter</code> and
        <code>AsyncFileHandler</code> by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>52558</bug>: Refactor <code>CometConnectionManagerValve</code> so
        that it does not prevent the session from being serialized in when
        running in a cluster. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>52767</bug>: Remove reference to MySQL specific autoReconnect
        property in <code>JDBCAccessLogValve</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Make the Mapper type-safe. Hosts, Contexts and Wrappers are no
        longer handled as plain objects, instead they keep their type.
        Code using the Mapper doesn't need to cast objects returned by
        the mapper. (rjung)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Move Manager, Loader and Resources from Container to Context since
        Context is the only place they are used. The documentation already
        states (and has done for some time) that Context is the only valid
        location for these nested components. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Move the Mapper from the Connector to the Service since the Mapper is
        identical for all Connectors of a given Service and it is common for
        there to be multiple Connectors for a Service (http, https and ajp).
        This means there is now only ever one Mapper per Service rather than
        possibly multiple identically configured Mapper objects. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove the per Context Mapper objects and use the Mapper from the
        Service. This removes the need to maintain two copies of the mappings
        for Servlets and Filters. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Implement a new Resources implementation that merges Aliases,
        VirtualLoader, VirtualDirContext, JAR resources and external
        repositories into a single framework rather than a separate one for each
        feature. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        URL rewrite valve, similar in functionality to mod_rewrite. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        Port storeconfig functionality, which can persist to server.xml and
        context.xml runtime container configuration changes. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>54095</bug>: Add support to the Default Servlet for serving
        gzipped versions of static resources directly from disk as an
        alternative to Tomcat compressing them on each request. Patch by
        Philippe Marschall. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>54708</bug>: Change the name of the working directory for the ROOT
        application (located under $CATALINA_BASE/work by default) from _ to
        ROOT. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Change default configuration so that a change to the global web.xml file
        will trigger a reload of all web applications. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55101</bug>: Make BASIC authentication more tolerant of whitespace.
        Patch provided by Brian Burch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>55166</bug>: Move JSP descriptor and tag library descriptor schemas
        to servlet-api.jar to enable relative references between the schemas to
        be correctly resolved. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor the descriptor parsing code into a separate module that can be
        used by both Catalina and Jasper. Includes patches provided by Jeremy
        Boynes. (violetagg/markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        <bug>55246</bug>: Move TLD scanning to a ServletContainerInitializer
        provided by Jasper. Includes removal of TldConfig lifecycle listener and
        associated Context properties. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>55317</bug>: Facilitate weaving by allowing ClassFileTransformer to
        be added to WebppClassLoader. Patch by Nick Williams. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55620</bug>: Enable Tomcat to start when either $CATALINA_HOME
        and/or $CATALINA_BASE contains a comma character. Prevent Tomcat from
        starting when $CATALINA_HOME and/or $CATALINA_BASE contains a semi-colon
        on Windows. Prevent Tomcat from starting when $CATALINA_HOME and/or
        $CATALINA_BASE contains a colon on Linux/FreeBSD/etc. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Initialize the JSP runtime in Jasper's initializer to avoid need for a
        Jasper-specific lifecycle listener. <code>JasperListener</code> has been
        removed. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Change ordering of elements of JMX objects names so components are
        grouped more logically in JConsole. Generally, components are now
        grouped by Host and then by Context. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Context listener to allow better EE and framework integration. (remm)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Experimental support for SPDY. Includes contributions from Sheldon Shao.
        (costin)
      </add>
      <scode>
        The default connector is now the Java NIO connector even when specifying
        HTTP/1.1 as protocol (fhanik)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Update default value of pollerThreadCount for the NIO connector. The new
        default value will never go above 2 regardless of available processors.
        (fhanik)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>54010</bug>: Remove some unnecessary code (duplicate calls to
        configure the scheme as https for AJP requests originally received over
        HTTPS). (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor char encoding/decoding using NIO APIs. (remm)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Change the default URIEncoding for all connectors from ISO-8859-1 to
        UTF-8. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Simplify API of <code>ErrorDispatcher</code> class by using varargs.
        (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Update Jasper to use the new common web.xml parsing code. Includes
        patches by Jeremy Boynes. (markt/violetagg)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Create test cases for JspC. Patch by Jeremy Boynes. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        <bug>55246</bug>: TLD scanning is now performed by JasperInitializer
        (a ServletContainerInitializer) removing the need for support within the
        Servlet container itself. The scan is now performed only once rather than
        in two passes reducing startup time. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>55251</bug>: Do not allow JspC task to fail silently if the web.xml
        or web.xml fragment can not be generated. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove unused JvmRouteSessionIDBinderListener and SessionIDMessage.
        (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Modify method signature in ReplicationValve. Cluster instance is not
        necessary to argument of method. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove unused <code>expireSessionsOnShutdown</code> attribute in
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.BackupManager</code>. (kfujino)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Extend the diagnostic information provided by the Manager web
        application to include details of the configured SSL ciphers suites for
        each connector. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        <bug>48550</bug>: Update examples web application to use UTF-8. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        <bug>55383</bug>: Improve the design and correct the HTML markup of
        the documentation web application. Patches provided by Konstantin
        Preißer. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>AbstractReplicatedMap</code> to use generics. A key
        side-effect of this is that the class now implements
        <code>Map&lt;K,V&gt;</code> rather than extends
        <code>ConcurrentMap</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove unused, deprecated code. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove static info String and associated getInfo() method where present.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        (<rev>1353242</rev>, <rev>1353410</rev>):
        Remove Ant tasks <code>jasper2</code> and <code>jkstatus</code>.
        The correct names are <code>jasper</code> and <code>jkupdate</code>.
        (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>53529</bug>: Clean-up the handling of
        <code>InterruptedException</code> throughout the code base. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>54899</bug>: Provide an initial implementation of NetBeans support.
        Patch provided by Brian Burch. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55166</bug>: Move the JSP descriptor and tag library descriptor
        schema defintion files from jsp-api.jar to servlet-api.jar so relative
        includes between the J2EE, Servlet and JSP schemas are correctly
        resolved. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>55372</bug>: When starting Tomcat with the <code>jpda</code> option
        to enable remote debugging, by default only listen on localhost for
        connections from a debugger. Prior to this change, Tomcat listened on
        all known addresses. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
