<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix/scode.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues do not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M10" rtext="in development">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59813</bug>: Ensure that circular relations of the Class-Path
        attribute from JAR manifests will be processed correctly. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that reading the <code>singleThreadModel</code> attribute of a
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> via JMX does not trigger initialisation of
        the associated servlet. With some frameworks this can trigger an
        unexpected initialisation thread and if initilisation is not thread-safe
        the initialisation can then fail. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Compatibility with rewrite from httpd for non existing headers.
        (jfclere)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in refactoring to enable injection of custom
        keystores that broke the automatic conversion of OpenSSL style PEM
        key and certificate files for use with JSSE TLS connectors. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When writing out a full web.xml file with JspC ensure that the encoding
        used in the XML prolog matches the encoding used to write the contents
        of the file. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59867</bug>: Correct the documentation provided by Manager's
        403.jsp. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid the unintended skip of <code>PoolCleaner</code>,
        remove the check code of the execution interval in the task that has
        been scheduled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59850</bug>: Ensure that the <code>ResultSet</code> is closed when
        enabling the <code>StatementCache</code> interceptor. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M9" rtext="2016-07-12">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>18500</bug>: Add limited support for wildcard host names and host
        aliases. Names of the form <code>*.domainname</code> are now permitted.
        Note that an exact host name match takes precedence over a wild card
        host name match. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>57705</bug>: Add debug logging for requests denied by the remote
        host and remote address valves and filters. Based on a patch by Graham
        Leggett. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>58588</bug> that removed the
        entire <code>org.apache.juli</code> package from the embedded JARs
        rendering them unusable. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>59399</bug>: Add a new option to the Realm implementations that
        ship with Tomcat that allows the HTTP status code used for HTTP -> HTTPS
        redirects to be controlled per Realm. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59708</bug>: Modify the LockOutRealm logic. Valid authentication
        attempts during the lock out period will no longer reset the lock out
        timer to zero. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Change the default of the
        <code>sessionCookiePathUsesTrailingSlash</code> attribute of the
        <code>Context</code> element to <code>false</code> since the problems
        caused when a Servlet is mapped to <code>/*</code> are more significant
        than the security risk of not enabling this option by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to <bug>59655</bug>. Improve the documentation for configuring
        permitted cookie names. Patch provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not attempt to start web resources during a web application's
        initialisation phase since the web application is not fully configured
        at that point and the web resources may not be correctly configured.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix a cause of multiple attempts to close the same socket. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor the certifcate keystore and trust store generation to make it
        easier for embedded users to inject their own key stores. (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Add a <code>maxConcurrentStreamExecution</code> on the HTTP/2
        protocol handler to allow restricting the amount of concurrent stream
        that are being executed in a single connection. The default is to
        not limit it. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>59233</bug>: Add the ability to add TLS virtual hosts dynamically.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correct a problem with <code>ServletRequest.getServerPort()</code> for
        secure HTTP/2 connections that meant an incorrect value was retured when
        using the default port. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Now the WebSocket implementation is not built directly on top of the
        Servlet API and can use Tomcat internals, there is no need for the
        dedicated WebSocket Executor. It has been replaced by the use of the
        Connector/Endpoint provided Executor. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Do not log an additional case of <code>IOException</code>s in the
        error handler for the Drawboard WebSocket example when the root cause is
        the client disconnecting since the logs add no value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59642</bug>: Mention the <code>localDataSource</code> in the
        <code>DataSourceRealm</code> section of the Realm How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59672</bug>: Update the security considerations page of the
        documentation web application to take account of the fact that the
        Manager and HostManager applications now have a
        <code>RemoteAddrValve</code> configured by default. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to the fix for <bug>59399</bug>. Ensure that the new attribute
        <code>transportGuaranteeRedirectStatus</code> is documented for all
        <strong>Realm</strong>s. Also document the <code>NullRealm</code> and
        when it is automatically created for an <strong>Engine</strong>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix the description of <code>maxAge</code> attribute in jdbc-pool doc.
        This attribute works both when a connection is returned and when a
        connection is borrowed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59774</bug>: Correct the <code>prefix</code> values in the the
        documented examples for configuring the <code>AccessLogValve</code>.
        Patch provided by Mike Noordermeer. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add log message when the ping has timed-out. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        If the ping message has been received at the
        <code>AbstractReplicatedMap#leftOver</code> method, ensure that notify
        the member is alive than ignore it. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix the duplicated connection release when connection verification
        failed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that do not remove the abandoned connection that has been already
        released. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove JULI plus log4j extras and embedded artifacts from Maven release
        script. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Use the mirror network rather than the ASF master site to download the
        current ASF dependencies. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.8 to
        pick up the latest fixes and make 1.2.8 the minimum recommended version.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M8" rtext="2016-06-13">
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove accidentally committed debug code. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M7" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        RMI Target related memory leaks are avoidable which makes them an
        application bug that needs to be fixed rather than a JRE bug to work
        around. Therefore, start logging RMI Target related memory leaks on web
        application stop. Add an option that controls if the check for these
        leaks is made. Log a warning if running on Java 9 with this check
        enabled but without the command line option it requires. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure NPE will not be thrown during deployment when scanning jar files
        without MANIFEST.MF file. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>clearReferencesStatic</code> option from
        <code>StandardContext</code>. It was known to cause problems with some
        libraries (such as log4j) and was only linked to suspected memory leaks
        rather than known memory leaks. It had been disabled by default with no
        increase in the reports of memory leaks for some time. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>59604</bug>: Correct the assumption made in the URL decoding that
        the default platform encoding is always compatible with ISO-8859-1. This
        assumption is not always valid, e.g. on z/OS. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59608</bug>: Skip over any invalid <code>Class-Path</code> attribute
        from JAR manifests. Log errors at debug level due to many bad libraries.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix error message when failed to register MBean. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59655</bug>: Configure the cookie name validation to use RFC6265
        rules by default to align it with the default cookie parser. Document
        the impact system properties have on cookie name validation. (mark)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that requests with HTTP method names that are not tokens (as
        required by RFC 7231) are rejected with a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When an asynchronous request is processed by the AJP connector, ensure
        that request processing has fully completed before starting the next
        request. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of HTTP/2 stream resets. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58750</bug>: The HTTP Server header is no longer set by default. A
        Server header may be configured by setting the <code>server</code>
        attribute on the <code>Connector</code>. A new <code>Connector</code>
        attribute, <code>serverRemoveAppProvidedValues</code> may be used to
        remove any Server header set by a web application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59564</bug>: Correct offset when reading into HTTP/2 input buffer
        that could cause problems reading request bodies. (violetagg/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify the handling of read/write timeouts so that the appropriate error
        handling (<code>ReadListener.onError()</code>,
        <code>WriteListener.onError()</code> or
        <code>AsycnListener.onError()</code>) is called. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
       If an async dispatch results in the completion of request processing,
       ensure that any remaining request body is swallowed before starting the
       processing of the next request else the remaining body may be read as the
       start of the next request leading to a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59567</bug>: Fix NPE scanning webapps for TLDs when an exploded
        JAR has an empty WEB-INF/classes/META-INF folder. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak in the expression language implementation that caused
        the class loader of the first web application to use expressions to be
        pinned in memory. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59654</bug>: Improve error message when attempting to use a TLD
        file from an invalid location. Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59659</bug>: Fix possible memory leak in WebSocket handling of
        unexpected client disconnects. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58891</bug>: Update the SSL how-to. Based on a suggestion by
        Alexander Kjäll. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Extras">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        <bug>58588</bug>: Remove the JULI extras package from the distribution.
        It was only useful for switching Tomcat's internal logging to log4j
        1.2.x and that version of log4j is no longer supported. No additional
        Tomcat code is required if switching Tomcat's internal logging to log
        via log4j 2.x. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak with the pool cleaner thread that retained a reference
        to the web application class loader for the first web application to use
        a connection pool. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to r1743696 (2.1.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to r1743697 (2.4.2 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons File Upload to r1743698 (1.3.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Use UTF-8 with a standard prolog for all XML files. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>58626</bug>: Add support for a new environment variable
        (<code>USE_NOHUP</code>) that causes <code>nohup</code> to be used when
        starting Tomcat. It is disabled by default except on HP-UX where it is
        enabled by default since it is required when starting Tomcat at boot on
        HP-UX. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M6" rtext="2016-05-16">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that annotated web components packed in web fragments will be
        processed when <code>unpackWARs</code> is enabled. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M5" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>48922</bug>: Apply a very small performance improvement to the
        date formatting in Tomcat's internal request object. Based on a patch
        provided by Ondrej Medek. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59206</bug>: Ensure NPE will not be thrown by
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.file.ConfigFileLoader</code> when
        <code>catalina.base</code> is not specified. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59217</bug>: Remove duplication in the recycling of the path in
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.http.ServerCookie</code>. Patch is provided by
        Kyohei Nakamura. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed possible NPE in
        <code>o.a.catalina.loader.WebappClassLoaderBase.getResourceAsStream</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59213</bug>: Async dispatches should be based off a wrapped
        request. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>javax.servlet.ServletRequest</code> and
        <code>javax.servlet.ServletResponse</code> provided during
        <code>javax.servlet.AsyncListener</code> registration are made
        available via <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedRequest</code>
        and <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedResponse</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59219</bug>: Ensure <code>AsyncListener.onError()</code> is called
        if an <code>Exception</code> is thrown during async processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59220</bug>: Ensure that <code>AsyncListener.onComplete()</code> is
        called if the async request times out and the response is already
        committed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59226</bug>: Process the <code>Class-Path</code> attribute from
        JAR manifests for JARs on the class path excluding JARs packaged in
        <code>WEB-INF/lib</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59255</bug>: Fix possible NPE in mapper. (kkolinko/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59256</bug>: <code>slf4j-taglib*.jar</code> should not be excluded
        from the standard JAR scanning by default. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify the log message that specifying both urlPatterns and value
        attributes in @WebServlet and @WebFilter annotations is not allowed.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure the exceptions caused by Valves will be available in the log
        files so that they can be evaluated when
        <code>o.a.catalina.valves.ErrorReportValve.showReport</code> is
        disabled. Patch is provided by Svetlin Zarev. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove unused <code>distributable</code> attribute that is defined as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code> of <code>Manager</code> in StoreConfig.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix handling of Cluster Receiver in StoreConfig. The <code>bind</code>
        and <code>host</code> attributes define as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59261</bug>: <code>ServletRequest.getAsyncContext()</code> now
        throws an <code>IllegalStateException</code> as required by the Servlet
        specification if the request is not in asynchronous mode when called.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59269</bug>: Correct the implementation of
        <code>PersistentManagerBase</code> so that <code>minIdleSwap</code>
        functions as designed and sessions are swapped out to keep the active
        session count below <code>maxActiveSessions</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the implementation of the the proposed Servlet 4.0 API to provide
        mapping type information for the current request to reflect discussions
        within the EG. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correctly configure the base path for a resources directory provided by
        an expanded JAR file. Patch provided by hengyunabc. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        When multiple compressed formats are available and the client does not
        express a preference, use the server order to determine the preferred
        format. Based on a patch by gmokki. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59284</bug>: Allow the Tomcat provided JASPIC
        <code>SimpleServerAuthConfig</code> to pick up module configuration
        properties from either the property set passed to its constructor or
        from the properties passed in the call to <code>getAuthContext</code>.
        Based on a patch by Thomas Maslen. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59310</bug>: Do not add a <code>Content-Length: 0</code> header for
        custom responses to <code>HEAD</code> requests that do not set a
        <code>Content-Length</code> value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When normalizing paths, improve the handling when paths end with
        <code>/.</code> or <code>/..</code> and ensure that input and output are
        consistent with respect to whether or not they end with <code>/</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59317</bug>: Ensure that
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getRequestURI()</code> returns an encoded URI
        rather than a decoded URI after a dispatch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use the correct URL for the fragment when reporting errors processing
        a <code>web-fragment.xml</code> file from a JAR located in an unpacked
        WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>JarScanner</code> only uses the explicit call-back to
        process <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and only when configured to treat
        the contents of <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> as a possible exploded JAR.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>java2DDisposerProtection</code> option from the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code>. The leak is fixed in Java
        7 onwards and Tomcat 9 requires Java 8 so the option is unnecessary.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>securityPolicyProtection</code> option from the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code>. The leak is fixed in Java
        8 onwards and Tomcat 9 requires Java 8 so the option is unnecessary.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>securityLoginConfigurationProtection</code> option from
        the <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code>. The leak is fixed in
        Java 8 onwards and Tomcat 9 requires Java 8 so the option is
        unnecessary. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the value for the header <code>X-Frame-Options</code> is
        constructed correctly according to the specification when
        <code>ALLOW-FROM</code> option is used. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> if the first use of an
        internal <code>Response</code> object requires JASPIC authentication.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not trigger unnecessary session ID changes when using JASPIC and the
        user is authenticated using cached credentials. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59437</bug>: Ensure that the JASPIC <code>CallbackHandler</code> is
        thread-safe. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59449</bug>: In <code>ContainerBase</code>, ensure that the process
        to remove a child container is the reverse of the process to add one.
        Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improves OpenSSL engine robustness when SSL allocation fails for
        some reason. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        OpenSSL engine code cleanups. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Align cipher configuration parsing with current OpenSSL master. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Change the default for <code>honorCipherOrder</code> to
        <code>false</code>. With the current default TLS configuration, it is no
        longer necessary for this to be <code>true</code> for a reasonably
        secure configuration. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add a new environment variable <code>JSSE_OPTS</code> that is intended
        to be used to pass JVM wide configuration to the JSSE implementation.
        The default value is <code>-Djdk.tls.ephemeralDHKeySize=2048</code>
        which protects against weak Diffie-Hellman keys. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58970</bug>: Fix a connection counting bug in the NIO connector
        that meant some dropped connections were not removed from the current
        connection count. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59289</bug>: Do not recycle upgrade processors in unexpected close
        situations. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Use <code>Locale.toLanguageTag()</code> to construct
        the <code>Content-Language</code> HTTP header to ensure the locale is
        correctly represented. Patch provided by zikfat. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Add support for using pem encoded certificates with
        JSSE SSL. Submitted by Emmanuel Bourg with additional tweaks. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Make the TLS certificate chain available to clients when using
        JSSE+OpenSSL with the certificate chain stored in a Java KeyStore.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Work around <a herf="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/issues/188">a
        known issue in OpenSSL</a> that does not permit the TLS handshake to be
        failed if the ALPN negotiation fails. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59421</bug>: Add direct HTTP/2 connection support. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle a call to <code>AsyncContext.complete()</code> from a
        non-container thread when non-blocking I/O is being used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59451</bug>: Correct Javadoc for <code>MessageBytes</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59450</bug>: Correctly handle the case where the
        <code>LegacyCookieProcessor</code> is configured with
        <code>allowHttpSepsInV0</code> set to <code>false</code> and
        <code>forwardSlashIsSeparator</code> set to <code>true</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When scanning JARs for TLDs, correctly handle the (rare) case where a
        JAR has been exploded into <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and the web
        application is deployed as a packed WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59640</bug>: NPEs with not found TLDs. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59189</bug>: Explicitly release the native memory held by the
        <code>Inflater</code> and <code>Deflater</code> when using
        PerMessageDeflate and the WebSocket session ends. Based on a patch by
        Henrik Olsson. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Restore the <code>WsServerContainer.doUpgrade()</code> method which was
        accidentally removed since it is not used by Tomcat. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a regression caused by the connector refactoring and ensure that the
        thread context class loader is set to the to the web application
        classloader when processing WebSocket messages on the server. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that a client disconnection triggers the error handling for the
        associated WebSocket end point. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make WebSocket client more robust when handling errors during the close
        of a WebSocket session. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59218</bug>: Correct the path to <code>jaspic-providers.xml</code>
        in Jaspic How-To. Patch is provided by Tatsuya Bessho. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove button that has accidentally been added to the host manager.
        Submitted by Coty Sutherland. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update in the documentation the link to the maven repository where
        Tomcat snapshot artifacts are deployed. (markt/violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify in the documentation that calls to
        <code>ServletContext.log(String, Throwable)</code> or
        <code>GenericServlet.log(String, Throwable)</code> are logged at the
        SEVERE level. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a typo in SSL/TLS Configuration How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE when a proxy node failed to retrieve a backup entry. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add the flag indicating that member is a localMember. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix potential NPE that depends on the setting order of attributes of
        static member when using the static cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to
        <code>ChannelInterceptor</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        As with the multicast cluster environment, in the static cluster
        environment, the local member inherits properties from the cluster
        receiver. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to each Channel
        services. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add name to channel in order to identify channels. In tomcat cluster
        environment, it is set the cluster name + "-Channel" as default value.
        (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the channel name to the thread which is invoked by channel services
        in order to identify the associated channel. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that clear the channel instance from channel services when
        stopping channel. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Implement map state in the replication map. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the ping is not executed during the start/stop of the
        replication map. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In ping processing in the replication map, send not the
        <code>INIT</code> message but the newly introduced <code>PING</code>
        message. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59211</bug>: Add hamcrest to Eclipse classpath. Patch is provided
        by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59276</bug>: Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.17.
        (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        <bug>59280</bug>: Update the NSIS Installer used to build the
        Windows Installers to version 2.51. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.7 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2h and APR
        1.5.2. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M4" rtext="2016-03-16">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>/WEB-INF/classes</code> is never processed as a web
        fragment. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Switch default connector when native is installed. Unless configured
        otherwise, the NIO endpoint will be used by default. If SSL is
        configured, OpenSSL will be used rather than JSSE. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>58867</bug>. When configuring a
        Context to use an external directory for the <code>docBase</code>, and
        that directory happens to be located along side the original WAR, use
        the directory as the <code>docBase</code> rather than expanding the
        WAR into the <code>appBase</code> and using the newly created expanded
        directory as the <code>docBase</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58351</bug>: Make the server build date and server version number
        accessible via JMX. Patch provided by  Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>58988</bug>: Special characters in the substitutions for the
        RewriteValve can now be quoted with a backslash. (fschumacher)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58999</bug>: Fix class and resource name filtering in
        WebappClassLoader. It throws a StringIndexOutOfBoundsException if the
        name is exactly "org" or "javax". (rjung)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add JASPIC (JSR-196) support. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Make checking for var and map replacement in RewriteValve a bit stricter
        and correct detection of colon in var replacement. (fschumacher)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Refactor the web application class loader to reduce the impact of JAR
        scanning on the memory footprint of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix some resource leaks in the error handling for accessing files from
        JARs and WARs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the JAR and JAR-in-WAR resource handling to reduce the memory
        footprint of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the web.xml parsing so a new parser is created every time the
        web application starts rather than creating and caching the parser when
        the Context is created. This enables the parser to take account of
        modified Context configuration parameters and reduces (slightly) the
        memory footprint of a running Tomcat instance. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Switch the web application class loader to the
        <code>ParallelWebappClassLoader</code> by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>57809</bug>: Remove the custom context attribute that held the
        effective web.xml. Components needing access to configuration
        information may access it via the Servlet API. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor JAR scanning to reduce memory footprint. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59001</bug>: Correctly handle the case when Tomcat is installed on
        a path where one of the segments ends in an exclamation mark. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Expand the fix for <bug>59001</bug> to cover the special sequences used
        in Tomcat&apos;s custom jar:war: URLs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59043</bug>: Avoid warning while expiring sessions associated with
        a single sign on if <code>HttpServletRequest.logout()</code> is used.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59054</bug>: Ensure that using the
        <code>CrawlerSessionManagerValve</code> in a distributed environment
        does not trigger an error when the Valve registers itself in the
        session. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add socket properties support to storeconfig. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix incorrect parsing of the NE and NC flags in rewrite rules. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59065</bug>: Correct the timing of the check for colons in paths
        on non-Windows systems implemented in <code>catalina.sh</code> so it
        works correctly with Cygwin. Patch provided by Ed Randall. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When a Host is configured with an appBase that does not exist, create
        the appBase before trying to expand an external WAR file into it.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
       <bug>59115</bug>: When using the Servlet 3.0 file upload, the submitted
       file name may be provided as a token or a quoted-string. If a
       quoted-string, unquote the string before returning it to the user.
       (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59123</bug>: Close <code>NamingEnumeration</code> objects used by
        the <code>JNDIRealm</code> once they are no longer required.
        (fschumacher/markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Implement the proposed Servlet 4.0 API to provide mapping type
        information for the current request. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59138</bug>: Correct a false positive warning for ThreadLocal
        related memory leaks when the key class but not the value class has been
        loaded by the web application class loader. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>59017</bug>: Make the pre-compressed file support in the Default
        Servlet generic so any compression may be used rather than just gzip.
        Patch provided by Mikko Tiihonen. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59145</bug>: Don't log an invalid warning when a user logs out of
        a session associated with SSO. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59150</bug>: Add an additional flag on APR listener to allow
        disabling automatic use of OpenSSL. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59151</bug>: Fix a regression in the fix for <bug>56917</bug> that
        added additional (and arguably unnecessary) validation to the provided
        redirect location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59154</bug>: Fix a <code>NullPointerException</code> in the
        <code>JAASMemoryLoginModule</code> resulting from the introduction of
        the <code>CredentialHandler</code> to <code>Realm</code>s.
        (schultz/markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Handle the case in the NIO2 connector where the required TLS buffer
        sizes increase after the connection has been initiated. (markt/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Bad processing of handshake errors in NIO2. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use JSSE session configuration options with OpenSSL. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59015</bug>: Fix potential cause of endless APR Poller loop during
        shutdown if the Poller experiences an error during the shutdown process.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Align cipher aliases for <code>kECDHE</code> and <code>ECDHE</code> with
        the current OpenSSL implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59081</bug>: Retain the user defined cipher order when defining
        ciphers. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59089</bug>: Correctly ignore HTTP headers that include non-token
        characters in the header name. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>57583</bug>: Improve the performance of
        <code>javax.servlet.jsp.el.ScopedAttributeELResolver</code> when
        resolving attributes that do not exist. This improvement only works when
        Jasper is used with with Tomcat's EL implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix a timing issue on session close that could result in an exception
        being thrown for an incomplete message even through the message was
        completed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle compression of partial messages when the final message
        fragment has a zero length payload. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59119</bug>: Correct read logic for WebSocket client when using
        secure connections. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59134</bug>: Correct client connect logic for secure connections
        made through a proxy. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct an error in the documentation of the expected behaviour for
        automatic deployment. If a WAR is updated and an expanded directory is
        present, the directory will always be deleted and recreated by expanding
        the WAR if <code>unpackWARs</code> is <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>48674</bug>: Implement an option within the Host Manager web
        application to persist the current configuration. Based on a patch by
        Coty Sutherland. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58935</bug>: Remove incorrect references in the documentation to
        using <code>jar:file:</code> URLs with the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the description of the
        <code>ServletRequest.getServerPort()</code> in Proxy How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <add>
        The Manager and Host Manager applications are now only accessible via
        <code>localhost</code> by default. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        If promoting a proxy node to a primary node when getting a session,
        notify the change of the new primary node to the original backup node.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58283</bug>: Change the default download location for libraries
        during the build process from <code>/usr/share/java</code> to
        <code>${user.home}/temp</code>. Patch provided by Ahmed Hosni. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59031</bug>: When using the Windows uninstaller, do not remove the
        contents of any directories that have been symlinked into the Tomcat
        directory structure. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.5 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2g and APR
        1.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Modify the default <code>tomcat-users.xml</code> file to make it harder
        for users to configure the entries intended for use with the examples
        web application for the Manager application. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M3" rtext="2016-02-05">
  <subsection name="General">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Allow to configure multiple JUnit test class patterns with the build
        property <code>test.name</code> and document the property in
        BUILDING.txt. (rjung)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Protect initialization of <code>ResourceLinkFactory</code> when
        running with a SecurityManager. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a thread safety issue in the filtering of session attributes
        based on the implementing class name of the value object. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix class loader decision on the delegation for class loading and
        resource lookup and make it faster too. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58768</bug>: Log a warning if a redirect fails because of an
        invalid location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>58827</bug>: Remove remains of JSR-77 implementation. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>58946</bug>: Ensure that the request parameter map remains
        immutable when processing via a RequestDispatcher. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58905</bug>: Ensure that <code>Tomcat.silence()</code> silences the
        correct logger and respects the current setting. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the connector refactoring in 9.0.0.M2 that broke
        TLS support for the APR/native connector. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct an NPE when listing the enabled ciphers (e.g. via the Manager
        web application) for a TLS enabled APR/native connector. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        New configuration option <code>ajpFlush</code> for the AJP connectors
        to disable the sending of AJP flush packets. (rjung)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Handle the case in the NIO connector where the required TLS buffer sizes
        increase after the connection has been initiated. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M2" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor creation of <code>MapperListener</code> to ensure that the
        <code>Mapper</code> used is the <code>Mapper</code> associated with the
        <code>Service</code> for which the listener was created. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Move the functionality that provides redirects for context roots and
        directories where a trailing <code>/</code> is added from the Mapper to
        the <code>DefaultServlet</code>. This enables such requests to be
        processed by any configured Valves and Filters before the redirect is
        made. This behaviour is configurable via the
        <code>mapperContextRootRedirectEnabled</code> and
        <code>mapperDirectoryRedirectEnabled</code> attributes of the Context
        which may be used to restore the previous behaviour. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>Service.getContainer()</code> to return an
        <code>Engine</code> rather than a <code>Container</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>34319</bug>: Only load those keys in <code>StoreBase.processExpire</code>
        from JDBCStore, that are old enough, to be expired. Based on a patch
        by Tom Anderson. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56917</bug>: As per RFC7231 (HTTP/1.1), allow HTTP/1.1 and later
        redirects to use relative URIs. This is controlled by a new attribute
        <code>useRelativeRedirects</code> on the <strong>Context</strong> and
        defaults to <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58629</bug>: Allow an embedded Tomcat instance to start when the
        <code>Service</code> has no <code>Engine</code> configured. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly notify the MapperListener associated with a Service if the
        Engine for that Service is changed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make a web application's CredentialHandler available through a context
        attribute. This allows a web application to use the same algorithm
        for validating or generating new stored credentials from cleartext
        ones. (schultz)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58635</bug>: Enable break points to be set within agent code when
        running Tomcat with a Java agent. Based on a patch by Huxing Zhang.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed potential NPE in <code>HostConfig</code> while deploying an
        application. Issue reported by coverity scan. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58655</bug>: Fix an <code> IllegalStateException</code> when
        calling <code>HttpServletResponse.sendRedirect()</code> with the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code>. This was caused by trying to correctly
        generate the absolute URI for the redirect. With the fix for
        <bug>56917</bug>, redirects may now be relative making the
        <code>sendRedirect()</code> implementation for the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code> much simpler. This also addresses issues
        where the redirect may not have behaved as expected when redirecting
        from http to https to from https to http. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58657</bug>: Exceptions in a Servlet 3.1 <code>ReadListener</code>
        or <code>WriteListener</code> do not need to be immediately fatal to the
        connection. Allow an error response to be written. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct implementation of
        <code>validateClientProvidedNewSessionId</code> so client provided
        session IDs may be rejected if validation is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58701</bug>: Reset the <code>instanceInitialized</code> field in
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> when unloading a Servlet so that a new
        instance may be correctly initialized. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Add a new flag <code>aprPreferred</code> to the Apr listener. if set to
        <code>false</code>, when using the connector defaults, it will use
        NIO + OpenSSL if tomcat-native is available, rather than the APR
        connector. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Add path parameter handling to
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getContextPath()</code>. This is a follow-up to
        the fix for <bug>57215</bug>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58692</bug>: Make <code>StandardJarScanner</code> more robust. Log
        a warning if a class path entry cannot be scanned rather than triggering
        the failure of the web application. Includes a test case written by
         Derek Abdine. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58702</bug>: Ensure an access log entry is generated if the client
        aborts the connection. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed various issues reported by Findbugs. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58735</bug>: Add support for the <code>X-XSS-Protection</code>
        header to the <code>HttpHeaderSecurityFilter</code>. Patch provided by
        Jacopo Cappellato. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add the <code>StatusManagerServlet</code> to the list of Servlets that
        can only be loaded by privileged applications. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Simplify code and fix messages in
        <code>org.apache.catalina.core.DefaultInstanceManager</code> class.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58751</bug>: Correctly handle the case where an
        <code>AsyncListener</code> dispatches to a Servlet on an asynchronous
        timeout and the Servlet uses <code>sendError()</code> to trigger an
        error page. Includes a test case based on code provided by Andy
        Wilkinson.(markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the proper file encoding if specified will be used when
        a readme file is served by DefaultServlet. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix declaration of <code>localPort</code> attribute of Connector MBean:
        it is read-only. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58766</bug>: Make skipping non-class files during annotation
        scanning faster by checking the file name first. Improve debug logging.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58836</bug>: Correctly merge query string parameters when
        processing a forwarded request where the target includes a query string
        that contains a parameter with no value. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make sure that shared Digester is reset in an unlikely error case
        in <code>HostConfig.deployWAR()</code>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Extend the feature available in the cluster session manager
        implementations that enables session attribute replication to be
        filtered based on attribute name to all session manager implementations.
        Note that configuration attribute name has changed from
        <code>sessionAttributeFilter</code> to
        <code>sessionAttributeNameFilter</code>. Apply the filter on load as
        well as unload to ensure that configuration changes made while the web
        application is stopped are applied to any persisted data. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Extend the session attribute filtering options to include filtering
        based on the implementation class of the value and optional
        <code>WARN</code> level logging if an attribute is filtered. These
        options are available for all of the Manager implementations that ship
        with Tomcat. When a <code>SecurityManager</code> is used filtering will
        be enabled by default. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Remove <code>distributable</code> and <code>maxInactiveInterval</code>
        from the <code>Manager</code> interface because the attributes are never
        used. The equivalent attributes from the <code>Context</code> always
        take precedence. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>58867</bug>: Improve checking on Host start for WAR files that have
        been modified while Tomcat has stopped and re-expand them if
        <code>unpackWARs</code> is <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58900</bug>: Correctly undeploy symlinked resources and prevent an
        infinite cycle of deploy / undeploy. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58621</bug>: The certificate chain cannot be set using the main
        certificate attribute, so restore the certificate chain property. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow a new SSL config type where a connector can use either JSSE or
        OpenSSL. Both could be allowed, but it would likely create support
        issues. This type is used by the OpenSSL implementation for NIOx. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve upgrade context classloader handling by using Context.bind and
        unbind. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Improve OpenSSL keystore/truststore configuration by using the code
        from the JSSE implementation. (remm, jfclere)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix a potential loop when a client drops the connection unexpectedly.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        OpenSSL renegotiation support for client certificate authentication.
        (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix NIO connector renegotiation. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58659</bug>: Fix a potential deadlock during HTTP/2 processing when
        the connection window size is limited. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>57136#c25</bug>: Change default value of
        <code>quoteAttributeEL</code> setting in Jasper to be <code>true</code>
        for better compatibility with other implementations and older versions
        of Tomcat. Add command line option <code>-no-quoteAttributeEL</code> in
        JspC. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix handling of missing messages in
        <code>org.apache.el.util.MessageFactory</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable an explicit configuration of local member in the static cluster
        membership. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>DeltaSession</code>.
        Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid that the heartbeat thread and the background thread to
        run <code>Channel.heartbeat</code> simultaneously, if
        <code>heartbeatBackgroundEnabled</code> of <code>SimpleTcpCluster</code>
        set to <code>true</code>, ensure that the heartbeat thread does not
        start. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>55006</bug>: The WebSocket client now honors the
        <code>java.net.java.net.ProxySelector</code> configuration (using the
        HTTP type) when establishing WebSocket connections to servers. Based on
        a patch by Niki Dokovski. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58624</bug>: Correct a potential deadlock if the WebSocket
        connection is closed when a message write is in progress. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>57489</bug>: Ensure <code>onClose()</code> is called when a
        WebSocket connection is closed even if the sending of the close message
        fails. Includes test cases by Barry Coughlan. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58631</bug>: Correct the continuation character use in the Windows
        Service How-To page of the documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the SSL documentation for deprecated attributes to point to the
        correct, new location for attributes related to individual certificates.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct some typos in the JNDI resources How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Host Manager application.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58723</bug>: Clarify documentation and error messages for the text
        interface of the manager to make clear that version must be used with
        path when referencing contexts deployed using parallel deployment.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Document <code>test.threads</code> option in BUILDING.txt. (kkolinko)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the static member is registered to the add suspect list even
        if the static member that is registered to the remove suspect list has
        disappeared. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When using a static cluster, add the members that have been cached in
        the membership service to the map members list in order to ensure that
        the map member is a static member. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for the startup notification of local members in the static
        cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ignore the unnecessary member remove operation from different domain.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for the shutdown notification of local members in the static
        cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct evaluation of system property
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.jdbc.pool.onlyAttemptCurrentClassLoader</code>.
        It was basically ignored before. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>ConnectionPool</code> and
        <code>PooledConnection</code>. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.14.1. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.4 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2e and APR
        1.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows Installers to
        version 2.50. (markt/kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons BCEL to r1725718 to align with the
        refactoring for BCEL 6, the next major BCEL release. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to r1725730 (2.1.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to r1725738 (2.4.2 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Codec to r1725746 (1.9 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M1" rtext="2015-11-17">
  <subsection name="General">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Make Java 8 the minimum required version to build and run Tomcat 9.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Remove support for Comet. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Tighten up the default file permissions for the <code>.tar.gz</code>
        distribution so no files or directories are world readable by default.
        Configure Tomcat to run with a default umask of <code>0027</code> which
        may be overridden by setting <code>UMASK</code> in
        <code>setenv.sh</code>. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove native code (Windows Service Wrapper, APR/native connector)
        support for Windows Itanium. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        The default HTTP cookie parser has been changed to
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.http.Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove support for the HTTP BIO and AJP BIO connectors. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor HTTP upgrade and AJP implementations to reduce duplication.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Add support for HPACK header encoding and decoding, contributed
        by Stuart Douglas. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>57108</bug>: Add support for Server Name Indication (SNI). There
        has been significant changes to the SSL configuration in server.xml to
        support this. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add SSL engine for JSSE backed by OpenSSL. Includes ALPN support.
        Based on code contributed by Numa de Montmollin and derived from code
        developed by Twitter and Netty. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        RFC 7230 states that clients should ignore reason phrases in HTTP/1.1
        response messages. Since the reason phrase is optional, Tomcat no longer
        sends it. As a result the system property
        <code>org.apache.coyote.USE_CUSTOM_STATUS_MSG_IN_HEADER</code> is no
        longer used and has been removed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        The minimum required Tomcat Native version has been increased to 1.2.2.
        The 1.2.x branch includes ALPN and SNI support which are required for
        HTTP/2. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add support for HTTP/2 including server push. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Clarify the handling of Copy message and Copy nodes. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Support the use of the <code>threads</code> attribute on Ant&apos;s
        junit task. Note that using this with a value of greater than one will
        disable Cobertura code coverage. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
