<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix/scode.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues do not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M2">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor creation of <code>MapperListener</code> to ensure that the
        <code>Mapper</code> used is the <code>Mapper</code> associated with the
        <code>Service</code> for which the listener was created. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Move the functionality that provides redirects for context roots and
        directories where a trailing <code>/</code> is added from the Mapper to
        the <code>DefaultServlet</code>. This enables such requests to be
        processed by any configured Valves and Filters before the redirect is
        made. This behaviour is configurable via the
        <code>mapperContextRootRedirectEnabled</code> and
        <code>mapperDirectoryRedirectEnabled</code> attributes of the Context
        which may be used to restore the previous behaviour. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>Service.getContainer()</code> to return an
        <code>Engine</code> rather than a <code>Container</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>34319</bug>: Only load those keys in <code>StoreBase.processExpire</code>
        from JDBCStore, that are old enough, to be expired. Based on a patch
        by Tom Anderson. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>56917</bug>: As per RFC7231 (HTTP/1.1), allow HTTP/1.1 and later
        redirects to use relative URIs. This is controlled by a new attribute
        <code>useRelativeRedirects</code> on the <strong>Context</strong> and
        defaults to <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58629</bug>: Allow an embedded Tomcat instance to start when the
        <code>Service</code> has no <code>Engine</code> configured. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly notify the MapperListener associated with a Service if the
        Engine for that Service is changed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make a web application's CredentialHandler available through a context
        attribute. This allows a web application to use the same algorithm
        for validating or generating new stored credentials from cleartext
        ones. (schultz)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58635</bug>: Enable break points to be set within agent code when
        running Tomcat with a Java agent. Based on a patch by Huxing Zhang.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed potential NPE in <code>HostConfig</code> while deploying an
        application. Issue reported by coverity scan. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58655</bug>: Fix an <code> IllegalStateException</code> when
        calling <code>HttpServletResponse.sendRedirect()</code> with the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code>. This was caused by trying to correctly
        generate the absolute URI for the redirect. With the fix for
        <bug>56917</bug>, redirects may now be relative making the
        <code>sendRedirect()</code> implementation for the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code> much simpler. This also addresses issues
        where the redirect may not have behaved as expected when redirecting
        from http to https to from https to http. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58657</bug>: Exceptions in a Servlet 3.1 <code>ReadListener</code>
        or <code>WriteListener</code> do not need to be immediately fatal to the
        connection. Allow an error response to be written. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct implementation of
        <code>validateClientProvidedNewSessionId</code> so client provided
        session IDs may be rejected if validation is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58701</bug>: Reset the <code>instanceInitialized</code> field in
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> when unloading a Servlet so that a new
        instance may be correctly initialized. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Add a new flag <code>aprPreferred</code> to the Apr listener. if set to
        <code>false</code>, when using the connector defaults, it will use
        NIO + OpenSSL if tomcat-native is available, rather than the APR
        connector. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Add path parameter handling to
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getContextPath()</code>. This is a follow-up to
        the fix for <bug>57215</bug>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58692</bug>: Make <code>StandardJarScanner</code> more robust. Log
        a warning if a class path entry cannot be scanned rather than triggering
        the failure of the web application. Includes a test case written by
         Derek Abdine. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58702</bug>: Ensure an access log entry is generated if the client
        aborts the connection. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58621</bug>: The certificate chain cannot be set using the main
        certificate attribute, so restore the certificate chain property. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow a new SSL config type where a connector can use either JSSE or
        OpenSSL. Both could be allowed, but it would likely create support
        issues. This type is used by the OpenSSL implementation for NIOx. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve upgrade context classloader handling by using Context.bind and
        unbind. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Improve OpenSSL keystore/truststore configuration by using the code
        from the JSSE implementation. (remm, jfclere)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix a potential loop when a client drops the connection unexpectedly.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        OpenSSL renegotiation support for client certificate authentication.
        (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix NIO connector renegotiation. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58659</bug>: Fix a potential deadlock during HTTP/2 processing when
        the connection window size is limited. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>57136#c25</bug>: Change default value of
        <code>quoteAttributeEL</code> setting in Jasper to be <code>true</code>
        for better compatibility with other implementations and older versions
        of Tomcat. Add command line option <code>-no-quoteAttributeEL</code> in
        JspC. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable an explicit configuration of local member in the static cluster
        membership. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>DeltaSession</code>.
        Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid that the heartbeat thread and the background thread to
        run <code>Channel.heartbeat</code> simultaneously, if
        <code>heartbeatBackgroundEnabled</code> of <code>SimpleTcpCluster</code>
        set to <code>true</code>, ensure that the heartbeat thread does not
        start. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>55006</bug>: The WebSocket client now honors the
        <code>java.net.java.net.ProxySelector</code> configuration (using the
        HTTP type) when establishing WebSocket connections to servers. Based on
        a patch by Niki Dokovski. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58624</bug>: Correct a potential deadlock if the WebSocket
        connection is closed when a message write is in progress. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>57489</bug>: Ensure <code>onClose()</code> is called when a
        WebSocket connection is closed even if the sending of the close message
        fails. Includes test cases by Barry Coughlan. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58631</bug>: Correct the continuation character use in the Windows
        Service How-To page of the documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the SSL documentation for deprecated attributes to point to the
        correct, new location for attributes related to individual certificates.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct some typos in the JNDI resources How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Host Manager application.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the static member is registered to the add suspect list even
        if the static member that is registered to the remove suspect list has
        disappeared. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When using a static cluster, add the members that have been cached in
        the membership service to the map members list in order to ensure that
        the map member is a static member. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for the startup notification of local members in the static
        cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ignore the unnecessary member remove operation from different domain.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct evaluation of system property <code>org.apache.tomcat.jdbc.pool.onlyAttemptCurrentClassLoader</code>.
        It was basically ignored before. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>ConnectionPool</code> and
        <code>PooledConnection</code>. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.13. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.3 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2e and APR
        1.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows Installers to
        version 2.49. (markt/kkolinko)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 9.0.0.M1" rtext="2015-11-17">
  <subsection name="General">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Make Java 8 the minimum required version to build and run Tomcat 9.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Remove support for Comet. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Tighten up the default file permissions for the <code>.tar.gz</code>
        distribution so no files or directories are world readable by default.
        Configure Tomcat to run with a default umask of <code>0027</code> which
        may be overridden by setting <code>UMASK</code> in
        <code>setenv.sh</code>. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove native code (Windows Service Wrapper, APR/native connector)
        support for Windows Itanium. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        The default HTTP cookie parser has been changed to
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.http.Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove support for the HTTP BIO and AJP BIO connectors. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor HTTP upgrade and AJP implementations to reduce duplication.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Add support for HPACK header encoding and decoding, contributed
        by Stuart Douglas. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>57108</bug>: Add support for Server Name Indication (SNI). There
        has been significant changes to the SSL configuration in server.xml to
        support this. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add SSL engine for JSSE backed by OpenSSL. Includes ALPN support.
        Based on code contributed by Numa de Montmollin and derived from code
        developed by Twitter and Netty. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        RFC 7230 states that clients should ignore reason phrases in HTTP/1.1
        response messages. Since the reason phrase is optional, Tomcat no longer
        sends it. As a result the system property
        <code>org.apache.coyote.USE_CUSTOM_STATUS_MSG_IN_HEADER</code> is no
        longer used and has been removed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        The minimum required Tomcat Native version has been increased to 1.2.2.
        The 1.2.x branch includes ALPN and SNI support which are required for
        HTTP/2. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add support for HTTP/2 including server push. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Clarify the handling of Copy message and Copy nodes. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Support the use of the <code>threads</code> attribute on Ant&apos;s
        junit task. Note that using this with a value of greater than one will
        disable Cobertura code coverage. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
