<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix/scode.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues do not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.29 (markt)" rtext="in development">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Minor optimization when calling class transformers. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Prevent Tomcat from applying gzip compression to content that is already
        compressed with brotli compression. Based on a patch provided by burka.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62090</bug>: Null container names are not allowed. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62104</bug>: Fix programmatic login regression as the
        NonLoginAuthenticator has to be set for it to work (if no login method
        is specified). (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62117</bug>: Improve error message in <code>catalina.sh</code> when
        calling <code>kill -0 &lt;pid&gt;</code> fails. Based on a suggestion
        from Mark Morschhaeuser. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62118</bug>: Correctly create a JNDI <code>ServiceRef</code> using
        the specified interface rather than the concrete type. Based on a
        suggestion by Ángel Álvarez Páscua. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix for <code>RequestDumperFilter</code> log attribute. Patch provided
        by Kirill Romanov via Github. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62123</bug>: Avoid <code>ConcurrentModificationException</code>
        when attempting to clean up application triggered RMI memory leaks on
        web application stop. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Add minor HPACK fixes, based on fixes by Stuart Douglas. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61751</bug>: Follow up fix so that OpenSSL engine returns
        underflow when unwrapping if no bytes were produced and the input is
        empty. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Minor OpenSSL engine cleanups. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        NIO SSL handshake should throw an exception on overflow status, like
        NIO2 SSL. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>48672</bug>: Add documentation for the Host Manager web
        application. Patch provided by Marek Czernek. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.28 (markt)" rtext="2018-02-11">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Prevent a stack trace being written to standard out when running on Java
        10 due to changes in the <code>LogManager</code> implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62000</bug>: When a JNDI reference cannot be resolved, ensure that
        the root cause exception is reported rather than swallowed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62036</bug>: When caching an authenticated user Principal in the
        session when the web application is configured with the
        <code>NonLoginAuthenticator</code>, cache the internal Principal object
        rather than the user facing Principal object as Tomcat requires the
        internal object to correctly process later authorization checks. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid duplicate load attempts if one has been made already. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE in ThreadLocalLeakPreventionListener if there is no Engine.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62067</bug>: Correctly apply security constraints mapped to the
        context root using a URL pattern of <code>&quot;&quot;</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When using Tomcat embedded, only perform Authenticator configuration
        once during web application start. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Process all <code>ServletSecurity</code> annotations at web application
        start rather than at servlet load time to ensure constraints are applied
        consistently. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61751</bug>: Fix truncated request input streams when using NIO2
        with TLS. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62023</bug>: Log error reporting multiple SSLHostConfig elements
        when using the APR Connector instead of crashing Tomcat. (csutherl)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62032</bug>: Fix NullPointerException when certificateFile is not
        defined on an SSLHostConfig and unify the behavior when a
        certificateFile is defined but the file does not exist for both
        JKS and PEM file types. (csutherl)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>62024</bug>: When closing a connection with an abnormal close,
        close the socket immediately rather than waiting for a close message
        from the client that may never arrive. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Webapps">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>62049</bug>: Fix missing class from manager 404 JSP error page.
        (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Enhance the JMX support for jdbc-pool in order to expose
        <code>PooledConnection</code> and <code>JdbcInterceptors</code>.
        (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add MBean for <code>PooledConnection</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>62011</bug>: Add MBean for <code>StatementCache</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Expose the cache size for each connection via JMX in
        <code>StatementCache</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add MBean for <code>ResetAbandonedTimer</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows installer to version
        3.03. (kkolinko)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.27 (markt)" rtext="2018-01-22">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the previous fix for <bug>61916</bug> that meant
        that any call to <code>addHeader()</code> would have been replaced with
        a call to <code>setHeader()</code> for all requests mapped to the
        <code>AddDefaultCharsetFilter</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61993</bug>: Improve handling for <code>ByteChunk</code> and
        <code>CharChunk</code> instances that grow close to the maximum size
        allowed by the JRE. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>43925</bug>: Add a new system property
        (<code>org.apache.jasper.runtime.BodyContentImpl.BUFFER_SIZE</code>) to
        control the size of the buffer used by Jasper when buffering tag bodies.
        (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>62006</bug>: Document the new <code>JvmOptions9</code> command line
        parameter for <code>tomcat8.exe</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.26 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct Javadoc errors in release build.
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.25 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>47214</bug>: Use a loop to preload anonymous inner classes
        when running under a <code>SecurityManager</code>, to be safe for
        future changes in the code or using a different compiler. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>57619</bug>: Implement a small optimisation to how JAR URLs are
        processed to reduce the storage of duplicate String objects in memory.
        Patch provided by Dmitri Blinov. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Add some missing NPEs to ServletContext. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61916</bug>: Extend the <code>AddDefaultCharsetFilter</code> to add
        a character set when the content type is set via
        <code>setHeader()</code> or <code>addHeader()</code> as well as when it
        is set via <code>setContentType()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61999</bug>: maxSavePostSize set to 0 should disable saving POST
        data during authentication. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>60276</bug>: Implement GZIP compression support for responses
        served over HTTP/2. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Do not call onDataAvailable without any data to read. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61886</bug>: Log errors on non-container threads at
        <code>DEBUG</code> rather than <code>INFO</code>. The exception will be
        made available to the application via the asynchronous error handling
        mechanism. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61914</bug>: Possible NPE with Java 9 when creating a SSL engine.
        Patch submitted by Evgenij Ryazanov. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61918</bug>: Fix connectionLimitLatch counting when closing an
        already closed socket. Based on a patch by Ryan Fong. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add support for the OpenSSL ARIA ciphers to the OpenSSL to JSSE
        cipher mapping. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61932</bug>: Allow a call to <code>AsyncContext.dispatch()</code>
        to terminate non-blocking I/O. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61948</bug>: Improve the handling of malformed ClientHello messages
        in the code that extracts the SNI information from a TLS handshake for
        the JSSE based NIO and NIO2 connectors. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix NIO2 handshaking with a full input buffer. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Return a simple, plain text error message if a client attempts to make a
        plain text HTTP connection to a TLS enabled NIO or NIO2 Connector.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle EOF when <code>ServletInputStream.isReady()</code> is
        called. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61854</bug>: When using sets and/or maps in EL expressions, ensure
        that Jasper correctly parses the expression. Patch provided by Ricardo
        Martin Camarero. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the handling of methods with varargs in EL expressions. In
        particular, the calling of a varargs method with no parameters now works
        correctly. Based on a patch by Nitkalya (Ing) Wiriyanuparb. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove the Servlet 4.0 early preview example from the examples web
        application as the early preview is now deprecated in favour of Tomcat
        9 which provides a full Servlet 4.0 implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61223</bug>: Add the mbeans-descriptors.dtd file to the custom
        MBean documentation so users have a reference to use when constructing
        mbeans-descriptors.xml files for custom components. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>61566</bug>: Expose the currently in use certificate chain and list
        of trusted certificates for all virtual hosts configured using the JSSE
        style (keystore) TLS configuration via the Manager web application.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Partial fix for <bug>61886</bug>. Ensure that multiple threads do not
        attempt to complete the <code>AsyncContext</code> if an I/O error occurs
        in the stock ticker example Servlet. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61886</bug>: Prevent <code>ConcurrentModificationException</code>
        when running the asynchronous stock ticker in the examples web
        application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61886</bug>: Prevent <code>NullPointerException</code> and other
        errors if the stock ticker example is running when the examples web
        application is stopped. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61910</bug>: Clarify the meaning of the <code>allowLinking</code>
        option in the documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add OCSP configuration information to the SSL How-To. Patch provided by
        Marek Czernek. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61312</bug>: Prevent <code>NullPointerException</code> when using
        the statement cache of connection that has been closed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Add an additional system property for the system property replacement.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add missing SHA-512 hash for release artifacts to the build script.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to 2.4.3. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to 8a71764 (2017-10-18) to
        pick up some bug fixes and enhancements. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons FileUpload to 6c00d57 (2017-11-23)
        to pick up some code clean-up. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Codec to r1817136 to pick up some
        code clean-up. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        The native source bundles (for Commons Daemon and Tomcat Native) are no
        longer copied to the bin directory for the deploy target. They are now
        only copied to the bin directory for the release target. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.24 (markt)" rtext="2017-11-30">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        When running under Java 9 or later, and the
        <code>urlCacheProtection</code> option of the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code> is enabled, use the API
        added in Java 9 to only disable the caching for JAR URL connections.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix possible <code>SecurityException</code> when using TLS related
        request attributes. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61597</bug>: Extend the <code>StandardJarScanner</code> to scan
        JARs on the module path when running on Java 9 and class path scanning
        is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61601</bug>: Add support for multi-release JARs in JAR scanning and
        web application class loading. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61681</bug>: Allow HTTP/2 push when using request wrapping. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Provide the <code>SessionInitializerFilter</code> that can be used to
        ensure that an HTTP session exists when initiating a WebSocket
        connection. Patch provided by isapir. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61682</bug>: When re-prioritising HTTP/2 streams, ensure that both
        parent and children fields are correctly updated to avoid a possible
        <code>StackOverflowError</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve concurrency by reducing the scope of the synchronisation for
        <code>javax.security.auth.message.config.AuthConfigFactory</code> in the
        JASPIC API implementation. Based on a patch by Pavan Kumar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid a possible <code>NullPointerException</code> when timing out
        <code>AsyncContext</code> instances during shut down. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61777</bug>: Avoid a <code>NullPointerException</code> when
        detaching a JASPIC <code>RegistrationListener</code>. Patch provided by
        Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61778</bug>: Correct the return value when detaching a JASPIC
        <code>RegistrationListener</code>. Patch provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61779</bug>: Avoid a <code>NullPointerException</code> when a
        <code>null</code> <code>RegistrationListener</code> is passed to
        <code>AuthConfigFactory.getConfigProvider()</code>. Patch provided by
        Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61780</bug>: Only include the default JASPIC registration ID in the
        return value for a call to
        <code>AuthConfigFactory.getRegistrationIDs()</code> if a
        <code>RegistrationContext</code> has been registered using the default
        registration ID. Patch provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61781</bug>: Enable JASPIC provider registrations to be persisted
        when the layer and/or application context are <code>null</code>. Patch
        provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61782</bug>: When calling
        <code>AuthConfigFactory.doRegisterConfigProvider()</code> and the
        requested JASPIC config provider class is found by the web application
        class loader, do not attempt to load the class with the class loader
        that loaded the JASPIC API. Patch provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61783</bug>: When calling
        <code>AuthConfigFactory.removeRegistration()</code> and the registration
        is persistent, it should be removed from the persistent store. Patch
        provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61784</bug>: Correctly handle the case when
        <code>AuthConfigFactoryImpl.registerConfigProvider()</code> is called
        with a provider name of <code>null</code>. Patch provided by Lazar.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61795</bug>: Add a property to the <code>Authenticator</code>
        implementations to enable a custom JASPIC <code>CallbackHandler</code>
        to be specified. Patch provided by Lazar. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Enable ALPN and also, therefore, HTTP/2 for the NIO and NIO2 HTTP
        connectors when using the JSSE implementation for TLS when running on
        Java 9. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>60762</bug>: Add the ability to make changes to the TLS
        configuration of a connector at runtime without having to restart the
        Connector. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61568</bug>: Avoid a potential <code>SecurityException</code> when
        using the NIO2 connector and a new thread is added to the pool. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61583</bug>: Correct a further regression in the fix to enable the
        use of Java key stores that contained multiple keys that did not all
        have the same password. This fixes PKCS11 key store handling with
        multiple keys selected with an alias. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Reduce default HTTP/2 stream concurrent execution within a connection
        from 200 to 20. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61668</bug>: Avoid a possible NPE when calling
        <code>AbstractHttp11Protocol.getSSLProtocol()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61673</bug>: Avoid a possible
        <code>ConcurrentModificationException</code> when working with the
        streams associated with a connection. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61719</bug>: Avoid possible NPE calling
        InputStream.setReadListener with HTTP/2. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61736</bug>: Improve performance of NIO connector when clients
        leave large time gaps between network packets. Patch provided by Zilong
        Song. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61740</bug>: Correct an off-by-one error in the Hpack header index
        validation that caused intermittent request failures when using HTTP/2.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61816</bug>: Invalid expressions in attribute values or template
        text should trigger a translation (compile time) error, not a run time
        error. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61604</bug>: Add support for authentication in the websocket
        client. Patch submitted by J Fernandez. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable Javadoc to be built with Java 9. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61603</bug>: Add XML filtering for the status servlet output where
        needed. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the description of how the CGI servlet maps a request to a
        script in the CGI How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix incorrect behavior that attempts to resend channel messages more
        than the actual setting value of <code>maxRetryAttempts</code>.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the remaining Sender can send channel messages by avoiding
        unintended <code>ChannelException</code> caused by comparing the number
        of failed members and the number of remaining Senders. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that remaining SelectionKeys that were not handled by throwing a
        <code>ChannelException</code> during SelectionKey processing are
        handled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve the fix for <bug>61439</bug> and exclude the JPA, JAX-WS and EJB
        annotations completely from the Tomcat distributions. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of endorsed directories. The endorsed directory
        mechanism will only be used if the <code>JAVA_ENDORSED_DIRS</code>
        system property is explicitly set or if
        <code>$CATALINA_HOME/endorsed</code> exists. When running on Java 9, any
        such attempted use of the endorsed directory mechanism will trigger an
        error and Tomcat will fail to start. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactoring in preparation for Java 9. Refactor to avoid using some
        methods that will be deprecated in Java 9 onwards. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>51496</bug>: When using the Windows installer, check if the
        requested service name already exists and, if it does, prompt the user
        to select an alternative service name. Patch provided by Ralph
        Plawetzki. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Add necessary Java 9 configuration options to the startup scripts to
        prevent warnings being generated on web application stop. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61590</bug>: Enable <code>service.bat</code> to recognise when
        <code>JAVA_HOME</code> is configured for a Java 9 JDK. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61598</bug>: Update the Windows installer to search the new (as of
        Java 9) registry locations when looking for a JRE. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add generation of a SHA-512 hash for release artifacts to the build
        script. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61658</bug>: Update MIME mappings for fonts to use
        <code>font/*</code> as per RFC8081. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.16 to
        pick up the latest Windows binaries built with APR 1.6.3 and OpenSSL
        1.0.2m. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows installer to version
        3.02.1. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the Windows installer to use "The Apache Software Foundation" as
        the Publisher when Tomcat is displayed in the list of installed
        applications in Microsoft Windows. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>61803</bug>: Remove outdated SSL information from the Security
        documentation. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.23 (markt)" rtext="2017-10-01">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Use the correct path when loading the JVM <code>logging.properties</code>
        file for Java 9. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add additional validation to the resource handling required to fix
        CVE-2017-12617 on Windows. The checks were being performed elsewhere but
        adding them to the resource handling ensures that the checks are always
        performed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61554</bug>: Exclude test files in unusual encodings and markdown
        files intended for display in GitHub from RAT analysis. Patch provided
        by Chris Thistlethwaite. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61563</bug>: Correct typos in Spanish translation. Patch provided by
        Gonzalo Vásquez. (csutherl)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.22 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60963</bug>: Add <code>ExtractingRoot</code>, a new
        <code>WebResourceRoot</code> implementation that extracts JARs to the
        work directory for improved performance when deploying packed WAR files.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add an option to reject requests that contain HTTP headers with invalid
        (non-token) header names with a 400 response. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61542</bug>: Fix CVE-2017-12617 and prevent JSPs from being
        uploaded via a specially crafted request when HTTP PUT was enabled.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Implement the requirements of RFC 7230 (and RFC 2616) that HTTP/1.1
        requests must include a <code>Host</code> header and any request that
        does not must be rejected with a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Implement the requirements of RFC 7230 that any HTTP/1.1 request that
        specifies a host in the request line, must specify the same host in the
        <code>Host</code> header and that any such request that does not, must
        be rejected with a 400 response. This check is optional but disabled by
        default. It may be enabled with the
        <code>allowHostHeaderMismatch</code> attribute of the Connector. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Implement the requirements of RFC 7230 that any HTTP/1.1 request that
        contains multiple <code>Host</code> headers is rejected with a 400
        response. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Add a way to set the property source in embedded mode. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>61557</bug>: Correct a further regression in the fix to enable the
        use of Java key stores that contain multiple keys that do not all have
        the same password. The regression broke support for some FIPS compliant
        key stores. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61545</bug>: Correctly handle invocations of methods defined in the
        <code>PooledConnection</code> interface when using pooled XA
        connections. Patch provided by Nils Winkler. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Update fix for <bug>59904</bug> so that values less than zero are accepted
        instead of throwing a NegativeArraySizeException. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.21 (markt)" rtext="2017-09-19">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Before generating an error page in the <code>ErrorReportValve</code>,
        check to see if I/O is still permitted for the associated connection
        before generating the error page so that the page generation can be
        skipped if the page is never going to be sent. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61189</bug>: Add the ability to set environment variables for
        individual CGI scripts. Based on a patch by jm009. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61210</bug>: When running under a SecurityManager, do not print a
        warning about not being able to read a logging configuration file when
        that file does not exist. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61280</bug>: Add RFC 7617 support to the
        <code>BasicAuthenticator</code>. Note that the default configuration
        does not change the existing behaviour. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61424</bug>: Avoid a possible <code>StackOverflowError</code> when
        running under a <code>SecurityManager</code> and using
        <code>Subject.doAs()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        The minimum required Tomcat Native version has been increased to 1.2.14.
        This version includes a new API needed for correct client certificate
        support when using a Java connector with OpenSSL TLS implementation and
        support for the <code>SSL_CONF</code> OpenSSL API. (rjung)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add support for the OpenSSL <code>SSL_CONF</code> API when using
        TLS with OpenSSL implementation. It can be used by adding
        <code>OpenSSLConf</code> elements underneath <code>SSLHostConfig</code>.
        The new element contains a list of <code>OpenSSLConfCmd</code> elements,
        each with the attributes <code>name</code> and <code>value</code>.
        (rjung)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When using a Java connector in combination with the OpenSSL TLS
        implementation, do not configure each SSL connection object via
        the OpenSSLEngine. For OpenSSL the SSL object inherits its
        settings from the SSL_CTX which we have already configured.
        (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When using JSSE TLS configuration with the OpenSSL implementation and
        client certificates: include client CA subjects in the TLS handshake
        so that the client can choose an appropriate client certificate to
        present. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        If an invalid option is specified for the
        <code>certificateVerification</code> attribute of an
        <code>SSLHostConfig</code> element, treat it as <code>required</code>
        which is the most secure / restrictive option in addition to reporting
        the configuration error. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the handling of client disconnections during the TLS
        renegotiation handshake. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Prevent exceptions being thrown during normal shutdown of NIO
        connections. This enables TLS connections to close cleanly. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix possible race condition when setting IO listeners on an upgraded
        connection. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>48655</bug>: Enable Tomcat to shutdown cleanly when using sendfile,
        the APR/native connector and a multi-part download is in progress.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58244</bug>: Handle the case when OpenSSL resumes a TLS session
        using a ticket and the full client certificate chain is not available.
        In this case the client certificate without the chain will be presented
        to the application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the warning message when JSSE and OpenSSL configuration styles
        are mixed on the same <code>SSLHostConfig</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61415</bug>: Fix TLS renegotiation with OpenSSL based connections
        and session caching. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Delay checking that the configured attributes for an
        <code>SSLHostConfig</code> instance are consistent with the configured
        SSL implementation until <code>Connector</code> start to avoid incorrect
        warnings when the SSL implementation changes during initialisation.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61450</bug>: Fix default key alias algorithm. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61451</bug>: Correct a regression in the fix to enable the use of
        Java key stores that contained multiple keys that did not all have the
        same password. The regression broke support for any key store that did
        not store keys in PKCS #8 format such as hardware key stores and Windows
        key stores. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60523</bug>: Reduce the number of packets used to send WebSocket
        messages by not flushing between the header and the payload when the
        two are written together. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61491</bug>: When using the <code>permessage-deflate</code>
        extension, correctly handle the sending of empty messages after
        non-empty messages to avoid the <code>IllegalArgumentException</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Show connector cipher list in the manager web application in the
        correct cipher order. (rjung)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        To avoid unexpected session timeout notification from backup session,
        update the access time when receiving the map member notification
        message. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add member info to the log message when the failure detection check
        fails in <code>TcpFailureDetector</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid Ping timeout until the added map member by receiving
        <code>MSG_START</code> message is completely started. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When sending a channel message, make sure that the Sender has connected.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the backup node selection logic that node 0 is returned twice
        consecutively. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix race condition of <code>responseMap</code> in
        <code>RpcChannel</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61391</bug>: Ensure that failed queries are logged if the
        <code>SlowQueryReport</code> interceptor is configured to do so and the
        connection has been abandoned. Patch provided by Craig Webb. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61425</bug>: Ensure that transaction of idle connection has
        terminated  when the <code>testWhileIdle</code> is set to
        <code>true</code> and <code>defaultAutoCommit</code> is set to
        <code>false</code>. Patch provided by WangZheng. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61439</bug>: Remove the Java Annotation API classes from
        tomcat-embed-core.jar and package them in a separate JAR in the
        embedded distribution to provide end users with greater flexibility to
        handle potential conflicts with the JRE and/or other JARs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61441</bug>: Improve the detection of <code>JAVA_HOME</code> by the
        <code>daemon.sh</code> script when running on a platform where Java has
        been installed from an RPM. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.14 to
        pick up the latest Windows binaries built with APR 1.6.2 and OpenSSL
        1.0.2l. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        <bug>61599</bug>: Update to Commons Daemon 1.1.0 for improved Java 9
        support. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.20 (markt)" rtext="2017-08-08">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Revert the fix for <bug>49464</bug> since it continued to trigger
        regressions. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a bug in the <code>PushBuilder</code> implementation that
        meant push URLs containing <code>%nn</code> sequences were not correctly
        decoded. Identified by FindBugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61164</bug>: Add support for the <code>%X</code> pattern in the
        <code>AccessLogValve</code> that reports the connection status at the
        end of the request. Patch provided by Zemian Deng. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61351</bug>: Correctly handle %nn decoding of URL patterns in
        web.xml and similar locations that may legitimately contain characters
        that are not permitted by RFC 3986. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61366</bug>: Add a new attribute, <code>localDataSource</code>, to
        the <code>JDBCStore</code> that allows the Store to be configured to use
        a DataSource defined by the web application rather than the default of
        using a globally defined DataSource. Patch provided by Jonathan
        Horowitz. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61086</bug>: Ensure to explicitly signal an empty request body for
        HTTP 205 responses. Additional fix to r1795278. Based on a patch
        provided by Alexandr Saperov. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>61345</bug>: Add a server listener that can be used to do system
        property replacement from the property source configured in the
        digester. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add additional logging to record problems that occur while waiting for
        the NIO pollers to stop during the Connector stop process. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61364</bug>: Ensure that files are closed after detecting encoding
        of JSPs so that files do not remain locked by the file system. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>57767</bug>: Add support to the WebSocket client for following
        redirects when attempting to establish a WebSocket connection. Patch
        provided by J Fernandez. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.19 (markt)" rtext="2017-07-28">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Performance improvements for service loader look-ups (and look-ups of
        other class loader resources) when the web application is deployed in a
        packed WAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61253</bug>: Add warn message when Digester.updateAttributes
        throws an exception instead of ignoring it. (csutherl)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a further regression in the fix for <bug>49464</bug> that could
        cause an byte order mark character to appear at the start of content
        included by the <code>DefaultServlet</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61313</bug>: Make the read timeout configurable in the
        <code>JNDIRealm</code> and ensure that a read timeout will result in an
        attempt to fail over to the alternateURL. Based on patches by Peter
        Maloney and Felix Schumacher. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct the documentation for how <code>StandardRoot</code> is
        configured. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61316</bug>: Fix corruption of UTF-16 encoded source files in
        released source distributions. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.18 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61232</bug>: When log rotation is disabled only one separator will
        be used when generating the log file name. For example if the prefix is
        <code>catalina.</code> and the suffix is <code>.log</code> then the log
        file name will be <code>catalina.log</code> instead of
        <code>catalina..log</code>. Patch provided by Katya Stoycheva.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61264</bug>: Correct a regression in the refactoring to use
        <code>Charset</code> rather than <code>String</code> to store request
        character encoding that prevented <code>getReader()</code> throwing an
        <code>UnsupportedEncodingException</code> if the user agent specifies
        an unsupported character encoding. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>49464</bug> that could cause an
        incorrect <code>Content-Length</code> header to be sent by the
        <code>DefaultServlet</code> if the encoding of a static is not
        consistent with the encoding of the response. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable TLS connectors to use Java key stores that contain multiple keys
        where each key has a separate password. Based on a patch by Frank
        Taffelt. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the handling of HTTP/2 stream resets due to excessive headers
        when a continuation frame is used. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>53031</bug>: Add support for the <code>fork</code> option when
        compiling JSPs with the Jasper Ant task and javac. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>52791</bug>: Add the ability to set the defaults used by the
        Windows installer from a configuration file. Patch provided by Sandra
        Madden. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.17 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>49464</bug>: Improve the Default Servlet's handling of static files
        when the file encoding is not compatible with the required response
        encoding. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61214</bug>: Remove deleted attribute <code>servlets</code> from
        the Context MBean description. Patch provided by Alexis Hassler. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61215</bug>: Correctly define <code>addConnectorPort</code> and
        <code>invalidAuthenticationWhenDeny</code> in the
        <code>mbean-descriptors.xml</code> file for the
        <code>org.apache.catalina.valves</code> package so that the attributes
        are accessible via JMX. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make asynchronous error handling more robust. In particular ensure that
        <code>onError()</code> is called for any registered
        <code>AsyncListener</code>s after an I/O error on a non-container
        thread. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Additional permission for deleting files is granted to JULI as it is
        required by FileHandler when running under a Security Manager. The
        thread that cleans the log files is marked as daemon thread.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61229</bug>: Correct a regression in 8.5.15 that broke WebDAV
        handling for resources with names that included a <code>&amp;</code>
        character. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Restore the ability to configure support for SSLv3. Enabling this
        protocol will trigger a warning in the logs since it is known to be
        insecure. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not log a warning when a <code>null</code> session is returned for an
        OpenSSL based TLS session since this is expected when session tickets
        are enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When the access log valve logs a TLS related request attribute and the
        NIO2 connector is used with OpenSSL, ensure that the TLS attributes are
        available to the access log valve when the connection is closing.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60461</bug>: Sync SSL session access for the APR connector. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        To ease migration from 8.0.x to 8.5.x, if the HTTP or AJP BIO connector
        is explicitly configured, rather than failing to start the connector
        because BIO has been removed, automatically switch to NIO and continue.
        A warning will be logged to alert the user to the switch. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove references to the Loader attribute
        <code>searchExternalFirst</code> from the documentation since the
        attribute is no longer supported. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.16 (markt)" rtext="2017-06-26">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61072</bug>: Respect the documentation statements that allow
        using the platform default secure random for session id generation.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the javadoc for
        <code>o.a.c.connector.CoyoteAdapter#parseSessionCookiesId</code>.
        Patch provided by John Andrew (XUZHOUWANG) via Github. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61101</bug>: CORS filter should set Vary header in response.
        Submitted by Rick Riemer. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61105</bug>: Add a new JULI FileHandler configuration for
        specifying the maximum number of days to keep the log files.
        (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61125</bug>: Ensure that <code>WarURLConnection</code> returns the
        correct value for calls to <code>getLastModified()</code> as this is
        required for the correct detection of JSP modifications when the JSP is
        packaged in a WAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the <code>SSLValve</code> so it is able to handle client
        certificate headers from Nginx. Based on a patch by Lucas Ventura Carro.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61134</bug>: Do not use '[' and ']' symbols around substituted
        text fragments when generating the default error pages. Patch provided
        by Katya Todorova. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61154</bug>: Allow the Manager and Host Manager web applications to
        start by default when running under a security manager. This was
        accomplished by adding a custom permission,
        <code>org.apache.catalina.security.DeployXmlPermission</code>, that
        permits an application to use a <code>META-INF/context.xml</code> file
        and then granting that permission to the Manager and Host Manager.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61173</bug>: Polish the javadoc for
        <code>o.a.catalina.startup.Tomcat</code>. Patch provided by
        peterhansson_se. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <add>
        A new configuration property <code>crawlerIps</code> is added to the
        <code>o.a.catalina.valves.CrawlerSessionManagerValve</code>. Using this
        property one can specify a regular expression that will be used to
        identify crawlers based on their IP address. Based on a patch provided
        by Tetradeus. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>61180</bug>: Log a warning message rather than an information
        message if it takes more than 100ms to initialised a
        <code>SecureRandom</code> instance for a web application to use to
        generate session identifiers. Patch provided by Piotr Chlebda. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61185</bug>: When an asynchronous request is dispatched via
        <code>AsyncContext.dispatch()</code> ensure that
        <code>getRequestURI()</code> for the dispatched request matches that of
        the original request. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61197</bug>: Ensure that the charset name used in the
        <code>Content-Type</code> header has exactly the same form as that
        provided by the application. This reverts a behavioural change in
        8.5.15 that caused problems for some clients. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61201</bug>: Ensure that the <code>SCRIPT_NAME</code> environment
        variable for CGI executables is populated in a consistent way regardless
        of how the CGI servlet is mapped to a request. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61086</bug>: Explicitly signal an empty request body for HTTP 205
        responses. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61120</bug>: Do not ignore path parameters when processing HTTP/2
        requests. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Revert a change introduced in the fix for bug <bug>60718</bug> that
        changed the status code recorded in the access log when the client
        dropped the connection from 200 to 500. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add additional syncs to the SSL session object provided by the OpenSSL
        engine so that a concurrent destruction cannot cause a JVM crash.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61195</bug>: Backport, with deprecation where appropriate, the
        endpoint and protocol property changes from 9.0.x to ease migration from
        8.5.x to 9.0.x. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>44787</bug>: Improve error message when JSP compiler configuration
        options are not valid. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61137</bug>: <code>j.s.jsp.tagext.TagLibraryInfo#uri</code> and
        <code>j.s.jsp.tagext.TagLibraryInfo#prefix</code> fields should not be
        final. Patch provided by Katya Todorova. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct the log message when a <code>MessageHandler</code> for
        <code>PongMessage</code> does not implement
        <code>MessageHandler.Whole</code>. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Introduce new API <code>o.a.tomcat.websocket.WsSession#suspend</code>/
        <code>o.a.tomcat.websocket.WsSession#resume</code> that can be used to
        suspend/resume reading of the incoming messages. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Improve thread-safety of <code>Future</code>s used to report the result
        of sending WebSocket messages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61183</bug>: Correct a regression in the previous fix for
        <bug>58624</bug> that could trigger a deadlock depending on the locking
        strategy employed by the client code. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Better document the meaning of the trimSpaces option for Jasper. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61150</bug>: Configure the Manager and Host-Manager web
        applications to permit serialization and deserialization of
        CRSFPreventionFilter related session objects to avoid warning messages
        and/or stack traces on web application stop and/or start when running
        under a security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the TLS configuration documentation to remove SSLv2 and SSLv3
        from the list of supported protocols. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add JMX support for Tribes components. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>45832</bug>: Add HTTP DIGEST authentication support to the Catalina
        Ant tasks used to communicate with the Manager application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>45879</bug>: Add the <code>RELEASE-NOTES</code> file to the root of
        the installation created by the Tomcat installer for Windows to make it
        easier for users to identify the installed Tomcat version. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61055</bug>: Clarify the code comments in the rewrite valve to make
        clear that there are no plans to provide proxy support for this valve
        since Tomcat does not have proxy capabilities. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61076</bug>: Document the <code>altDDName</code> attribute for the
        <code>Context</code> element. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct typo in Jar Scan Filter Configuration Reference.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61145</bug>: Add missing <code>@Documented</code> annotation to
        annotations in the annotations API. Patch provided by Katya Todorova.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>61146</bug>: Add missing <code>lookup()</code> method to
        <code>@EJB</code> annotation in the annotations API. Patch provided by
        Katya Todorova. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct typo in Context Container Configuration Reference.
        Patch provided by Katya Todorova. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.15 (markt)" rtext="2017-05-10">
  <subsection name="General">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Allow to exclude JUnit test classes using the build property
        <code>test.exclude</code> and document the property in
        BUILDING.txt. (rjung)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Review those places where Tomcat re-encodes a URI or URI component and
        ensure that that correct encoding (path differs from query string) is
        applied and that the encoding is applied consistently. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid a <code>NullPointerException</code> when reading attributes for a
        initialised HTTP connector where TLS is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Always quote the <code>hostName</code> of an <code>SSLHostConfig</code>
        element when using it as part of the JMX object name to avoid errors that
        prevent the associated TLS connector from starting if a wild card
        <code>hostName</code> is configured (because <code>*</code> is a
        reserved character for JMX object names). (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Switch to using <code>Charset</code> rather than <code>String</code> to
        store encoding settings (including for configuration and for the
        <code>Content-Type header</code>) to reduce the number of places the
        associated <code>Charset</code> needs to be looked up. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Use a more reliable mechanism for the <code>DefaultServlet</code> when
        determining if the current request is for custom error page or not.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that when the Default or WebDAV servlets process an error
        dispatch that the error resource is processed via the
        <code>doGet()</code> method irrespective of the method used for the
        original request that triggered the error. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        If a static custom error page is specified that does not exist or cannot
        be read, ensure that the intended error status is returned rather than a
        404 or 403. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When the WebDAV servlet is configured and an error dispatch is made to a
        custom error page located below <code>WEB-INF</code>, ensure that the
        target error page is displayed rather than a 404 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>61047</bug>: Add MIME mapping for woff2 fonts in the default
        web.xml. Patch provided by Justin Williamson. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correct the logic that selects the encoding to use to decode the query
        string in the <code>SSIServletExternalResolver</code> so that the
        <code>useBodyEncodingForURI</code> attribute of the
        <code>Connector</code> is correctly taken into account. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Within the Expires filter, make the content type value specified with the
        <code>ExpiresByType</code> parameter, case insensitive. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When a <code>TrustManager</code> is configured that does not support
        <code>certificateVerificationDepth</code> only log a warning about that
        lack of support when <code>certificateVerificationDepth</code> has been
        explicitly set. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60970</bug>: Extend the fix for large headers to push requests.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not include a <code>Date</code> header in HTTP/2 responses with
        status codes less than 200. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When no BOM is present and an encoding is detected, do not skip the
        bytes used to detect the encoding since they are not part of a BOM.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>61057</bug>: Update to Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.6.3. (violetagg)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>61065</bug>: Ensure that once the class is resolved by
        <code>javax.el.ImportHandler#resolveClass</code> it will be cached with
        the proper name. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>61003</bug>: Ensure the flags for reading/writing in
        <code>o.a.t.websocket.AsyncChannelWrapperSecure</code> are correctly
        reset even if some exceptions occurred during processing. (markt/violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add documents for <code>maxIdleTime</code> attribute to Channel Receiver
        docs. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Modify the Ant build script used to publish to a Maven repository so
        that it no longer requires artifacts to be GPG signed. This is make it
        possible for the CI system to upload snapshot builds to the ASF Maven
        repository. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Review i18n property files, remove unnecessary escaping and consistently
        use <code>[...]</code> to delimit inserted values. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.14 (markt)" rtext="2017-04-18">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59825</bug>: Log a message that lists the components in the
        processing chain that do not support async processing when a call to
        <code>ServletRequest.startAsync()</code> fails. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60926</bug>: Ensure
        <code>o.a.c.core.ApplicationContextFacade#setSessionTimeout</code> will
        invoke the correct method when running Tomcat with security manager.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the early access Servlet 4.0 API implementation to reflect the
        change in method name from <code>getPushBuilder()</code> to
        <code>newPushBuilder()</code>. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the X to comma refactoring that broke JMX
        operations that take parameters. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid a <code>NullPointerException</code> when reading attributes for a
        running HTTP connector where TLS is not enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60940</bug>: Improve the handling of the <code>META-INF/</code> and
        <code>META-INF/MANIFEST.MF</code> entries for Jar files located in
        <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> when running a web application from a packed
        WAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Pre-load the <code>ExceptionUtils</code> class. Since the class is used
        extensively in error handling, it is prudent to pre-load it to avoid any
        failure to load this class masking the true problem during error
        handling. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid potential <code>NullPointerException</code>s related to access
        logging during shutdown, some of which have been observed when running
        the unit tests. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When there is no <code>javax.servlet.WriteListener</code> registered
        then a call to <code>javax.servlet.ServletOutputStream#isReady</code>
        will return <code>false</code> instead of throwing
        <code>IllegalStateException</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When there is no <code>javax.servlet.ReadListener</code> registered
        then a call to <code>javax.servlet.ServletInputStream#isReady</code>
        will return <code>false</code> instead of throwing
        <code>IllegalStateException</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Align cipher configuration parsing with current OpenSSL master. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60970</bug>: Fix infinite loop if application tries to write a
        large header to the response when using HTTP/2. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60925</bug>: Improve the handling of access to properties defined
        by interfaces when a <code>BeanELResolver</code> is used under a
        <code>SecurityManager</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor the creating a constructor for a proxy class to reduce
        duplicate code. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        In <code>StatementFacade</code>, the method call on the statements that
        have been closed throw <code>SQLException</code> rather than
        <code>NullPointerException</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct comments about Java 8 in <code>Jre8Compat</code>.
        Patch provided by fibbers via Github. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60932</bug>: Correctly escape single quotes when used in i18n
        messages. Based on a patch by Michael Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update the custom Ant task that integrates with the Symantec code
        signing service to use the now mandatory 2-factor authentication.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.13 (markt)" rtext="2017-03-30">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>54618</bug>: Add support to the
        <code>HttpHeaderSecurityFilter</code> for the HSTS preload parameter.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60853</bug>: Expose the <code>SSLHostConfig</code> and
        <code>SSLHostConfigCertificate</code> objects via JMX. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60876</bug>: Ensure that <code>Set-Cookie</code> headers generated
        by the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code> are aligned with the
        specification. Patch provided by Jim Griswold. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60882</bug>: Fix a <code>NullPointerException</code> when obtaining
        a <code>RequestDispatcher</code> for a request that will not have any
        pathInfo associated with it. This was a regression in the changes in
        8.5.12 for the Servlet 4.0 API early preview changes. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Align <code>PushBuilder</code> API with changes from Servlet expert
        group. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor the various implementations of X to comma separated list to a
        single utility class and update the code to use the new utility class.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>60911</bug>: Ensure NPE will not be thrown when looking for SSL
        session ID. Based on a patch by Didier Gutacker. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>60362</bug>: Add a new Connector configuration
        <code>sendReasonPhrase</code>. When this attribute is set to
        <code>true</code>, a reason phrase will be sent with the response.
        By default a reason phrase will not be sent. This option is deprecated
        and is not available in Tomcat 9. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix HTTP/2 incorrect input unblocking on EOF. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Close the connection sooner if an event occurs for a current connection
        that is not consistent with the current state of that connection.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Speed up shutdown when using multiple acceptor threads by ensuring that
        the code that unlocks the acceptor threads correctly handles the case
        where there are multiple threads. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60852</bug>: Correctly spell compressible when used in
        configuration attributes and internal code. Based on a patch by Michael
        Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60900</bug>: Avoid a <code>NullPointerException</code> in the APR
        Poller if a connection is closed at the same time as new data arrives on
        that connection. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve HPACK specification compliance by fixing some test failures
        reported by the h2spec tool written by Moto Ishizawa. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve HTTP/2 specification compliance by fixing some test failures
        reported by the h2spec tool written by Moto Ishizawa. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60918</bug>: Fix sendfile processing error that could lead to
        subsequent requests experiencing an <code>IllegalStateException</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve sendfile handling when requests are pipelined. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve the error handling for simple tags to ensure that the tag is
        released and destroyed once used. (remm, violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60844</bug>: Correctly handle the error when fewer parameter values
        than required by the method are used to invoke an EL method expression.
        Patch provided by Daniel Gray. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60764</bug>: Implement <code>equals()</code> and
        <code>hashCode()</code> in the <code>StatementFacade</code> in order to
        enable these methods to be called on the closed statements if any
        statement proxy is set. This behavior can be changed with
        <code>useStatementFacade</code> attribute. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Refactor the build script and the NSIS installer script so that either
        NSIS 2.x or NSIS 3.x can be used to build the installer. This is
        primarily to re-enable building the installer on the Linux based CI
        system where the combination of NSIS 3.x and wine leads to failed
        installer builds. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.12 (markt)" rtext="2017-03-13">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60469</bug>: Refactor <code>RealmBase</code> for better code re-use
        when implementing Realms that use a custom <code>Principal</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60490</bug>: Various formatting and layout improvements for the
        <code>ErrorReportValve</code>. Patch provided by Michael Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>60596</bug>: Improve performance of DefaultServlet when sendfile
        feature is disabled on connector. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Make it easier for sub-classes of <code>Tomcat</code> to modify the
        default web.xml settings by over-riding
        <code>getDefaultWebXmlListener()</code>. Patch provided by Aaron
        Anderson. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Reduce the contention in the default <code>InstanceManager</code>
        implementation when multiple threads are managing objects and need to
        reference the annotation cache. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>60674</bug>: Remove <code>final</code> marker from
        <code>CorsFilter</code> to enable sub-classing. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>60683</bug>: Security manager failure causing NPEs when doing IO
        on some JVMs. (csutherl)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60688</bug>: Update the internal fork of Apache Commons BCEL to
        r1782855 to add early access Java 9 support to the annotation scanning
        code. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60694</bug>: Prevent NPE during authentication when no JASPIC
        <code>AuthConfigFactory</code> is available. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60697</bug>: When HTTP TRACE requests are disabled on the
        Connector, ensure that the HTTP OPTIONS response from custom servlets
        does not include TRACE in the returned Allow header. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60718</bug>: Improve error handling for asynchronous processing and
        correct a number of cases where the <code>requestDestroyed()</code>
        event was not being fired and an entry wasn't being made in the access
        logs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60720</bug>: Replace "WWW-Authenticate" literal with static final
        AUTH_HEADER_NAME in SpnegoAuthenticator. Patch provided by Michael
        Osipov. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        The default JASPIC <code>AuthConfigFactory</code> now correctly notifies
        registered <code>RegistrationListener</code>s when a new
        <code>AuthConfigProvider</code> is registered. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Improve the performance of <code>AuthenticatorBase</code> when there is
        no JASPIC configuration available. (violetagg)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        When HTTP TRACE requests are disabled on the Connector, ensure that the
        HTTP OPTIONS response from the WebDAV servlet does not include
        TRACE in the returned Allow header. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60722</bug>: Take account of the
        <strong>dispatchersUseEncodedPaths</strong> setting on the current
        <strong>Context</strong> when generating paths for dispatches triggered
        by <code>AsyncContext.dispatch()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60728</bug>: Make the separator Tomcat uses in the Tomcat specific
        <code>war:file:...</code> URL protocol customizable via a system
        property. The separator is equivalent to the use of the <code>!</code>
        character in <code>jar:file:...</code> URLs. The default separator of
        <code>*</code> remains unchanged. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the <code>org.apache.catalina.servlet4preview</code> package that
        can be used to gain early access to Servlet 4.0 features to align with
        the latest proposals from the Servlet 4.0 expert group. This includes
        updates to the new Servlet mapping API, new methods on the
        <code>ServletContext</code> to make the available API more equivalent to
        the deployment descriptor, updates to the HTTP push API and the ability
        to set default request and response character encoding per web
        application. Note that the Servlet 4.0 API is still a work in progress
        and further changes are likely. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>60798</bug>: Correct a bug in the handling of JARs in unpacked WARs
        that meant multiple attempts to read the same entry from a JAR in
        succession would fail for the second and subsequent attempts. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60808</bug>: Ensure that the <code>Map</code> returned by
        <code>ServletRequest.getParameterMap()</code> is fully immutable. Based
        on a patch provided by woosan. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60824</bug>: Correctly cache the <code>Subject</code> in the
        session - if there is a session - when running under a
        <code>SecurityManager</code>. Patch provided by Jan Engehausen. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure request and response facades are used when firing application
        listeners. (markt/remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of case when an HTTP/2 client sends more data that is
        subject to flow control than the current window size allows. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve NIO2 look-ahead parsing of TLS client hello for SNI with large
        client hello messages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59807</bug>: Provide a better error message when there is no
        <strong>SSLHostConfig</strong> defined with a <code>hostName</code> that
        matches the <code>defaultSSLHostConfigName</code> for the associated
        <strong>Connector</strong>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Include the value of <code>SslHostConfig.truststoreAlgorithm</code> when
        warning that the algorithm does not support the
        <code>certificateVerificationDepth</code> configuration option. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that executor thread pools used with connectors pre-start the
        configured minimum number of idle threads. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>60594</bug>: Allow some invalid characters that were recently
        restricted to be processed in requests by using the system property
        <code>tomcat.util.http.parser.HttpParser.requestTargetAllow</code>.
        (csutherl)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60627</bug>: Modify the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code> so that
        in addition to cookie headers that start with an explicit RFC 2109
        <code>$Version=1</code>, cookies that start with <code>$Version=0</code>
        are also parsed as RFC 2109 cookies. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60716</bug>: Add a new JSSE specific attribute,
        <code>revocationEnabled</code>, to <code>SSLHostConfig</code> to permit
        JSSE provider revocation checks to be enabled when no
        <code>certificateRevocationListFile</code> has been configured. The
        expectation is that configuration will be performed via a JSSE provider
        specific mechanisms. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify the cookie header generated by the
        <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code> so it always sends an
        <code>Expires</code> attribute as well as a <code>Max-Age</code>
        attribute to avoid problems with Microsoft browsers that do not support
        the <code>Max-Age</code> attribute. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60761</bug>: Expose a protected getter and setter for
        <code>NioEndpoint.stopLatch</code> to make the class easier to extend.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Prevent blocking reads after a stream exception occurs with HTTP/2.
        (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Follow up to the fix for <bug>58178</bug>. When creating the
        <code>ELContext</code> for a tag file, ensure that any registered
        <code>ELContextListener</code>s are fired. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor code generated for JSPs to reduce the size of the code required
        for tags. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60769</bug>: Correct a regression in the XML encoding detection
        refactoring carried out for 8.5.10 that incorrectly always used the
        detected BOM encoding in preference to any encoding specified in the
        prolog. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.6.1. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Make the <code>accessTimeout</code> configurable in
        <code>BackupManager</code> and <code>ClusterSingleSignOn</code>. The
        <code>accessTimeout</code> is used as a timeout period for PING in
        replication map. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60806</bug>: To avoid <code>ClassNotFoundException</code>, make
        sure that the web application class loader is passed to
        <code>ReplicatedContext</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60617</bug>: Correctly create a <code>CONNECT</code> request when
        establishing a WebSocket connection via a proxy. Patch provided by
        Svetlin Zarev. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add log message that PING message has received beyond the timeout
        period. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When a PING message that beyond the time-out period has been received,
        make sure that valid member is added to the map membership. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>NoRpcChannelReply</code> messages are not received on
        <code>RpcCallback</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Add Specification and Javadoc references for JASPIC to the Docs
        application. (csutherl)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Spelling corrections provided by Josh Soref. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.12 to
        pick up the latest Windows binaries built with OpenSSL 1.0.2k. (violetagg)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>60784</bug>: Update all unit tests that test the HTTP status line
        to check for the required space after the status code. Patch provided by
        Michael Osipov. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows installer to version
        3.01. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.11 (markt)" rtext="2017-01-16">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>60620</bug>:
        Extend the <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code> to provide
        protection against <code>ForkJoinPool.commonPool()</code> related memory
        leaks. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure UpgradeProcessor instances associated with closed connections are
        removed from the map of current connections to Processors. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove a workaround for a problem previously reported with WebSocket,
        TLS and APR that treated some error conditions as not errors. The
        original problem cannot be reproduced with the current code and the
        work-around is now causing problems. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60497</bug>: Follow up fix using a better variable name for the
        tag reuse flag. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Revert use of try/finally for simple tags. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Prevent potential processing loop on unexpected WebSocket connection
        closure. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Enable reset the statistics without restarting the pool. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Spelling corrections provided by Josh Soref. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.10 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>53602</bug>: Add HTTP status code 451 (RFC 7725) to the list of
        HTTP status codes recognised by the ErrorReportValve. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60446</bug>: Handle the case where the stored user credential uses
        a different key length than the length currently configured for the
        <code>CredentialHandler</code>. Based on a patch by Niklas Holm. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the warnings that reference required options for running on Java
        9 to use the latest syntax for those options. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>60513</bug>: Fix thread safety issue with RMI cleanup code. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Expand the search process for a server certificate when OpenSSL is used
        with a JSSE connector and an explicit alias has not been configured.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60450</bug>: Improve the selection algorithm for the default trust
        store type for a TLS Virtual Host. In particular, don't use
        <code>PKCS12</code> as a default trust store type. Better document how
        the default trust store type is selected for a TLS virtual host. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60451</bug>: Correctly handle HTTP/2 header values that contain
        characters with unicode code points in the range 128 to 255. Reject
        with a clear error message HTTP/2 header values that contain characters
        with unicode code points above 255. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the logic that selects an address to use to unlock the Acceptor
        to take account of platforms what do not listen on all local addresses
        when configured with an address of <code>0.0.0.0</code> or
        <code>::</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the refactoring to make wider use of
        <code>ByteBuffer</code> that caused an intermittent failure in the unit
        tests. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60482</bug>: HTTP/2 shouldn't do URL decoding on the query string.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix an HTTP/2 compression error. Once a new size has been agreed for the
        dynamic HPACK table, the next header block must begin with a dynamic
        table update. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60508</bug>: Set request start time for HTTP/2. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Implement a simpler JSP file encoding detector that delegates XML prolog
        encoding detection to the JRE rather than using a custom XML parser.
        (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>60497</bug>: Restore previous tag reuse behavior following the use
        of try/finally. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the error handling for simple tags to ensure that the tag is
        released and destroyed once used. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle blocking WebSocket writes when the write times out just
        before the write is attempted. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        In the documentation web application, be explicit that clustering
        requires a secure network for all of the cluster network traffic.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the ASF logos to the new versions.
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>60344</bug>: Add a note to BUILDING.txt regarding using the source
        bundle with the correct line endings. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60468</bug>: Correct the format of the sample ISO-8601 date used
        to report the build date for the documentation. Patch provided by
        Michael Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the ASF logos used in the Apache Tomcat installer for Windows to
        use the new versions.
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.9 (markt)" rtext="2016-12-08">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        <bug>60202</bug>: Add an available flag to realms, to indicate the
        state, or the realm backend. Update lockout realm to only register
        auth failures if the realm is available. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>60340</bug>: Readability improvements for CSS used in
        DefaultServlet and ErrorReportValve. Patch provided by Michael
        Osipov. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60351</bug>: Delay creating <code>META-INF/war-tracker</code> file
        until after the WAR has been expanded to address the case where the
        Tomcat process terminates during the expansion. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly generate URLs for resources located inside JARs that are
        themselves located inside a packed WAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle the <code>configClass</code> attribute of a Host when
        embedding Tomcat. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60368</bug>: Restore egde case for embedded allowing the connector
        to be removed. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60379</bug>: Dispose of the GSS credential once it is no longer
        required. Patch provided by Michael Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60380</bug>: Ensure that a call to
        <code>HttpServletRequest#logout()</code> triggers a call to
        <code>TomcatPrincipal#logout()</code>. Based on a patch by Michael
        Osipov. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60387</bug>: Correct the javadoc for
        <code>o.a.catalina.AccessLog.setRequestAttributesEnabled</code>.
        The default value is different for the different implementations.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>60393</bug>: Use consistent parameter naming in implementations of
        <code>Realm#authenticate(GSSContext, boolean)</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>60395</bug>: Log when an <code>Authenticator</code> passes an
        incomplete <code>GSSContext</code> to a Realm since it indicates a bug
        in the <code>Authenticator</code>. Patch provided by Michael Osipov.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60400</bug>: When expanding the buffer used for reading the
        request body, ensure the read position will be restored to the
        original one. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60410</bug>: Ensure that multiple calls to
        <code>JarInputStreamWrapper#close()</code> do not incorrectly trigger
        the closure of the underlying JAR or WAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60411</bug>: Implement support in the <code>RewriteValve</code> for
        symbolic names to specify the redirect code to use when returning a
        redirect response to the user agent. Patch provided by Michael Osipov.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60413</bug>: In the <code>RewriteValve</code> write empty capture
        groups as the empty string rather than as <code>&quot;null&quot;</code>
        when generating the re-written URL. Based on a patch by Michael Osipov.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60372</bug>: Ensure the response headers' buffer limit is reset to
        the capacity of this buffer when IOException occurs while writing the
        headers to the socket. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the availability of configured upgrade protocols that
        require ALPN is correctly reported during Tomcat start. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60386</bug>: Implement a more sophisticated pruning algorithm for
        removing closed streams from the priority tree to ensure that the tree
        does not grow too large. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60409</bug>: When unable to complete sendfile request, ensure the
        Processor will be added to the cache only once. (markt/violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the endpoint is able to unlock the acceptor thread during
        shutdown if the endpoint is configured to listen to any local address
        of a specific type such as <code>0.0.0.0</code> or <code>::</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a new configuration option, <code>ipv6v6only</code> to the APR
        connectors that allows them to be configure to only accept IPv6
        connections when configured with an IPv6 address rather than the
        default which is to accept IPv4 connections as well if the operating
        system uses a dual network stack. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Improve the logic that unlocks the acceptor thread so a better choice is
        made for the address to connect to when a connector is configured for
        any local port. This reduces the likelihood of the unlock failing.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60436</bug>: Avoid a potential NPE when processing async timeouts.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Reduce the window in which an async request that has just started
        processing on a container thread remains eligible for an async timeout.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60431</bug>: Improve handling of varargs in UEL expressions. Based
        on a patch by Ben Wolfe. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix JDK version number documented in BUILDING.txt. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a typo in Host Configuration Reference.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60412</bug>: Add information on the comment syntax for the
        <code>RewriteValve</code> configuration. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60467</bug>: remove problematic characters from XML documentation.
        Based upon a patch by Michael Osipov. (schultz)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Reduce the warning logs for a message received from a different domain
        in order to avoid excessive log outputs. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60437</bug>: Avoid possible handshake overflows in the websocket
        client. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>58816</bug>: Implement the statistics of jdbc-pool. The stats infos
        are <code>borrowedCount</code>, <code>returnedCount</code>,
        <code>createdCount</code>, <code>releasedCount</code>,
        <code>reconnectedCount</code>, <code>releasedIdleCount</code> and
        <code>removeAbandonedCount</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60194</bug>: If <code>validationQuery</code> is not specified,
        connection validation is done by calling the <code>isValid()</code>
        method. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60398</bug>: Fix testcase of <code>TestSlowQueryReport</code>.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Allow customization of service.bat, such as heap memory size, service
        startup mode and JVM args. Patch provided by isapir via Github.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60366</bug>: Change <code>catalina.bat</code> to use directly
        <code>LOGGING_MANAGER</code> and <code>LOGGING_CONFIG</code> variables
        in order to configure logging, instead of modifying
        <code>JAVA_OPTS</code>. Patch provided by Petter Isberg. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60383</bug>: JASPIC API is added as a dependency to the
        <code>org.apache.tomcat:tomcat-catalina</code> maven artifact.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update the comments associated with the TLS Connector examples in
        <code>server.xml</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        New property is added <code>test.verbose</code> in order to control
        whether the output of the tests is displayed on the console or not.
        Patch provided by Emmanuel Bourg. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <scode>
        <code>TestOpenSSLCipherConfigurationParser.testSpecification</code>
        - if there are test failures, provide more detailed information. Patch
        provided by Emmanuel Bourg. (violetagg)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.8 (markt)" rtext="2016-11-08">
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Check that threadPriority values used in AbstractProtocol are valid.
        (fschumacher)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.7 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When creating a new Connector via JMX, ensure that both HTTP/1.1 and
        AJP/1.3 connectors can be created. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Include the Context name in the log message when an item cannot be
        added to the cache. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Exclude JAR files in <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> from the static resource
        cache. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When calling <code>getResourceAsStream()</code> on a directory, ensure
        that <code>null</code> is returned. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60161</bug>: Allow creating subcategories of the container logger,
        and use it for the rewrite valve. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly test for control characters when reading the provided shutdown
        password. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60297</bug>: Simplify connector creation in embedded mode. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor creation of containers in embedded mode for more consistency
        and flexibility. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Introduce new methods <code>read(ByteBuffer)</code>/
        <code>write(ByteBuffer)</code> in
        <code>o.a.catalina.connector.CoyoteInputStream</code>/
        <code>o.a.catalina.connector.CoyoteOutputStream</code>. (violetagg)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When configuring the JMX remote listener, specify the allowed types for
        the credentials. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct the HPACK header table size configuration that transposed the
        client and server table sizes when creating the encoder and decoder.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't continue to process an HTTP/2 stream if it is reset during header
        parsing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        HTTP/2 uses separate headers for each Cookie. As required by RFC 7540,
        merge these into a single Cookie header before processing continues.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Align the HTTP/2 implementation with the HTTP/1.1 implementation and
        return a 500 response when an unhandled exception occurs during request
        processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the HTTP header parser so that DEL is not treated as a valid
        token character. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add checks around the handling of HTTP/2 pseudo headers. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add support for trailer headers to the HTTP/2 implementation. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60232</bug>: When processing headers for an HTTP/2 stream, ensure
        that the read buffer is large enough for the header being processed.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add configuration options to the HTTP/2 implementation to control the
        maximum number of headers allowed, the maximum size of headers allowed,
        the maximum number of trailer headers allowed, the maximum size of
        trailer headers allowed and the maximum number of cookies allowed.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correctly differentiate between sending and receiving a reset frame when
        tracking the state of an HTTP/2 stream. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60319</bug>: When using an Executor, disconnect it from the
        Connector attributes <code>maxThreads</code>,
        <code>minSpareThreads</code> and <code>threadPriority</code> to enable
        the configuration settings to be consistently reported. These Connector
        attributes will be reported as <code>-1</code> when an Executor is in
        use. The values used by the executor may be set and obtained via the
        Executor. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        If an I/O error occurs during async processing on a non-container
        thread, ensure that the <code>onError()</code> event is triggered.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve detection of I/O errors during async processing on non-container
        threads and trigger async error handling when they are detected. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add additional checks for valid characters to the HTTP request line
        parsing so invalid request lines are rejected sooner. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add HTTP/2 configuration information to the documentation web
        application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix default value of <code>validationInterval</code> attribute in
        jdbc-pool. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a typo in CGI How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When the proxy node sends a backup retrieve message, ensure that using
        the <code>channelSendOptions</code> that has been set rather than the
        default <code>channelSendOptions</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add the JASPIC API jar to the Maven Central publication script. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Remove classes from tomcat-util-scan.jar that are duplicates of those in
        tomcat-util.jar. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.6 (markt)" rtext="2016-10-10">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>59961</bug>: Add an option to the <code>StandardJarScanner</code>
        to control whether or not JAR Manifests are scanned for additional
        class path entries. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60013</bug>: Refactor the previous fix to align the behaviour of
        the Rewrite Valve with mod_rewrite. As part of this, provide an
        implementation for the <code>B</code> and <code>NE</code> flags and
        improve the handling for the <code>QSA</code> flag. Includes multiple
        test cases by Santhana Preethiand a patch by Tiago Oliveira. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60087</bug>: Refactor the web resources handling to use the Tomcat
        specific <code>war:file:...</code> URL protocol to refer to WAR files
        and their contents rather than the standard <code>jar:file:...</code>
        form since some components of the JRE, such as JAR verification, give
        unexpected results when the standard form is used. A side-effect of the
        refactoring is that when using packed WARs, it is now possible to
        reference a WAR and/or specific JARs within a WAR in the security policy
        file used when running under a <code>SecurityManager</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60116</bug>: Fix a problem with the rewrite valve that caused back
        references evaluated in conditions to be forced to lower case when using
        the <code>NC</code> flag. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure <code>Digester.useContextClassLoader</code> is considered in
        case the class loader is used. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60117</bug>: Ensure that the name of <code>LogLevel</code> is
        localized when using <code>OneLineFormatter</code>. Patch provided by
        Tatsuya Bessho. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60138</bug>: Fix the <code>SSLHostConfig</code> so that the
        <code>protocols</code> attribute is limited to the protocols supported
        by the current JSSE implementation rather than the default protocols
        used by the implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60146</bug>: Improve performance for resource retrieval by making
        calls to WebResource.getInputStream() trigger caching if the resource is
        small enough. Patch provided by mohitchugh. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>60151</bug>: Improve the exception error messages when a
        <code>ResourceLink</code> fails to specify the type, specifies an
        unknown type or specifies the wrong type. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60167</bug>: Ignore empty lines in <code>/etc/passwd</code> files
        when using the <code>PasswdUserDatabase</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60170</bug>: Exclude the compressed test file
        <code>index.html.br</code> from RAT analysis. Patch provided by Gavin
        McDonald. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When starting web resources, ensure that class resources are only
        started once. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the access checks for linked global resources to handle the case
        where the current class loader is a child of the web application class
        loader. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60196</bug>: Ensure that the <code>isMandatory</code> flag is
        correctly set when using JASPIC authentication. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60199</bug>: Log a warning if deserialization issues prevent a
        session attribute from being loaded. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60208</bug>: When using RFC6265 compliant cookies, the
        <code>/</code> character should not be allowed in a cookie name since
        the RFC6265 will drop such cookies as invalid. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Refactor the code that implements the requirement that a call to
        <code>complete()</code> or <code>dispatch()</code> made from a
        non-container thread before the container initiated thread that called
        <code>startAsync()</code> completes must be delayed until the container
        initiated thread has completed. Rather than implementing this by
        blocking the non-container thread, extend the internal state machine to
        track this. This removes the possibility that blocking the non-container
        thread could trigger a deadlock. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fail earlier if the client closes the connection during SNI processing.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60123</bug>: Avoid potential threading issues that could cause
        excessively large vales to be returned for the processing time of
        a current request. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60174</bug>: Log instances of <code>HeadersTooLargeException</code>
        during request processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60173</bug>: Allow up to 64kB HTTP/2 header table size limit. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Java 9 compatibility of direct ByteBuffer cleaner. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>60101</bug>: Remove preloading of the class that was deleted.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Expand the documentation for the nested elements within a
        <code>Resources</code> element to clarify the behaviour of different
        configuration options with respect to the order in which resources are
        searched. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add an example of using the <code>classesToInitialize</code> attribute
        of the <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code> to the documentation
        web application. Based on a patch by Cris Berneburg. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60192</bug>: Correct a typo in the status output of the Manager
        application. Patch provided by  Radhakrishna Pemmasani. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Notify jmx when returning the connection that has been marked suspect.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the <code>POOL_EMPTY</code> notification has been added to
        the jmx notification types. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60099</bug>: Ensure that use all method arguments as a cache key
        when using <code>StatementCache</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60139</bug>: Correct Javadocs for
        <code>PoolConfiguration.getValidationInterval</code> and
        <code>setValidationInterval</code>. Reported by Phillip Webb. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Update the download location for Objenesis. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60164</bug>: Replace <code>log4j-core*.jar</code> with
        <code>log4j-web*.jar</code> since it is <code>log4j-web*.jar</code> that
        contains the <code>ServletContainerInitializer</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add documentation to the bin/catalina.bat script to remind users that
        environment variables don't affect the configuration of Tomcat when
        run as a Windows Service. Based upon a documentation patch by
        James H.H. Lampert. (schultz)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.10 to
        pick up the latest Windows binaries built with OpenSSL 1.0.2j. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.5 (markt)" rtext="2016-09-05">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>18500</bug>: Add limited support for wildcard host names and host
        aliases. Names of the form <code>*.domainname</code> are now permitted.
        Note that an exact host name match takes precedence over a wild card
        host name match. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59813</bug>: Ensure that circular relations of the Class-Path
        attribute from JAR manifests will be processed correctly. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that reading the <code>singleThreadModel</code> attribute of a
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> via JMX does not trigger initialisation of
        the associated servlet. With some frameworks this can trigger an
        unexpected initialisation thread and if initialisation is not thread-safe
        the initialisation can then fail. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Compatibility with rewrite from httpd for non existing headers.
        (jfclere)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        By default, treat paths used to obtain a request dispatcher as encoded.
        This behaviour can be changed per web application via the
        <code>dispatchersUseEncodedPaths</code> attribute of the Context.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59839</bug>: Apply <code>roleSearchAsUser</code> to all nested searches
        in JNDIRealm. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59859</bug>: Fix resource leak in WebDAV servlet. Based on patch by
        Coty Sutherland. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Provide a mechanism that enables the container to check if a component
        (typically a web application) has been granted a given permission when
        running under a SecurityManager without the current execution stack
        having to have passed through the component. Use this new mechanism to
        extend SecurityManager protection to the system property replacement
        feature of the digester. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        When retrieving an object via a <code>ResourceLink</code>, ensure that
        the object obtained is of the expected type. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59823</bug>: Ensure that JASPIC configuration is taken into account
        when calling <code>HttpServletRequest.authenticate()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59824</bug>: Mark the <code>RewriteValve</code> as supporting async
        processing by default. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59862</bug>: Allow nested jar files scanning to be filtered with
        the system property
        <code>tomcat.util.scan.StandardJarScanFilter.jarsToSkip</code>. Patch
        is provided by Terence Bandoian. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59866</bug>: When scanning <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> for
        annotations, don't scan the contents of
        <code>WEB-INF/classes/META-INF</code> (if present) since classes will
        never be loaded from that location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59888</bug>: Correctly handle tabs and spaces in quoted version one
        cookies when using the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59912</bug>: Fix an edge case in input stream handling where an
        <code>IOException</code> could be thrown when reading a POST body.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59913</bug>: Correct a regression introduced with the support for
        the Servlet 4 <code>HttpServletRequest.getMapping()</code> API that
        caused the attributes for forwarded requests to be lost if requested
        from within a subsequent include. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59966</bug>: Do not start the web application if the error page
        configuration in web.xml is invalid. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Switch the CGI servlet to the standard logging mechanism and remove
        support for the debug attribute. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60012</bug>: Improvements in the log messages. Based on
        suggestions by Nemo Chen. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Changes to the <code>allowLinking</code> attribute of a
        <code>StandardRoot</code> instance now invalidate the cache if caching
        is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a new initialisation parameter, <code>envHttpHeaders</code>, to
        the CGI Servlet to mitigate <a href="https://httpoxy.org">httpoxy</a>
        (<a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2016-5388"
        >CVE-2016-5388</a>) by default and to provide a mechanism that can be
        used to mitigate any future, similar issues. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        When adding and removing <code>ResourceLink</code>s dynamically, ensure
        that the global resource is only visible via the
        <code>ResourceLinkFactory</code> when it is meant to be. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60008</bug>: When processing CORs requests, treat any origin with a
        URI scheme of <code>file</code> as a valid origin. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of exceptions during a Lifecycle events triggered by a
        state transition. The exception is now caught and the component is now
        placed into the <code>FAILED</code> state. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60013</bug>: Fix encoding issues when using the RewriteValve with
        UTF-8 query strings or UTF-8 redirect URLs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60022</bug>: Improve handling when a WAR file and/or the associated
        exploded directory are symlinked into the <code>appBase</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a file descriptor leak when reading the global web.xml. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Consistently decode URL patterns provided via web.xml using the encoding
        of the web.xml file where specified or UTF-8 where no explicit encoding
        is specified. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make timing attacks against the Realm implementations harder. (schultz)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        A number of the JRE memory leaks addressed by the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code> have been fixed in Java 9
        so the associated protection is now disabled when running on Java 9
        onwards. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in refactoring to enable injection of custom
        keystores that broke the automatic conversion of OpenSSL style PEM
        key and certificate files for use with JSSE TLS connectors. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59910</bug>: Don't hardcode key alias value to "tomcat" for JSSE.
        When using a keystore, OpenSSL will still default to it. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59904</bug>: Add a limit (default 200) for the number of cookies
        allowed per request. Based on a patch by gehui. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59925</bug>: Correct regression in r1628368 and ensure that HTTP
        separators are handled as configured in the
        <code>LegacyCookieProcessor</code>. Patch provided by Kyohei Nakamura.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59950</bug>: Correct log message when reporting that the current
        number of HTTP/2 streams for a connection could not be pruned to below
        the limit. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>Semaphore.release</code> is called in all cases. Even
        when there is an exception. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60030</bug>: Correct a potential infinite loop in the SNI parsing
        code triggered by failing to handle an end of stream condition. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Small logging optimization in the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>.
        Patch provided by Svetlin Zarev. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        OpenSSL now disables 3DES by default so reflect this when using OpenSSL
        syntax to select ciphers. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use the proper ERROR socket status code for async errors with NIO2.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60035</bug>: Fix a potential connection leak if the client drops a
        TLS connection before the handshake completes. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the JSSE client certificate validation so that the
        effectiveness of the <code>certificateVerificationDepth</code>
        configuration attribute does not depend on the presence of a certificate
        revocation list. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Log a warning at start up if a JSSE TLS connector is configured with
        a trusted certificate that is either not yet valid or has expired.
        (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When writing out a full web.xml file with JspC ensure that the encoding
        used in the XML prolog matches the encoding used to write the contents
        of the file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the error handling for custom tags to ensure that the tag is
        returned to the pool or released and destroyed once used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60032</bug>: Fix handling of method calls that use varargs within
        EL value expressions. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ignore <code>engineOptionsClass</code> and <code>scratchdir</code> when
        running under a security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed StringIndexOutOfBoundsException. Based on a patch provided by
        wuwen via Github. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59908</bug>: Ensure that a reason phrase is included in the close
        message if a session is closed due to a timeout. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59867</bug>: Correct the documentation provided by Manager's
        403.jsp. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59868</bug>: Clarify the documentation for the Manager web
        application to make clearer that the host name and IP address in the
        server section are the primary host name and IP address. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59940</bug>: Correct the name of the
        <code>truststorePassword</code> attribute of the
        <code>SSLHostConfig</code> element in the configuration documentation.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        MBeans Descriptors How-To is moved to
        <code>mbeans-descriptors-howto.html</code>. Patch provided by Radoslav
        Husar. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update NIO Connector configuration documentation with an information
        about <code>socket.directSslBuffer</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60034</bug>: Correct a typo in the Manager How-To page of the
        documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid the unintended skip of <code>PoolCleaner</code>,
        remove the check code of the execution interval in the task that has
        been scheduled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59850</bug>: Ensure that the <code>ResultSet</code> is closed when
        enabling the <code>StatementCache</code> interceptor. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59923</bug>: Reduce the default value of
        <code>validationInterval</code> in order to avoid the potential issue
        that continues to return an invalid connection after database restart.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the <code>ResultSet</code> is returned as Proxy object when
        enabling the <code>StatementDecoratorInterceptor</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60043</bug>: Ensure that the <code>suspectTimeout</code> works
        without removing connection when the <code>removeAbandoned</code> is
        disabled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add log message of when returning the connection that has been marked
        suspect. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct Javadoc for <code>ConnectionPool.suspect()</code>. Based on a
        patch by Yahya Cahyadi. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>59871</bug>: Add a property (<code>timeFormat</code>) to
        JULI&apos;s <code>OneLineFormatter</code> to enable the format of the
        time stamp used in log messages to be configured. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59899</bug>: Update Tomcat&apos;s copy of the Java Persistence
        annotations to include the changes made in 2.1 / JavaEE 7. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed typos in mbeans-descriptors.xml files. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons BCEL to r1757132 to align with the
        BCEL 6 release. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP2 to r1757164 to pick up a
        couple of bug fixes. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Codec to r1757174. Code formatting
        changes only. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons FileUpload to afdedc9. This pulls in
        a fix to improve the performance with large multipart boundaries.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.4 (markt)" rtext="2016-07-12">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>57705</bug>: Add debug logging for requests denied by the remote
        host and remote address valves and filters. Based on a patch by Graham
        Leggett. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>58588</bug> that removed the
        entire <code>org.apache.juli</code> package from the embedded JARs
        rendering them unusable. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>59399</bug>: Add a new option to the Realm implementations that
        ship with Tomcat that allows the HTTP status code used for HTTP -> HTTPS
        redirects to be controlled per Realm. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Change the default of the
        <code>sessionCookiePathUsesTrailingSlash</code> attribute of the
        <code>Context</code> element to <code>false</code> since the problems
        caused when a Servlet is mapped to <code>/*</code> are more significant
        than the security risk of not enabling this option by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to <bug>59655</bug>. Improve the documentation for configuring
        permitted cookie names. Patch provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not attempt to start web resources during a web application's
        initialisation phase since the web application is not fully configured
        at that point and the web resources may not be correctly configured.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59708</bug>: Modify the LockOutRealm logic. Valid authentication
        attempts during the lock out period will no longer reset the lock out
        timer to zero. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor the certificate keystore and trust store generation to make it
        easier for embedded users to inject their own key stores. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>59233</bug>: Add the ability to add TLS virtual hosts dynamically.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Add a <code>maxConcurrentStreamExecution</code> on the HTTP/2
        protocol handler to allow restricting the amount of concurrent stream
        that are being executed in a single connection. The default is to
        not limit it. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a problem with <code>ServletRequest.getServerPort()</code> for
        secure HTTP/2 connections that meant an incorrect value was returned when
        using the default port. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Now the WebSocket implementation is not built directly on top of the
        Servlet API and can use Tomcat internals, there is no need for the
        dedicated WebSocket Executor. It has been replaced by the use of the
        Connector/Endpoint provided Executor. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Do not log an additional case of <code>IOException</code>s in the
        error handler for the Drawboard WebSocket example when the root cause is
        the client disconnecting since the logs add no value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59642</bug>: Mention the <code>localDataSource</code> in the
        <code>DataSourceRealm</code> section of the Realm How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59672</bug>: Update the security considerations page of the
        documentation web application to take account of the fact that the
        Manager and HostManager applications now have a
        <code>RemoteAddrValve</code> configured by default. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to the fix for <bug>59399</bug>. Ensure that the new attribute
        <code>transportGuaranteeRedirectStatus</code> is documented for all
        <strong>Realm</strong>s. Also document the <code>NullRealm</code> and
        when it is automatically created for an <strong>Engine</strong>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix the description of <code>maxAge</code> attribute in jdbc-pool doc.
        This attribute works both when a connection is returned and when a
        connection is borrowed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59774</bug>: Correct the <code>prefix</code> values in the
        documented examples for configuring the <code>AccessLogValve</code>.
        Patch provided by Mike Noordermeer. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Extras">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        <bug>58588</bug>: Remove the JULI extras package from the distribution.
        It was only useful for switching Tomcat's internal logging to log4j
        1.2.x and that version of log4j is no longer supported. No additional
        Tomcat code is required if switching Tomcat's internal logging to log
        via log4j 2.x. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add log message when the ping has timed-out. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        If the ping message has been received at the
        <code>AbstractReplicatedMap#leftOver</code> method, ensure that notify
        the member is alive than ignore it. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix the duplicated connection release when connection verification
        failed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that do not remove the abandoned connection that has been already
        released. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        <bug>59276</bug>: Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.17. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <add>
        Use the mirror network rather than the ASF master site to download the
        current ASF dependencies. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.8 to
        pick up the latest fixes and make 1.2.8 the minimum recommended version.
        (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Use UTF-8 with a standard prolog for all XML files. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.3 (markt)" rtext="2016-06-13">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        RMI Target related memory leaks are avoidable which makes them an
        application bug that needs to be fixed rather than a JRE bug to work
        around. Therefore, start logging RMI Target related memory leaks on web
        application stop. Add an option that controls if the check for these
        leaks is made. Log a warning if running on Java 9 with this check
        enabled but without the command line option it requires. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure NPE will not be thrown during deployment when scanning jar files
        without MANIFEST.MF file. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>clearReferencesStatic</code> option from
        <code>StandardContext</code>. It was known to cause problems with some
        libraries (such as log4j) and was only linked to suspected memory leaks
        rather than known memory leaks. It had been disabled by default with no
        increase in the reports of memory leaks for some time. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>59604</bug>: Correct the assumption made in the URL decoding that
        the default platform encoding is always compatible with ISO-8859-1. This
        assumption is not always valid, e.g. on z/OS. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59608</bug>: Skip over any invalid <code>Class-Path</code> attribute
        from JAR manifests. Log errors at debug level due to many bad libraries.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix error message when failed to register MBean. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59655</bug>: Configure the cookie name validation to use RFC6265 rules by default to
        align it with the default cookie parser. Document the impact system properties have on
        cookie name validation. (mark)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that requests with HTTP method names that are not tokens (as
        required by RFC 7231) are rejected with a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When an asynchronous request is processed by the AJP connector, ensure
        that request processing has fully completed before starting the next
        request. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of HTTP/2 stream resets. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58750</bug>: The HTTP Server header is no longer set by default. A
        Server header may be configured by setting the <code>server</code>
        attribute on the <code>Connector</code>. A new <code>Connector</code>
        attribute, <code>serverRemoveAppProvidedValues</code> may be used to
        remove any Server header set by a web application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59564</bug>: Correct offset when reading into HTTP/2 input buffer
        that could cause problems reading request bodies. (violetagg/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify the handling of read/write timeouts so that the appropriate error
        handling (<code>ReadListener.onError()</code>,
        <code>WriteListener.onError()</code> or
        <code>AsyncListener.onError()</code>) is called. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
       If an async dispatch results in the completion of request processing,
       ensure that any remaining request body is swallowed before starting the
       processing of the next request else the remaining body may be read as the
       start of the next request leading to a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a cause of multiple attempts to close the same socket. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59567</bug>: Fix NPE scanning webapps for TLDs when an exploded
        JAR has an empty WEB-INF/classes/META-INF folder. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak in the expression language implementation that caused
        the class loader of the first web application to use expressions to be
        pinned in memory. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59654</bug>: Improve error message when attempting to use a TLD
        file from an invalid location. Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59659</bug>: Fix possible memory leak in WebSocket handling of
        unexpected client disconnects. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58891</bug>: Update the SSL how-to. Based on a suggestion by
        Alexander Kjäll. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak with the pool cleaner thread that retained a reference
        to the web application class loader for the first web application to use
        a connection pool. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to r1743696 (2.1.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to r1743697 (2.4.2 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons File Upload to r1743698 (1.3.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>58626</bug>: Add support for a new environment variable
        (<code>USE_NOHUP</code>) that causes <code>nohup</code> to be used when
        starting Tomcat. It is disabled by default except on HP-UX where it is
        enabled by default since it is required when starting Tomcat at boot on
        HP-UX. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.2 (markt)" rtext="2016-05-16">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that annotated web components packed in web fragments will be
        processed when <code>unpackWARs</code> is enabled. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.1 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59206</bug>: Ensure NPE will not be thrown by
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.file.ConfigFileLoader</code> when
        <code>catalina.base</code> is not specified. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59217</bug>: Remove duplication in the recycling of the path in
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.http.ServerCookie</code>. Patch is provided by
        Kyohei Nakamura. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed possible NPE in
        <code>o.a.catalina.loader.WebappClassLoaderBase.getResourceAsStream</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59213</bug>: Async dispatches should be based off a wrapped request.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>javax.servlet.ServletRequest</code> and
        <code>javax.servlet.ServletResponse</code> provided during
        <code>javax.servlet.AsyncListener</code> registration are made
        available via <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedRequest</code>
        and <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedResponse</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59219</bug>: Ensure <code>AsyncListener.onError()</code> is called
        if an <code>Exception</code> is thrown during async processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59220</bug>: Ensure that <code>AsyncListener.onComplete()</code> is
        called if the async request times out and the response is already
        committed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59226</bug>: Process the <code>Class-Path</code> attribute from
        JAR manifests for JARs on the class path excluding JARs packaged in
        <code>WEB-INF/lib</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59255</bug>: Fix possible NPE in mapper. (kkolinko/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59256</bug>: <code>slf4j-taglib*.jar</code> should not be excluded
        from the standard JAR scanning by default. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify in the log message that specifying both urlPatterns and value
        attributes in WebServlet and WebFilter annotations is not allowed.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure the exceptions caused by Valves will be available in the log
        files so that they can be evaluated when
        <code>o.a.catalina.valves.ErrorReportValve.showReport</code> is
        disabled. Patch is provided by Svetlin Zarev. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove unused <code>distributable</code> attribute that is defined as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code> of <code>Manager</code> in StoreConfig.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix handling of Cluster Receiver in StoreConfig. The <code>bind</code>
        and <code>host</code> attributes define as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59261</bug>: <code>ServletRequest.getAsyncContext()</code> now
        throws an <code>IllegalStateException</code> as required by the Servlet
        specification if the request is not in asynchronous mode when called.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59269</bug>: Correct the implementation of
        <code>PersistentManagerBase</code> so that <code>minIdleSwap</code>
        functions as designed and sessions are swapped out to keep the active
        session count below <code>maxActiveSessions</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add the <code>org.apache.catalina.servlet4preview</code> package that
        can be used to gain early access to Servlet 4.0 features. Note that this
        package will <strong>not</strong> be present in Tomcat 9. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correctly configure the base path for a resources directory provided by
        an expanded JAR file. Patch provided by hengyunabc. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        When multiple compressed formats are available and the client does not
        express a preference, use the server order to determine the preferred
        format. Based on a patch by gmokki. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59284</bug>: Allow the Tomcat provided JASPIC
        <code>SimpleServerAuthConfig</code> to pick up module configuration
        properties from either the property set passed to its constructor or
        from the properties passed in the call to <code>getAuthContext</code>.
        Based on a patch by Thomas Maslen. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59310</bug>: Do not add a <code>Content-Length: 0</code> header for
        custom responses to <code>HEAD</code> requests that do not set a
        <code>Content-Length</code> value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When normalizing paths, improve the handling when paths end with
        <code>/.</code> or <code>/..</code> and ensure that input and output are
        consistent with respect to whether or not they end with <code>/</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59317</bug>: Ensure that
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getRequestURI()</code> returns an encoded URI
        rather than a decoded URI after a dispatch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use the correct URL for the fragment when reporting errors processing
        a <code>web-fragment.xml</code> file from a JAR located in an unpacked
        WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>JarScanner</code> only uses the explicit call-back to
        process <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and only when configured to treat
        the contents of <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> as a possible exploded JAR.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>java2DDisposerProtection</code> option from the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code>. The leak is fixed in Java
        7 onwards and Tomcat 8 requires Java 7 so the option is unnecessary.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the value for the header <code>X-Frame-Options</code> is
        constructed correctly according to the specification when
        <code>ALLOW-FROM</code> option is used. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> if the first use of an
        internal <code>Response</code> object requires JASPIC authentication.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not trigger unnecessary session ID changes when using JASPIC and the
        user is authenticated using cached credentials. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59437</bug>: Ensure that the JASPIC <code>CallbackHandler</code> is
        thread-safe. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59449</bug>: In <code>ContainerBase</code>, ensure that the process
        to remove a child container is the reverse of the process to add one.
        Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Align cipher configuration parsing with current OpenSSL master. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Change the default for <code>honorCipherOrder</code> to
        <code>false</code>. With the current default TLS configuration, it is no
        longer necessary for this to be <code>true</code> for a reasonably
        secure configuration. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add a new environment variable <code>JSSE_OPTS</code> that is intended
        to be used to pass JVM wide configuration to the JSSE implementation.
        The default value is <code>-Djdk.tls.ephemeralDHKeySize=2048</code>
        which protects against weak Diffie-Hellman keys. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When running on Java 7, exclude DHE ciphers from the default cipher list
        for JSSE connectors since they use weak 768 bit DH keys and cannot be
        configured to use more secure keys. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58970</bug>: Fix a connection counting bug in the NIO connector
        that meant some dropped connections were not removed from the current
        connection count. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59289</bug>: Do not recycle upgrade processors in unexpected close
        situations. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Use <code>Locale.toLanguageTag()</code> to construct
        the <code>Content-Language</code> HTTP header to ensure the locale is
        correctly represented. Patch provided by zikfat. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Add support for using pem encoded certificates with
        JSSE SSL. Submitted by Emmanuel Bourg with additional tweaks. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Make the TLS certificate chain available to clients when using
        JSSE+OpenSSL with the certificate chain stored in a Java KeyStore.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Work around <a href="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/issues/188">a
        known issue in OpenSSL</a> that does not permit the TLS handshake to be
        failed if the ALPN negotiation fails. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59421</bug>: Add direct HTTP/2 connection support. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle a call to <code>AsyncContext.complete()</code> from a
        non-container thread when non-blocking I/O is being used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59451</bug>: Correct Javadoc for <code>MessageBytes</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59450</bug>: Correctly handle the case where the
        <code>LegacyCookieProcessor</code> is configured with
        <code>allowHttpSepsInV0</code> set to <code>false</code> and
        <code>forwardSlashIsSeparator</code> set to <code>true</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When scanning JARs for TLDs, correctly handle the (rare) case where a
        JAR has been exploded into <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and the web
        application is deployed as a packed WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59640</bug>: NPEs with not found TLDs. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59189</bug>: Explicitly release the native memory held by the
        <code>Inflater</code> and <code>Deflater</code> when using
        PerMessageDeflate and the WebSocket session ends. Based on a patch by
        Henrik Olsson. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Return back a container specific extension to the WsServerContainer
        to allow frameworks to more easily dispatch requests to WebSocket
        endpoints. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a regression caused by the connector refactoring and ensure that the
        thread context class loader is set to the web application
        classloader when processing WebSocket messages on the server. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that a client disconnection triggers the error handling for the
        associated WebSocket end point. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make WebSocket client more robust when handling errors during the close
        of a WebSocket session. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59210</bug>: Server push example has to use
        <code>o.a.catalina.connector.RequestFacade</code> when obtaining
        <code>o.a.catalina.core.ApplicationPushBuilder</code>. Patch is
        provided by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59218</bug>: Correct the path to <code>jaspic-providers.xml</code>
        in Jaspic How-To. Patch is provided by Tatsuya Bessho. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove button that has accidentally been added to the host manager.
        Submitted by Coty Sutherland. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update in the documentation the link to the maven repository where
        Tomcat snapshot artifacts are deployed. (markt/violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify in the documentation that calls to
        <code>ServletContext.log(String, Throwable)</code> or
        <code>GenericServlet.log(String, Throwable)</code> are logged at the
        SEVERE level. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a typo in SSL/TLS Configuration How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE when a proxy node failed to retrieve a backup entry. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add log of when received an unexpected messages. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the flag indicating that member is a localMember. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix potential NPE that depends on the setting order of attributes of
        static member when using the static cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to
        <code>ChannelInterceptor</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        As with the multicast cluster environment, in the static cluster
        environment, the local member inherits properties from the cluster
        receiver. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to each Channel
        services. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add name to channel in order to identify channels. In tomcat cluster
        environment, it is set the cluster name + "-Channel" as default value.
        (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the channel name to the thread which is invoked by channel services
        in order to identify the associated channel. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that clear the channel instance from channel services when
        stopping channel. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Implement map state in the replication map. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the ping is not executed during the start/stop of the
        replication map. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In ping processing in the replication map, send not the
        <code>INIT</code> message but the newly introduced <code>PING</code>
        message. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59209</bug>: Remove <code>honorCipherOrder=false</code> attribute
        from the connector example in server.xml. When the block is uncommented
        the connector will use the default value for this attribute which is
        <code>false</code>. If one needs to enable it, one can add it
        explicitly to the connector definition. Use of this feature requires
        Java 8 or later. Patch is provided by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59211</bug>: Add hamcrest to Eclipse classpath. Patch is provided
        by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59280</bug>: Update the NSIS Installer used to build the
        Windows Installers to version 2.51. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.7 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2h and APR
        1.5.2. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.0 (markt)" rtext="2016-03-24">
  <subsection name="General">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove support for Comet. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Tighten up the default file permissions for the <code>.tar.gz</code>
        distribution so no files or directories are world readable by default.
        Configure Tomcat to run with a default umask of <code>0027</code> which
        may be overridden by setting <code>UMASK</code> in
        <code>setenv.sh</code>. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove native code (Windows Service Wrapper, APR/native connector)
        support for Windows Itanium. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        The default HTTP cookie parser has been changed to
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.http.Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor creation of <code>MapperListener</code> to ensure that the
        <code>Mapper</code> used is the <code>Mapper</code> associated with the
        <code>Service</code> for which the listener was created. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Move the functionality that provides redirects for context roots and
        directories where a trailing <code>/</code> is added from the Mapper to
        the <code>DefaultServlet</code>. This enables such requests to be
        processed by any configured Valves and Filters before the redirect is
        made. This behaviour is configurable via the
        <code>mapperContextRootRedirectEnabled</code> and
        <code>mapperDirectoryRedirectEnabled</code> attributes of the Context
        which may be used to restore the previous behaviour. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>Service.getContainer()</code> to return an
        <code>Engine</code> rather than a <code>Container</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>34319</bug>: Only load those keys in
        <code>StoreBase.processExpire</code> from JDBCStore that are old enough
        to be expired. Based on a patch by Tom Anderson. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58351</bug>: Make the server build date and server version number
        accessible via JMX. Patch provided by  Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>56917</bug>: As per RFC7231 (HTTP/1.1), allow HTTP/1.1 and later
        redirects to use relative URIs. This is controlled by a new attribute
        <code>useRelativeRedirects</code> on the <strong>Context</strong> and
        defaults to <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58629</bug>: Allow an embedded Tomcat instance to start when the
        <code>Service</code> has no <code>Engine</code> configured. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly notify the MapperListener associated with a Service if the
        Engine for that Service is changed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make a web application's CredentialHandler available through a context
        attribute. This allows a web application to use the same algorithm
        for validating or generating new stored credentials from cleartext
        ones. (schultz)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58635</bug>: Enable break points to be set within agent code when
        running Tomcat with a Java agent. Based on a patch by Huxing Zhang.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed potential NPE in <code>HostConfig</code> while deploying an
        application. Issue reported by coverity scan. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58655</bug>: Fix an <code> IllegalStateException</code> when
        calling <code>HttpServletResponse.sendRedirect()</code> with the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code>. This was caused by trying to correctly
        generate the absolute URI for the redirect. With the fix for
        <bug>56917</bug>, redirects may now be relative making the
        <code>sendRedirect()</code> implementation for the
        <code>RemoteIpFilter</code> much simpler. This also addresses issues
        where the redirect may not have behaved as expected when redirecting
        from http to https to from https to http. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58657</bug>: Exceptions in a Servlet 3.1 <code>ReadListener</code>
        or <code>WriteListener</code> do not need to be immediately fatal to the
        connection. Allow an error response to be written. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct implementation of
        <code>validateClientProvidedNewSessionId</code> so client provided
        session IDs may be rejected if validation is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58701</bug>: Reset the <code>instanceInitialized</code> field in
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> when unloading a Servlet so that a new
        instance may be correctly initialized. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Add a new flag <code>aprPreferred</code> to the Apr listener. if set to
        <code>false</code>, when using the connector defaults, it will use
        NIO + OpenSSL if tomcat-native is available, rather than the APR
        connector. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Add path parameter handling to
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getContextPath()</code>. This is a follow-up to
        the fix for <bug>57215</bug>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58692</bug>: Make <code>StandardJarScanner</code> more robust. Log
        a warning if a class path entry cannot be scanned rather than triggering
        the failure of the web application. Includes a test case written by
         Derek Abdine. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58702</bug>: Ensure an access log entry is generated if the client
        aborts the connection. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed various issues reported by Findbugs. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58735</bug>: Add support for the <code>X-XSS-Protection</code>
        header to the <code>HttpHeaderSecurityFilter</code>. Patch provided by
        Jacopo Cappellato. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add the <code>StatusManagerServlet</code> to the list of Servlets that
        can only be loaded by privileged applications. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Simplify code and fix messages in
        <code>org.apache.catalina.core.DefaultInstanceManager</code> class.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58751</bug>: Correctly handle the case where an
        <code>AsyncListener</code> dispatches to a Servlet on an asynchronous
        timeout and the Servlet uses <code>sendError()</code> to trigger an
        error page. Includes a test case based on code provided by Andy
        Wilkinson.(markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the proper file encoding, if specified, will be used when
        a readme file is served by DefaultServlet. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix declaration of <code>localPort</code> attribute of Connector MBean:
        it is read-only. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58766</bug>: Make skipping non-class files during annotation
        scanning faster by checking the file name first. Improve debug logging.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58768</bug>: Log a warning if a redirect fails because of an
        invalid location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        <bug>58827</bug>: Remove remains of JSR-77 implementation. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>58836</bug>: Correctly merge query string parameters when
        processing a forwarded request where the target includes a query string
        that contains a parameter with no value. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make sure that shared Digester is reset in an unlikely error case
        in <code>HostConfig.deployWAR()</code>. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Extend the feature available in the cluster session manager
        implementations that enables session attribute replication to be
        filtered based on attribute name to all session manager implementations.
        Note that configuration attribute name has changed from
        <code>sessionAttributeFilter</code> to
        <code>sessionAttributeNameFilter</code>. Apply the filter on load as
        well as unload to ensure that configuration changes made while the web
        application is stopped are applied to any persisted data. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Extend the session attribute filtering options to include filtering
        based on the implementation class of the value and optional
        <code>WARN</code> level logging if an attribute is filtered. These
        options are available for all of the Manager implementations that ship
        with Tomcat. When a <code>SecurityManager</code> is used filtering will
        be enabled by default. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Remove <code>distributable</code> and <code>maxInactiveInterval</code>
        from the <code>Manager</code> interface because the attributes are never
        used. The equivalent attributes from the <code>Context</code> always
        take precedence. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>58867</bug>: Improve checking on Host start for WAR files that have
        been modified while Tomcat has stopped and re-expand them if
        <code>unpackWARs</code> is <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58900</bug>: Correctly undeploy symlinked resources and prevent an
        infinite cycle of deploy / undeploy. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Protect initialization of <code>ResourceLinkFactory</code> when
        running with a SecurityManager. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a thread safety issue in the filtering of session attributes
        based on the implementing class name of the value object. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix class loader decision on the delegation for class loading and
        resource lookup and make it faster too. (rjung)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58905</bug>: Ensure that <code>Tomcat.silence()</code> silences the
        correct logger and respects the current setting. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58946</bug>: Ensure that the request parameter map remains
        immutable when processing via a RequestDispatcher. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>/WEB-INF/classes</code> is never processed as a web
        fragment. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Switch default connector when native is installed. Unless configured
        otherwise, the NIO endpoint will be used by default. If SSL is
        configured, OpenSSL will be used rather than JSSE. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>58867</bug>. When configuring a
        Context to use an external directory for the <code>docBase</code>, and
        that directory happens to be located along side the original WAR, use
        the directory as the <code>docBase</code> rather than expanding the
        WAR into the <code>appBase</code> and using the newly created expanded
        directory as the <code>docBase</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58988</bug>: Special characters in the substitutions for the
        RewriteValve can now be quoted with a backslash. (fschumacher)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58999</bug>: Fix class and resource name filtering in
        WebappClassLoader. It throws a StringIndexOutOfBoundsException if the
        name is exactly "org" or "javax". (rjung)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add JASPIC (JSR-196) support. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Make checking for var and map replacement in RewriteValve a bit stricter
        and correct detection of colon in var replacement. (fschumacher)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Refactor the web application class loader to reduce the impact of JAR
        scanning on the memory footprint of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix some resource leaks in the error handling for accessing files from
        JARs and WARs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the JAR and JAR-in-WAR resource handling to reduce the memory
        footprint of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the web.xml parsing so a new parser is created every time the
        web application starts rather than creating and caching the parser when
        the Context is created. This enables the parser to take account of
        modified Context configuration parameters and reduces (slightly) the
        memory footprint of a running Tomcat instance. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Switch the web application class loader to the
        <code>ParallelWebappClassLoader</code> by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>57809</bug>: Remove the custom context attribute that held the
        effective web.xml. Components needing access to configuration
        information may access it via the Servlet API. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor JAR scanning to reduce memory footprint. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59001</bug>: Correctly handle the case when Tomcat is installed on
        a path where one of the segments ends in an exclamation mark. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Expand the fix for <bug>59001</bug> to cover the special sequences used
        in Tomcat&apos;s custom jar:war: URLs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59043</bug>: Avoid warning while expiring sessions associated with
        a single sign on if <code>HttpServletRequest.logout()</code> is used.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59054</bug>: Ensure that using the
        <code>CrawlerSessionManagerValve</code> in a distributed environment
        does not trigger an error when the Valve registers itself in the
        session. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add socket properties support to storeconfig. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix incorrect parsing of the NE and NC flags in rewrite rules. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59065</bug>: Correct the timing of the check for colons in paths
        on non-Windows systems implemented in <code>catalina.sh</code> so it
        works correctly with Cygwin. Patch provided by Ed Randall. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When a Host is configured with an appBase that does not exist, create
        the appBase before trying to expand an external WAR file into it.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
       <bug>59115</bug>: When using the Servlet 3.0 file upload, the submitted
       file name may be provided as a token or a quoted-string. If a
       quoted-string, unquote the string before returning it to the user.
       (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59123</bug>: Close <code>NamingEnumeration</code> objects used by
        the <code>JNDIRealm</code> once they are no longer required.
        (fschumacher/markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Implement the proposed Servlet 4.0 API to provide mapping type
        information for the current request. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59138</bug>: Correct a false positive warning for ThreadLocal
        related memory leaks when the key class but not the value class has been
        loaded by the web application class loader. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>59017</bug>: Make the pre-compressed file support in the Default
        Servlet generic so any compression may be used rather than just gzip.
        Patch provided by Mikko Tiihonen. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59145</bug>: Don't log an invalid warning when a user logs out of
        a session associated with SSO. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59150</bug>: Add an additional flag on APR listener to allow
        disabling automatic use of OpenSSL. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59151</bug>: Fix a regression in the fix for <bug>56917</bug> that
        added additional (and arguably unnecessary) validation to the provided
        redirect location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59154</bug>: Fix a <code>NullPointerException</code> in the
        <code>JAASMemoryLoginModule</code> resulting from the introduction of
        the <code>CredentialHandler</code> to <code>Realm</code>s.
        (schultz/markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove support for the HTTP BIO and AJP BIO connectors. (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor HTTP upgrade and AJP implementations to reduce duplication.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Add support for HPACK header encoding and decoding, contributed
        by Stuart Douglas. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>57108</bug>: Add support for Server Name Indication (SNI). There
        has been significant changes to the SSL configuration in server.xml to
        support this. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add SSL engine for JSSE backed by OpenSSL. Includes ALPN support.
        Based on code contributed by Numa de Montmollin and derived from code
        developed by Twitter and Netty. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        RFC 7230 states that clients should ignore reason phrases in HTTP/1.1
        response messages. Since the reason phrase is optional, Tomcat no longer
        sends it. As a result the system property
        <code>org.apache.coyote.USE_CUSTOM_STATUS_MSG_IN_HEADER</code> is no
        longer used and has been removed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        The minimum required Tomcat Native version has been increased to 1.2.2.
        The 1.2.x branch includes ALPN and SNI support which are required for
        HTTP/2. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add support for HTTP/2 including server push. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>58621</bug>: The certificate chain cannot be set using the main
        certificate attribute, so restore the certificate chain property. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow a new SSL config type where a connector can use either JSSE or
        OpenSSL. Both could be allowed, but it would likely create support
        issues. This type is used by the OpenSSL implementation for NIOx. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve upgrade context classloader handling by using Context.bind and
        unbind. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Improve OpenSSL keystore/truststore configuration by using the code
        from the JSSE implementation. (remm, jfclere)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix a potential loop when a client drops the connection unexpectedly.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        OpenSSL renegotiation support for client certificate authentication.
        (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix NIO connector renegotiation. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58659</bug>: Fix a potential deadlock during HTTP/2 processing when
        the connection window size is limited. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct an NPE when listing the enabled ciphers (e.g. via the Manager
        web application) for a TLS enabled APR/native connector. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        New configuration option <code>ajpFlush</code> for the AJP connectors
        to disable the sending of AJP flush packets. (rjung)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Handle the case in the NIO connector where the required TLS buffer sizes
        increase after the connection has been initiated. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Handle the case in the NIO2 connector where the required TLS buffer
        sizes increase after the connection has been initiated. (markt/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Bad processing of handshake errors in NIO2. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use JSSE session configuration options with OpenSSL. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59015</bug>: Fix potential cause of endless APR Poller loop during
        shutdown if the Poller experiences an error during the shutdown process.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Align cipher aliases for <code>kECDHE</code> and <code>ECDHE</code> with
        the current OpenSSL implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59081</bug>: Retain the user defined cipher order when defining
        ciphers. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59089</bug>: Correctly ignore HTTP headers that include non-token
        characters in the header name. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>57136#c25</bug>: Change default value of
        <code>quoteAttributeEL</code> setting in Jasper to be <code>true</code>
        for better compatibility with other implementations and older versions
        of Tomcat. Add command line option <code>-no-quoteAttributeEL</code> in
        JspC. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix handling of missing messages in
        <code>org.apache.el.util.MessageFactory</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update to the Eclipse JDT Compiler 4.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>57583</bug>: Improve the performance of
        <code>javax.servlet.jsp.el.ScopedAttributeELResolver</code> when
        resolving attributes that do not exist. This improvement only works when
        Jasper is used with Tomcat's EL implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable an explicit configuration of local member in the static cluster
        membership. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>DeltaSession</code>.
        Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid that the heartbeat thread and the background thread to
        run <code>Channel.heartbeat</code> simultaneously, if
        <code>heartbeatBackgroundEnabled</code> of <code>SimpleTcpCluster</code>
        set to <code>true</code>, ensure that the heartbeat thread does not
        start. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>55006</bug>: The WebSocket client now honors the
        <code>java.net.java.net.ProxySelector</code> configuration (using the
        HTTP type) when establishing WebSocket connections to servers. Based on
        a patch by Niki Dokovski. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>57489</bug>: Ensure <code>onClose()</code> is called when a
        WebSocket connection is closed even if the sending of the close message
        fails. Includes test cases by Barry Coughlan. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58624</bug>: Correct a potential deadlock if the WebSocket
        connection is closed when a message write is in progress. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a timing issue on session close that could result in an exception
        being thrown for an incomplete message even through the message was
        completed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle compression of partial messages when the final message
        fragment has a zero length payload. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59119</bug>: Correct read logic for WebSocket client when using
        secure connections. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59134</bug>: Correct client connect logic for secure connections
        made through a proxy. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>48674</bug>: Implement an option within the Host Manager web
        application to persist the current configuration. Based on a patch by
        Coty Sutherland. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58631</bug>: Correct the continuation character use in the Windows
        Service How-To page of the documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the SSL documentation for deprecated attributes to point to the
        correct, new location for attributes related to individual certificates.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct some typos in the JNDI resources How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Don't create session unnecessarily in the Host Manager application.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58723</bug>: Clarify documentation and error messages for the text
        interface of the manager to make clear that version must be used with
        path when referencing contexts deployed using parallel deployment.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Document <code>test.threads</code> option in BUILDING.txt. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correct an error in the documentation of the expected behaviour for
        automatic deployment. If a WAR is updated and an expanded directory is
        present, the directory will always be deleted and recreated by expanding
        the WAR if <code>unpackWARs</code> is <code>true</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58935</bug>: Remove incorrect references in the documentation to
        using <code>jar:file:</code> URLs with the Manager application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the description of the
        <code>ServletRequest.getServerPort()</code> in Proxy How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <add>
        The Manager and Host Manager applications are now only accessible via
        <code>localhost</code> by default. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Clarify the handling of Copy message and Copy nodes. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the static member is registered to the add suspect list even
        if the static member that is registered to the remove suspect list has
        disappeared. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When using a static cluster, add the members that have been cached in
        the membership service to the map members list in order to ensure that
        the map member is a static member. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for the startup notification of local members in the static
        cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ignore the unnecessary member remove operation from different domain.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add support for the shutdown notification of local members in the static
        cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        If promoting a proxy node to a primary node when getting a session,
        notify the change of the new primary node to the original backup node.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct evaluation of system property
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.jdbc.pool.onlyAttemptCurrentClassLoader</code>.
        It was basically ignored before. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix potential integer overflow in <code>ConnectionPool</code> and
        <code>PooledConnection</code>. Reported by coverity scan. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Allow to configure multiple JUnit test class patterns with the build
        property <code>test.name</code> and document the property in
        BUILDING.txt. (rjung)
      </add>
      <add>
        Support the use of the <code>threads</code> attribute on Ant&apos;s
        junit task. Note that using this with a value of greater than one will
        disable Cobertura code coverage. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.14.1. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.4 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2e and APR
        1.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the NSIS Installer used to build the Windows Installers to
        version 2.50. (markt/kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons BCEL to r1725718 to align with the
        refactoring for BCEL 6, the next major BCEL release. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to r1725730 (2.1.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to r1725738 (2.4.2 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Codec to r1725746 (1.9 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>58283</bug>: Change the default download location for libraries
        during the build process from <code>/usr/share/java</code> to
        <code>${user.home}/temp</code>. Patch provided by Ahmed Hosni. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59031</bug>: When using the Windows uninstaller, do not remove the
        contents of any directories that have been symlinked into the Tomcat
        directory structure. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.5 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2g and APR
        1.5.1. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Modify the default <code>tomcat-users.xml</code> file to make it harder
        for users to configure the entries intended for use with the examples
        web application for the Manager application. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
