<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix/scode.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues (i.e., numbered
  issues do not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M8 (markt)" rtext="in development">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64582</bug>: Pre-load the <code>CoyoteOutputStream</code> class to
        prevent a potential exception when running under a security manager.
        Patch provided by Johnathan Gilday. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64593</bug>: If a request is not matched to a Context, delay
        issuing the 404 response to give the rewrite valve, if configured, an
        opportunity to rewrite the request. (remm/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Change top package name for generated emebedded classes to avoid
        conflict with default host name on case insensitive filesystems.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add missing code generation for remaining digester rules. (remm)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Add a dedicated loader for generated code to avoid dynamic class
        loading. (remm)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove deprecated <code>CookieProcessor.generateHeader</code> method.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the implementation of
        <code>ServletInputStream.available()</code> to provide a more accurate
        return value, particularly when end of stream has been reached. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Requests received via proxies may be marked as using the <code>ws</code>
        or <code>wss</code> protocol rather than <code>http</code> or
        <code>https</code>. Ensure that such requests are not rejected. PR
        provided by Ronny Perinke. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a potential issue where the write lock for a WebSocket connection
        may not be released if an exception occurs during the write. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Remove the localization of the text output of the Manager application
        list of contexts and the Host Manager application list of hosts so that
        the output is more consistent. PR provided by Holomark. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clean-up / standardize the XSL files used to generate the documentation.
        PR provided by John Bampton. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>62723</bug>: Clarify the effects of some options for cluster
        <code>channelSendOptions</code>. Patch provided by Mitch Claborn.
        (schultz)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>64540</bug> and include
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.modeler.modules</code> and
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.net.jsse</code> in the list of exported
        packages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove the local copy of the <code>javax.transaction.xa</code> package
        which is only used during compilation. The package is provided by the
        JRE from Java 1.4 onwards so the local copy should be unnecessary.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Rename the local copy of the <code>javax.xml.ws</code> package to
        <code>jakarta.xml.ws</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M7 (markt)" rtext="2020-07-05">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Remove the error message on start if <code>java.io.tmpdir</code> is
        missing and add an explicit error message on application deployment when
        the sole feature that depends on it (anti-resource locking) is
        configured and can't be used. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Implement a significant portion of the TLS environment variables for
        the rewrite valve. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add the Jakarta EE 9 schema. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64506</bug>: Correct a potential race condition in the resource
        cache implementation that could lead to
        <code>NullPointerException</code>s during class loading. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add <code>application/wasm</code> to the media types recognised by
        Tomcat. Based on a PR by Thiago Henrique Hüpner. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix a bug in <code>HttpServlet</code> so that a <code>405</code>
        response is returned for an HTTP/2 request if the mapped servlet does
        implement the requested method rather than the more general
        <code>400</code> response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add generated classes using Tomcat embedded as an optional replacement
        for the Catalina configuration files. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64541</bug>: Refactor the DTD used to validate
        <code>mbeans-descriptors.xml</code> files to avoid issues when XML
        entity expansion is limited or disabled. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Include a <code>Connection: close</code> HTTP header when committing a
        response and it is known that the <code>maxSwallowSize</code> limit is
        going to be exceeded. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64509</bug>: Correctly parse RFC 2109 version 1 cookies that use a
        comma as a separator between cookies when using the RFC 6265 cookie
        processor. Based on a patch by W J Carpenter. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix the utility code that converted IPv6 addresses to a canonical form
        to correctly handle input addresses that ended with a pair of colons.
        Based on a patch by syarramsetty-skyhook. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correctly parse RFC 2109 version 1 cookies that have additional linear
        white space around cookie attribute names and values when using the RFC
        6265 cookie processor. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Once an HTTP/2 stream has been closed, ensure that the code that cleans
        up references that are no longer required is called. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Reduce the memory footprint of closed HTTP/2 streams. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the HTTP/1.1 processor is correctly recycled when a direct
        connection to h2c is made. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the JSP document validation to permit <code>3.0</code> as a valid
        version attribute for the <code>&lt;jsp-root&gt;</code> element. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64560</bug>: Refactor the replication of a changed session ID for a
        replicated session so that the list of changes associated with the
        session is not reset when the session ID changes. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64563</bug>: Add additional validation of payload length for
        WebSocket messages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the calculation of payload length when four or more bytes are
        required to represent the payload length. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update all web applications to use the Jakarta EE 9 schema for web.xml.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix incorrect version format in OSGi manifests. Patch provided by
        Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64513</bug>: Remove bndlib from dependencies as it is not required.
        Pull request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64515</bug>: Bnd files don't need to be filtered (save some work).
        Pull request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the OWB module to Apache OpenWebBeans 2.0.17. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64514</bug>: Fixes some missing class dependency issues in bootstrap
        to address packaging/dependency concerns for JPMS and OSGi. Pull request
        provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64521</bug>: Avoid moving i18n translations into classes dir since
        they are packaged into separate jars. Pull request provided by Raymond
        Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64522</bug>: Package jars in effective dependency order. Pull
        request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Store common build details in a shared build-defaults.bnd. Pull
        request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64532</bug>: Update to bnd 5.1.1. Pull request provided by Raymond
        Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64540</bug>: Switch from bndwrap task to bnd task, begin generating
        a better manifest and make sure the resulting jar contents are correct.
        Pull request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64544</bug>: Add built libs to the bnd classpath for introspection.
        Pull request provided by Raymond Augé. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Improve the quality and expand the coverage of the French translations
        provided with Apache Tomcat. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64548</bug>: Generate JPMS metadata. (rotty3000)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M6 (markt)" rtext="2020-06-07">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64432</bug>: Correct a refactoring regression that broke handling
        of multi-line configuration in the RewriteValve. Patch provided by Jj.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix use of multiple parameters when defining RewriteMaps.
        (remm/fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Add the special internal rewrite maps for case modification and
        escaping. (remm/fschumacher)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in an earlier fix that broke the loading of
        configuration files such as keystores via URIs on Windows. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Implement a few rewrite SSL env that correspond to Servlet request
        attributes. (remm)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>64442</bug>: Be more flexible with respect to the ordering of
        groups, roles and users in the <code>tomcat-users.xml</code> file.
        (fschumacher)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Add support for ALPN on recent OpenJDK 8 releases. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64467</bug>: Improve performance of closing idle HTTP/2 streams.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Expose server certificate through the <code>SSLSupport</code>
        interface. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>64483</bug>: Log a warning if an AJP request is rejected because it
        contains an unexpected request attribute. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64485</bug>: Fix possible resource leak getting last modified from
        <code>ConfigurationSource.Resource</code>. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the Jakarta Server Pages API implementation to align with
        specification updates to use generics and add missing
        <code>@Deprecated</code> annotations. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64488</bug>: Ensure that the ImportHandler from the Expression
        Language API is able to load classes from the Java runtime when running
        under a SecurityManager. Based on a patch by Volodymyr Siedleck. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add default implementations for <code>init()</code> and
        <code>destroy()</code> to the <code>Encoder</code> and
        <code>Decoder</code> interfaces. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Consistently throw a <code>DeploymentException</code> when an invalid
        endpoint path is specified and catch invalid endpoint paths earlier.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Include the target URL in the log message when a WebSocket connection
        fails. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the list of known <code>Charset</code>s in the
        <code>CharsetCache</code> to include <code>ISO-8859-16</code>, added in
        OpenJDK 15. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Improve the quality and expand the coverage of the French translations
        provided with Apache Tomcat. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>64430</bug>: Add support for the <code>CATALINA_OUT_CMD</code>
        environment variable that defines a command to which captured stdout and
        stderr will be redirected. Patch provided by Harald Dunkel. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Switch from the unsupported Maven Ant Tasks to the supported Maven
        Resolver Ant Tasks to upload artifacts to the ASF Maven repository (and
        from there to Maven Central). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update dependency on bnd to 5.1.0. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M5 (markt)" rtext="2020-05-11">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove <code>useAprConnector</code> flag from
        <code>AprLifecycleListener</code> so that the only way to use the APR
        connectors is to set the full class name. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>59203</bug>: Before calling <code>Thread.stop()</code> (if
        configured to do so) on a web application created thread that is not
        stopped by the web application when the web application is stopped, try
        interrupting the thread first. Based on a pull request by Govinda
        Sakhare. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>62912</bug>: Don't mutate an application provided content header if
        it does not contain a charset. Also remove the outdated workaround for
        the buggy Adobe Reader 9 plug-in for IE. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>reloadable</code> attribute from the
        <code>Loader</code> interface as it is duplicated on the
        <code>Context</code> interface. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Reduce reflection use and remove AJP specific code in the Connector.
        (remm/markt/fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Rework the fix for <bug>64021</bug> to better support web applications
        that use a custom class loader that loads resources from non-standard
        locations. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Remove redundant sole path/URI from error page message on SC_NOT_FOUND.
        (michaelo)
      </update>
      <add>
        Log a warning if a <code>CredentialHandler</code> instance is added to
        an instance of the <code>CombinedRealm</code> (or a sub-class) as the
        <code>CombinedRealm</code> doesn't use a configured
        <code>CredentialHandler</code> and it is likely that a configuration
        error has occurred. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add more descriptive error message in DefaultServlet for SC_NOT_FOUND.
        (michaelo)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64309</bug>: Improve the regular expression used to search for
        class loader repositories when bootstrapping Tomcat. Pull request
        provided by Paul Muriel Biya-Bi. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64384</bug>: Fix multipart configuration ignoring some parameters
        in some cases. (schultz)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>64386</bug>: WebdavServlet does not send "getlastmodified"
        property for resource collections. (michaelo)
      </add>
      <update>
        Remove reason phrase on WebDAV Multi-Status (207) response. (michaelo)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64398</bug>: Change default value separator for property
        replacement to <code>:-</code> due to possible conflicts. The
        syntax is now <code>${name:-default}</code>. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Improve validation of storage location when using FileStore. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Move <code>SocketProperties</code> mbean to its own type rather than
        use a subType to improve robustness with tools. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Include the problematic data in the error message when reporting that
        the provided request line contains an invalid component. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the handling of requests that use an expectation. Do not disable
        keep-alive where the response has a non-2xx status code but the request
        body has been fully read. (rjung/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64403</bug>: Ensure that compressed HTTP/2 responses are not sent
        with a content length header appropriate for the original, uncompressed
        response. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Remove redundant sole path/URI from error page message on SC_NOT_FOUND.
        (michaelo)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add more descriptive error message in DefaultServlet for SC_NOT_FOUND.
        (michaelo)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64373</bug>: When a tag file is packaged in a WAR and then that WAR
        is unpacked in <code>/WEB-INF/classes</code> ensure that the tag file
        can still be found. Patch provided by Karl von Randow. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the Jasper code that interfaces with the Eclipse Compiler
        for Java (ECJ) enables Jasper to compile JSPs using ECJ 4.14 onwards
        when the JSPs have inner classes. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Refactor Tribes BufferPool and add the
        <code>org.apache.catalina.tribes.io.BufferPool.DEFAULT_POOL_SIZE</code>
        system property to configure its size. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove java.io based Tribes receiver and sender, in favor of NIO which
        was the default. (remm)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix the saving of a Context configuration file via the scripting
        interface of the Manager web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a section to the TLS Connector documentation on different key store
        types and how to configure them. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update JUnit to version 4.13. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Add missing entries to test class path in sample NetBeans configuration
        files. Patch provided by Brian Burch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor to use parameterized <code>Collection</code> constructors where
        possible. Pull request provided by Lars Grefer. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Refactor to use empty arrays with <code>Collections.toArray()</code>.
        Pull request provided by Lars Grefer. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Refactor loops with a condition to exit as soon as the condition is met.
        Pull request provided by Lars Grefer. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Refactor bulk addition to collections to use <code>addAll()</code>
        rather than a loop. Pull request provided by Lars Grefer. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the Chinese translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. Contributions provided by winsonzhao, ZhangJieWen and Lee
        Yazhou. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Improve the quality and expand the coverage of the French translations
        provided with Apache Tomcat. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        Improve the quality of the Japanese translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. Includes contributions from Yoshy. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Improve the quality of the German translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.24.
        (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Refactor to use enhanced for loops where possible. Pull request by Lars
        Grefer. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Improve IDE support for IntelliJ IDEA. Patch provided by Lars Grefer.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Improve the coverage and quality of the Korean translations provided
        with Apache Tomcat. (woonsan)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update dependency on bnd to 5.0.1. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M4 (markt)" rtext="2020-04-08">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure all URL patterns provided via web.xml are %nn decoded
        consistently using the encoding of the web.xml file where specified and
        UTF-8 where no explicit encoding is specified. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Allow a comma separated list of class names for the
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.digester.PROPERTY_SOURCE</code>
        system property. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64149</bug>: Avoid NPE when using the access log valve without
        a pattern. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64226</bug>: Reset timezone after parsing a date since the date
        format is reused. Test case submitted by Gary Thomas. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64247</bug>: Using a wildcard for <code>jarsToSkip</code> should
        not override a possibly present <code>jarsToScan</code>. Based on code
        submitted by Iridias. (remm)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Refactor DefaultServlet to avoid using an internal Range structure that
        is duplicated from the parsing result. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.connector.CoyoteAdapter.ALLOW_BACKSLASH</code>
        system property, replaced by the <code>allowBackslash</code> attribute
        on the Connector. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.connector.Response.ENFORCE_ENCODING_IN_GET_WRITER</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>enforceEncodingInGetWriter</code> attribute on the Connector.
        (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.session.StandardSession.ACTIVITY_CHECK</code>
        system property, replaced by the <code>sessionActivityCheck</code> attribute
        on the Manager. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.session.StandardSession.LAST_ACCESS_AT_START</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>sessionLastAccessAtStart</code> attribute on the Manager. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.core.StandardHostValve.ACCESS_SESSION</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>alwaysAccessSession</code> attribute on the Context. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.core.ApplicationContext.GET_RESOURCE_REQUIRE_SLASH</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>contextGetResourceRequiresSlash</code> attribute on the Context. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.core.ApplicationDispatcher.WRAP_SAME_OBJECT</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>dispatcherWrapsSameObject</code> attribute on the Context. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64265</bug>: Fix ETag comparison performed by the default servlet.
        The default servlet always uses weak comparison. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Remove
        <code>org.apache.catalina.authenticator.Constants.SSO_SESSION_COOKIE_NAME</code>
        system property, replaced by the
        <code>cookieName</code> attribute on the SSO valve. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Add support for default values when using <code>${...}</code> property
        replacement in configuration files. Based on a pull request provided by
        Bernd Bohmann. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When closing a NIO channel, avoid canceling keys as a workaround for
        deadlocks when running on Java 11. Excessive internal NIO
        synchronization on channel close is resolved starting with this
        Java version. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        When configuring an HTTP Connector, ensure that the encoding specified
        for <code>URIEncoding</code> is a superset of US-ASCII as required by
        RFC7230. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Avoid always retrieving the NIO poller selection key when processing
        to reduce sync. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64240</bug>: Ensure that HTTP/0.9 requests that contain additional
        data on the request line after the URI are treated consistently. Such
        requests will now always be treated as HTTP/1.1. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Expose the HTTP/2 connection ID and stream ID to applications via the
        request attributes <code>org.apache.coyote.connectionID</code> and
        <code>org.apache.coyote.streamID</code> respectively. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Replace the system property
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.buf.UDecoder.ALLOW_ENCODED_SLASH</code>
        with the Connector attribute <code>encodedSolidusHandling</code> that
        adds an additional option to pass the <code>%2f</code> sequence through
        to the application without decoding it in addition to rejecting such
        sequences and decoding such sequences. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Expose the associated <code>HttpServletRequest</code> to the
        <code>CookieProcessor</code> when generating a cookie header so the
        header can be tailored based on the properties of the request, such as
        the user agent, if required. Based on a patch by Lazar Kirchev. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update to the Eclipse JDT compiler 4.15. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add support for specifying Java 14 (with the value <code>14</code>) and
        Java 15 (with the value <code>15</code>) as the compiler source and/or
        compiler target for JSP compilation. If used with an ECJ version that
        does not support these values, a warning will be logged and the latest
        supported version will used. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Remove Jasper configuration using system properties and replace them
        by a new set of JSP Servlet init parameters. (remm)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct the documentation web application to remove references to the
        <code>org.apache.catalina.STRICT_SERVLET_COMPLIANCE</code> system
        property changing the default for the <code>URIEncoding</code> attribute
        of the Connector. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the documentation web application to remove references to the
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.buf.UDecoder.ALLOW_ENCODED_SLASH</code>
        system property changing how the sequence <code>%5c</code> is
        interpreted in a URI. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove support for the deprecated system property
        <code>org.apache.catalina.tribes.dns_lookups</code>. The default value
        of <code>false</code> will now always be used. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Improve the quality and expand the coverage of the French translations
        provided with Apache Tomcat. Contribution provided by Tom Bens. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the Chinese translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. Contribution provided by Lee Yazhou. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64270</bug>: Set the documented default umask of <code>0027</code>
        when using jsvc via <code>daemon.sh</code> and allow the umask used to
        be configured via the <code>UMASK</code> environment variable as it is
        when using <code>catalina.sh</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the OWB module to Apache OpenWebBeans 2.0.16. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the CXF module to Apache CXF 3.3.6. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Remove the <code>LOGGING_CONFIG</code> environment variable and
        replace it with the <code>CATALINA_LOGGING_CONFIG</code> environment
        variable to avoid clashes with other components that use
        <code>LOGGING_CONFIG</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M3 (markt)" rtext="2020-03-16">
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64202</bug>: Use a loop on NIO blocking reads, as it is possible
        zero bytes are produced by a network read. (markt/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64210</bug>: Correct a regression in the improvements to HTTP
        header validation that caused requests to be incorrectly treated as
        invalid if a <code>CRLF</code> sequence was split between TCP packets.
        Improve validation of request lines, including for HTTP/0.9 requests.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>64206</bug>: Correct a regression introduced in 10.0.0-M1 that
        meant that the HTTP port specified when using the Windows Installer was
        ignored and 8080 was always used. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M2 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>HttpServlet.doOptions()</code> to improve performance.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Disable StandardManager session persistence by default. It can be
        enabled back in <code>context.xml</code>. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add extension point to DeltaSession to improve subclassing.
        Patch provided by ThStock. (schultz)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64153</bug>: Ensure that the parent for the web application class
        loader is set consistently. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64166</bug>: Ensure that the names returned by
        <code>HttpServletResponse.getHeaderNames()</code> are unique. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Rename <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.digester.Digester$EnvironmentPropertySource</code>
        to
        <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.digester.EnvironmentPropertySource</code>.
        Patch provided by Bernd Bohmann. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>63286</bug>: Resolve inconsistencies with access log valve. This
        changes the element API to use a nanosecond resolution elapsed time
        argument. (remm)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add new attribute <code>persistAuthentication</code> to both
        <code>StandardManager</code> and <code>PersistentManager</code> to
        support authentication persistence. Patch provided by Carsten Klein.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>64184</bug>: Avoid repeated log messages if a
        <code>MemoryUserDatabase</code> is configured but the specified
        configuration file is missing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>64189</bug>: Expose the web application version String as a
        <code>ServletContext</code> attribute named
        <code>org.apache.catalina.webappVersion</code>. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix support of native jakarta servlet attributes in AJP connector.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>56966</bug>: Add use of System.nanoTime to track request
        execution time. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>64141</bug>: If using a CA certificate, remove a default value
        for the truststore file when not using a JSSE configuration. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve robustness of OpenSSLEngine shutdown. Based on code submitted
        by Manuel Dominguez Sarmiento. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add the TLS request attributes used by IIS to the attributes that an AJP
        Connector will always accept. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        A zero length AJP secret will now behave as if it has not been
        specified. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64188</bug>: If an error occurs while committing or flushing the
        response when using a multiplexing protocol like HTTP/2 that requires
        the channel to be closed but not the connection, just close the channel
        and allow the other channels using the connection to continue. Based on
        a suggestion from Alejandro Anadon. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct the semantics of <code>getEnableSessionCreation</code> and
        <code>setEnableSessionCreation</code> for <code>OpenSSLEngine</code>.
        Pull request provided by Alexander Scheel. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>64192</bug>: Correctly handle case where unread data is returned to
        the read buffer when the read buffer is non empty. Ensure a gathering
        TLS read stops once the provided ByteBuffers are full or no more data is
        available. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Allow async requests to complete cleanly when the Connector is paused
        before <code>complete()</code> is called on a container thread. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Allow configuring the <code>DNSMembershipProvider</code> using the
        <code>dns</code> alias. Submitted by Bernd Bohmann. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Expand the documentation for the <code>address</code> attribute of the
        AJP Connector and document that the AJP Connector also supports the
        <code>ipv6v6only</code> attribute with the APR/Native implementation.
        (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the OWB module to Apache OpenWebBeans 2.0.15. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the CXF module to Apache CXF 3.3.5. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the Korean translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. Contributions provided by B. Cansmile Cha. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the French translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>64190</bug>: Add support for specifying milliseconds (using
        <code>S</code>, <code>SS</code> or <code>SSS</code>) in the timestamp
        used by JULI&apos;s <code>OneLineFormatter</code>. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 10.0.0-M1 (markt)" rtext="2020-02-20">
  <subsection name="General">
    <scode>
      This release contains all of the changes upto and including those in
      Apache Tomcat 9.0.31 plus the additional changes listed below. (markt)
    </scode>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Refactor recycle facade system property into a new connector attribute
        named <code>discardFacades</code> and enable it by default. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update to Jakarta Servlet 5.0, Jakarta Server Pages 3.0. Jakarta
        Expression Language 4.0, Jakarta WebSocket 2.0, Jakarta Authentication
        2.0 and Jakarta Annotations 2.0. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove GenericPrincipal.getPassword. The credentials should remain
        managed by the realm. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Add connection pooling to JNDI realm. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Use <code>&lt;request-character-encoding&gt;</code> and
        <code>&lt;response-character-encoding&gt;</code> in
        <code>conf/web.xml</code> to set the default request and response
        character encodings to UTF-8. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Store config compatibility with HostWebXmlCacheCleaner listener. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify the <code>RewriteValve</code> to use
        <code>ServletRequest.getServerName()</code> to populate the
        <code>HTTP_HOST</code> variable rather than extracting it from the
        <code>Host</code> header as this allows HTTP/2 to be supported. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Switch Tomcat embedded to loading MIME type mappings from a property
        file generated from the default <code>web.xml</code> so the MIME type
        mappings are consistent regardless of how Tomcat is started. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Missing store config attributes for Resources elements. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update endpoint cache sizes defaults. (remm)
      </update>
      <update>
        Remove unused NIO blocking selector. (remm)
      </update>
      <add>
        When using an AJP Connector, convert Java Servlet specific request
        attributes to the Jakarta Servlet equivalent. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        When reporting / logging invalid HTTP headers encode any non-printing
        characters using the 0xNN form. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Remove duplication of HTTP/1.1 configuration on the HTTP/2
        UpgradeProtocol element. Configuration from the main Connector element
        will now be used. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        When the NIO or APR/native connectors were configured with
        <code>useAsyncIO="true"</code> and a zero length read or write was
        performed, the read/write would time out rather than return immediately.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Parameterize JSP version and API class names in localization messages to
        allow simpler re-use between major versions. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Ensure that TLD files listed in the <code>jsp-config</code> section of
        <code>web.xml</code> that are registered in the
        <code>uriTldResourcePathMap</code> with the URI specified in
        <code>web.xml</code> are also registered with the URI in the TLD file if
        it is different. Patch provided by Markus Lottmann. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix cloud environment lookup order and add a dedicated
        <code>DNS_MEMBERSHIP_SERVICE_NAME</code> environment for use with the
        DNS membership provider. Submitted by Bernd Bohmann. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>53620</bug>: JULI now only creates logging files when there is a
        log entry to write. Based on a patch by Karol Bucek. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update implemented specification version information in a few places
        where it has not been updated for Jakarta EE 9. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the French translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        Expand the coverage of the Chinese translations provided with Apache
        Tomcat. Contribution provided by BoltzmannWxd. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
