<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, jdbc-pool, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix/scode.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues do not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.5">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>18500</bug>: Add limited support for wildcard host names and host
        aliases. Names of the form <code>*.domainname</code> are now permitted.
        Note that an exact host name match takes precedence over a wild card
        host name match. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59813</bug>: Ensure that circular relations of the Class-Path
        attribute from JAR manifests will be processed correctly. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that reading the <code>singleThreadModel</code> attribute of a
        <code>StandardWrapper</code> via JMX does not trigger initialisation of
        the associated servlet. With some frameworks this can trigger an
        unexpected initialisation thread and if initilisation is not thread-safe
        the initialisation can then fail. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Compatibility with rewrite from httpd for non existing headers.
        (jfclere)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        By default, treat paths used to obtain a request dispatcher as encoded.
        This behaviour can be changed per web application via the
        <code>dispatchersUseEncodedPaths</code> attribute of the Context.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59839</bug>: Apply <code>roleSearchAsUser</code> to all nested searches
        in JNDIRealm. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59859</bug>: Fix resource leak in WebDAV servlet. Based on patch by
        Coty Sutherland. (fschumacher)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Provide a mechanism that enables the container to check if a component
        (typically a web application) has been granted a given permission when
        running under a SecurityManager without the current execution stack
        having to have passed through the component. Use this new mechanism to
        extend SecurityManager protection to the system property replacement
        feature of the digester. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        When retrieving an object via a <code>ResourceLink</code>, ensure that
        the object obtained is of the expected type. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59823</bug>: Ensure that JASPIC configuration is taken into account
        when calling <code>HttpServletRequest.authenticate()</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59824</bug>: Mark the <code>RewriteValve</code> as supporting async
        processing by default. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59862</bug>: Allow nested jar files scanning to be filtered with
        the system property
        <code>tomcat.util.scan.StandardJarScanFilter.jarsToSkip</code>. Patch
        is provided by Terence Bandoian. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59866</bug>: When scanning <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> for
        annotations, don't scan the contents of
        <code>WEB-INF/classes/META-INF</code> (if present) since classes will
        never be loaded from that location. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59888</bug>: Correctly handle tabs and spaces in quoted version one
        cookies when using the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59912</bug>: Fix an edge case in input stream handling where an
        <code>IOException</code> could be thrown when reading a POST body.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59913</bug>: Correct a regression introduced with the support for
        the Servlet 4 <code>HttpServletRequest.getMapping()</code> API that
        caused the attributes for forwarded requests to be lost if requested
        from within a subsequent include. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59966</bug>: Do not start the web application if the error page
        configuration in web.xml is invalid. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Switch the CGI servlet to the standard logging mechanism and remove
        support for the debug attribute. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60012</bug>: Improvements in the log messages. Based on
        suggestions by Nemo Chen. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Changes to the <code>allowLinking</code> attribute of a
        <code>StandardRoot</code> instance now invalidate the cache if caching
        is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a new initialisation parameter, <code>envHttpHeaders</code>, to
        the CGI Servlet to mitigate <a href="https://httpoxy.org">httpoxy</a>
        (<a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2016-5388"
        >CVE-2016-5388</a>) by default and to provide a mechanism that can be
        used to mitigate any future, similar issues. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        When adding and removing <code>ResourceLink</code>s dynamically, ensure
        that the global resource is only visible via the
        <code>ResourceLinkFactory</code> when it is meant to be. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>60008</bug>: When processing CORs requests, treat any origin with a
        URI scheme of <code>file</code> as a valid origin. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of exceptions during a Lifecycle events triggered by a
        state transition. The exception is now caught and the component is now
        placed into the <code>FAILED</code> state. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60013</bug>: Fix encoding issues when using the RewriteValve with
        UTF-8 query strings or UTF-8 redirect URLs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60022</bug>: Improve handling when a WAR file and/or the associated
        exploded directory are symlinked into the <code>appBase</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a file descriptor leak when reading the global web.xml. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Consistently decode URL patterns provided via web.xml using the encoding
        of the web.xml file where specified or UTF-8 where no explicit encoding
        is specified. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Make timing attacks against the Realm implementations harder. (schultz)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        A number of the JRE memory leaks addressed by the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code> have been fixed in Java 9
        so the associated protection is now disabled when running on Java 9
        onwards. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in refactoring to enable injection of custom
        keystores that broke the automatic conversion of OpenSSL style PEM
        key and certificate files for use with JSSE TLS connectors. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59910</bug>: Don't hardcode key alias value to "tomcat" for JSSE.
        When using a keystore, OpenSSL will still default to it. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59904</bug>: Add a limit (default 200) for the number of cookies
        allowed per request. Based on a patch by gehui. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59925</bug>: Correct regression in r1628368 and ensure that HTTP
        separators are handled as configured in the
        <code>LegacyCookieProcessor</code>. Patch provided by Kyohei Nakamura.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59950</bug>: Correct log message when reporting that the current
        number of HTTP/2 streams for a connection could not be pruned to below
        the limit. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>Semaphore.release</code> is called in all cases. Even
        when there is an exception. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60030</bug>: Correct a potential infinite loop in the SNI parsing
        code triggered by failing to handle an end of stream condition. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Small logging optimization in the <code>Rfc6265CookieProcessor</code>.
        Patch provided by Svetlin Zarev. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        OpenSSL now disables 3DES by default so reflect this when using OpenSSL
        syntax to select ciphers. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use the proper ERROR socket status code for async errors with NIO2.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60035</bug>: Fix a potential connection leak if the client drops a
        TLS connection before the handshake completes. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Refactor the JSSE client certificate validation so that the
        effectiveness of the <code>certificateVerificationDepth</code>
        configuration attribute does not depend on the presence of a certificate
        revokation list. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Log a warning at start up if a JSSE TLS connector is configured with
        a trusted certificate that is either not yet valid or has expired.
        (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When writing out a full web.xml file with JspC ensure that the encoding
        used in the XML prolog matches the encoding used to write the contents
        of the file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the error handling for custom tags to ensure that the tag is
        returned to the pool or released and destroyed once used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60032</bug>: Fix handling of method calls that use varargs within
        EL value expressions. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ignore <code>engineOptionsClass</code> and <code>scratchdir</code> when
        running under a security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed StringIndexOutOfBoundsException. Based on a patch provided by
        wuwen via Github. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59908</bug>: Ensure that a reason phrase is included in the close
        message if a session is closed due to a timeout. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59867</bug>: Correct the documentation provided by Manager's
        403.jsp. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59868</bug>: Clarify the documentation for the Manager web
        application to make clearer that the host name and IP address in the
        server section are the primary host name and IP address. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59940</bug>: Correct the name of the
        <code>truststorePassword</code> attribute of the
        <code>SSLHostConfig</code> element in the configuration documentation.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        MBeans Descriptors How-To is moved to
        <code>mbeans-descriptors-howto.html</code>. Patch provided by Radoslav
        Husar. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update NIO Connector configuration documentation with an information
        about <code>socket.directSslBuffer</code>. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60034</bug>: Correct a typo in the Manager How-To page of the
        documentation web application. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In order to avoid the unintended skip of <code>PoolCleaner</code>,
        remove the check code of the execution interval in the task that has
        been scheduled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59850</bug>: Ensure that the <code>ResultSet</code> is closed when
        enabling the <code>StatementCache</code> interceptor. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59923</bug>: Reduce the default value of
        <code>validationInterval</code> in order to avoid the potential issue
        that continues to return an invalid connection after database restart.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the <code>ResultSet</code> is returned as Proxy object when
        enabling the <code>StatementDecoratorInterceptor</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>60043</bug>: Ensure that the <code>suspectTimeout</code> works
        without removing connection when the <code>removeAbandoned</code> is
        disabled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Add log message of when returning the connection that has been marked
        suspect. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct Javadoc for <code>ConnectionPool.suspect()</code>. Based on a
        patch by Yahya Cahyadi. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>59871</bug>: Add a property (<code>timeFormat</code>) to
        JULI&apos;s <code>OneLineFormatter</code> to enable the format of the
        time stamp used in log messages to be configured. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59899</bug>: Update Tomcat&apos;s copy of the Java Persistence
        annotations to include the changes made in 2.1 / JavaEE 7. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed typos in mbeans-descriptors.xml files. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons BCEL to r1757132 to align with the
        BCEL 6 release. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP2 to r1757164 to pick up a
        couple of bug fixes. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Codec to r1757174. Code formatting
        changes only. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons FileUpload to afdedc9. This pulls in
        a fix to improve the performance with large multipart boundaries.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.4" rtext="2016-07-12">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>57705</bug>: Add debug logging for requests denied by the remote
        host and remote address valves and filters. Based on a patch by Graham
        Leggett. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a regression in the fix for <bug>58588</bug> that removed the
        entire <code>org.apache.juli</code> package from the embedded JARs
        rendering them unusable. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>59399</bug>: Add a new option to the Realm implementations that
        ship with Tomcat that allows the HTTP status code used for HTTP -> HTTPS
        redirects to be controlled per Realm. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Change the default of the
        <code>sessionCookiePathUsesTrailingSlash</code> attribute of the
        <code>Context</code> element to <code>false</code> since the problems
        caused when a Servlet is mapped to <code>/*</code> are more significant
        than the security risk of not enabling this option by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to <bug>59655</bug>. Improve the documentation for configuring
        permitted cookie names. Patch provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not attempt to start web resources during a web application's
        initialisation phase since the web application is not fully configured
        at that point and the web resources may not be correctly configured.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59708</bug>: Modify the LockOutRealm logic. Valid authentication
        attempts during the lock out period will no longer reset the lock out
        timer to zero. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor the certificate keystore and trust store generation to make it
        easier for embedded users to inject their own key stores. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>59233</bug>: Add the ability to add TLS virtual hosts dynamically.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Add a <code>maxConcurrentStreamExecution</code> on the HTTP/2
        protocol handler to allow restricting the amount of concurrent stream
        that are being executed in a single connection. The default is to
        not limit it. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correct a problem with <code>ServletRequest.getServerPort()</code> for
        secure HTTP/2 connections that meant an incorrect value was returned when
        using the default port. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Now the WebSocket implementation is not built directly on top of the
        Servlet API and can use Tomcat internals, there is no need for the
        dedicated WebSocket Executor. It has been replaced by the use of the
        Connector/Endpoint provided Executor. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Improve error handling around user code prior to calling
        <code>InstanceManager.destroy()</code> to ensure that the method is
        executed. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Do not log an additional case of <code>IOException</code>s in the
        error handler for the Drawboard WebSocket example when the root cause is
        the client disconnecting since the logs add no value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59642</bug>: Mention the <code>localDataSource</code> in the
        <code>DataSourceRealm</code> section of the Realm How-To. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59672</bug>: Update the security considerations page of the
        documentation web application to take account of the fact that the
        Manager and HostManager applications now have a
        <code>RemoteAddrValve</code> configured by default. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Follow-up to the fix for <bug>59399</bug>. Ensure that the new attribute
        <code>transportGuaranteeRedirectStatus</code> is documented for all
        <strong>Realm</strong>s. Also document the <code>NullRealm</code> and
        when it is automatically created for an <strong>Engine</strong>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix the description of <code>maxAge</code> attribute in jdbc-pool doc.
        This attribute works both when a connection is returned and when a
        connection is borrowed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59774</bug>: Correct the <code>prefix</code> values in the the
        documented examples for configuring the <code>AccessLogValve</code>.
        Patch provided by Mike Noordermeer. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Extras">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        <bug>58588</bug>: Remove the JULI extras package from the distribution.
        It was only useful for switching Tomcat's internal logging to log4j
        1.2.x and that version of log4j is no longer supported. No additional
        Tomcat code is required if switching Tomcat's internal logging to log
        via log4j 2.x. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add log message when the ping has timed-out. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        If the ping message has been received at the
        <code>AbstractReplicatedMap#leftOver</code> method, ensure that notify
        the member is alive than ignore it. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix the duplicated connection release when connection verification
        failed. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that do not remove the abandoned connection that has been already
        released. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        <bug>59276</bug>: Update optional Checkstyle library to 6.17. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <add>
        Use the mirror network rather than the ASF master site to download the
        current ASF dependencies. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.8 to
        pick up the latest fixes and make 1.2.8 the minimum recommended version.
        (markt)
      </update>
      <scode>
        Use UTF-8 with a standard prolog for all XML files. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.3" rtext="2016-06-13">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        RMI Target related memory leaks are avoidable which makes them an
        application bug that needs to be fixed rather than a JRE bug to work
        around. Therefore, start logging RMI Target related memory leaks on web
        application stop. Add an option that controls if the check for these
        leaks is made. Log a warning if running on Java 9 with this check
        enabled but without the command line option it requires. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure NPE will not be thrown during deployment when scanning jar files
        without MANIFEST.MF file. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>clearReferencesStatic</code> option from
        <code>StandardContext</code>. It was known to cause problems with some
        libraries (such as log4j) and was only linked to suspected memory leaks
        rather than known memory leaks. It had been disabled by default with no
        increase in the reports of memory leaks for some time. (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>59604</bug>: Correct the assumption made in the URL decoding that
        the default platform encoding is always compatible with ISO-8859-1. This
        assumption is not always valid, e.g. on z/OS. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59608</bug>: Skip over any invalid <code>Class-Path</code> attribute
        from JAR manifests. Log errors at debug level due to many bad libraries.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix error message when failed to register MBean. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59655</bug>: Configure the cookie name validation to use RFC6265 rules by default to
        align it with the default cookie parser. Document the impact system properties have on
        cookie name validation. (mark)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that requests with HTTP method names that are not tokens (as
        required by RFC 7231) are rejected with a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When an asynchronous request is processed by the AJP connector, ensure
        that request processing has fully completed before starting the next
        request. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve handling of HTTP/2 stream resets. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>58750</bug>: The HTTP Server header is no longer set by default. A
        Server header may be configured by setting the <code>server</code>
        attribute on the <code>Connector</code>. A new <code>Connector</code>
        attribute, <code>serverRemoveAppProvidedValues</code> may be used to
        remove any Server header set by a web application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59564</bug>: Correct offset when reading into HTTP/2 input buffer
        that could cause problems reading request bodies. (violetagg/markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Modify the handling of read/write timeouts so that the appropriate error
        handling (<code>ReadListener.onError()</code>,
        <code>WriteListener.onError()</code> or
        <code>AsycnListener.onError()</code>) is called. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
       If an async dispatch results in the completion of request processing,
       ensure that any remaining request body is swallowed before starting the
       processing of the next request else the remaining body may be read as the
       start of the next request leading to a 400 response. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a cause of multiple attempts to close the same socket. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59567</bug>: Fix NPE scanning webapps for TLDs when an exploded
        JAR has an empty WEB-INF/classes/META-INF folder. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak in the expression language implementation that caused
        the class loader of the first web application to use expressions to be
        pinned in memory. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59654</bug>: Improve error message when attempting to use a TLD
        file from an invalid location. Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59659</bug>: Fix possible memory leak in WebSocket handling of
        unexpected client disconnects. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>58891</bug>: Update the SSL how-to. Based on a suggestion by
        Alexander Kjäll. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="jdbc-pool">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix a memory leak with the pool cleaner thread that retained a reference
        to the web application class loader for the first web application to use
        a connection pool. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons DBCP 2 to r1743696 (2.1.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons Pool 2 to r1743697 (2.4.2 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the internal fork of Commons File Upload to r1743698 (1.3.1 plus
        additional fixes). (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>58626</bug>: Add support for a new environment variable
        (<code>USE_NOHUP</code>) that causes <code>nohup</code> to be used when
        starting Tomcat. It is disabled by default except on HP-UX where it is
        enabled by default since it is required when starting Tomcat at boot on
        HP-UX. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.2" rtext="2016-05-16">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Ensure that annotated web components packed in web fragments will be
        processed when <code>unpackWARs</code> is enabled. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.1" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59206</bug>: Ensure NPE will not be thrown by
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.file.ConfigFileLoader</code> when
        <code>catalina.base</code> is not specified. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59217</bug>: Remove duplication in the recycling of the path in
        <code>o.a.tomcat.util.http.ServerCookie</code>. Patch is provided by
        Kyohei Nakamura. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed possible NPE in
        <code>o.a.catalina.loader.WebappClassLoaderBase.getResourceAsStream</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59213</bug>: Async dispatches should be based off a wrapped request.
        (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>javax.servlet.ServletRequest</code> and
        <code>javax.servlet.ServletResponse</code> provided during
        <code>javax.servlet.AsyncListener</code> registration are made
        available via <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedRequest</code>
        and <code>javax.servlet.AsyncEvent.getSuppliedResponse</code>
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59219</bug>: Ensure <code>AsyncListener.onError()</code> is called
        if an <code>Exception</code> is thrown during async processing. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59220</bug>: Ensure that <code>AsyncListener.onComplete()</code> is
        called if the async request times out and the response is already
        committed. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59226</bug>: Process the <code>Class-Path</code> attribute from
        JAR manifests for JARs on the class path excluding JARs packaged in
        <code>WEB-INF/lib</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59255</bug>: Fix possible NPE in mapper. (kkolinko/remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59256</bug>: <code>slf4j-taglib*.jar</code> should not be excluded
        from the standard JAR scanning by default. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify in the log message that specifying both urlPatterns and value
        attributes in WebServlet and WebFilter annotations is not allowed.
        (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure the exceptions caused by Valves will be available in the log
        files so that they can be evaluated when
        <code>o.a.catalina.valves.ErrorReportValve.showReport</code> is
        disabled. Patch is provided by Svetlin Zarev. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove unused <code>distributable</code> attribute that is defined as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code> of <code>Manager</code> in StoreConfig.
        (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix handling of Cluster Receiver in StoreConfig. The <code>bind</code>
        and <code>host</code> attributes define as
        <code>TransientAttribute</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59261</bug>: <code>ServletRequest.getAsyncContext()</code> now
        throws an <code>IllegalStateException</code> as required by the Servlet
        specification if the request is not in asynchronous mode when called.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59269</bug>: Correct the implementation of
        <code>PersistentManagerBase</code> so that <code>minIdleSwap</code>
        functions as designed and sessions are swapped out to keep the active
        session count below <code>maxActiveSessions</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add the <code>org.apache.catalina.servlet4preview</code> package that
        can be used to gain early access to Servlet 4.0 features. Note that this
        package will <strong>not</strong> be present in Tomcat 9. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Correctly configure the base path for a resources directory provided by
        an expanded JAR file. Patch provided by hengyunabc. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        When multiple compressed formats are available and the client does not
        express a preference, use the server order to determine the preferred
        format. Based on a patch by gmokki. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>59284</bug>: Allow the Tomcat provided JASPIC
        <code>SimpleServerAuthConfig</code> to pick up module configuration
        properties from either the property set passed to its constructor or
        from the properties passed in the call to <code>getAuthContext</code>.
        Based on a patch by Thomas Maslen. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59310</bug>: Do not add a <code>Content-Length: 0</code> header for
        custom responses to <code>HEAD</code> requests that do not set a
        <code>Content-Length</code> value. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When normalizing paths, improve the handling when paths end with
        <code>/.</code> or <code>/..</code> and ensure that input and output are
        consistent with respect to whether or not they end with <code>/</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59317</bug>: Ensure that
        <code>HttpServletRequest.getRequestURI()</code> returns an encoded URI
        rather than a decoded URI after a dispatch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Use the correct URL for the fragment when reporting errors processing
        a <code>web-fragment.xml</code> file from a JAR located in an unpacked
        WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that <code>JarScanner</code> only uses the explicit call-back to
        process <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and only when configured to treat
        the contents of <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> as a possible exploded JAR.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Remove the <code>java2DDisposerProtection</code> option from the
        <code>JreMemoryLeakPreventionListener</code>. The leak is fixed in Java
        7 onwards and Tomcat 8 requires Java 7 so the option is unnecessary.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the value for the header <code>X-Frame-Options</code> is
        constructed correctly according to the specification when
        <code>ALLOW-FROM</code> option is used. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix an <code>IllegalArgumentException</code> if the first use of an
        internal <code>Response</code> object requires JASPIC authentication.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Do not trigger unnecessary session ID changes when using JASPIC and the
        user is authenticated using cached credentials. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59437</bug>: Ensure that the JASPIC <code>CallbackHandler</code> is
        thread-safe. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59449</bug>: In <code>ContainerBase</code>, ensure that the process
        to remove a child container is the reverse of the process to add one.
        Patch provided by Huxing Zhang. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Align cipher configuration parsing with current OpenSSL master. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Change the default for <code>honorCipherOrder</code> to
        <code>false</code>. With the current default TLS configuration, it is no
        longer necessary for this to be <code>true</code> for a reasonably
        secure configuration. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        Add a new environment variable <code>JSSE_OPTS</code> that is intended
        to be used to pass JVM wide configuration to the JSSE implementation.
        The default value is <code>-Djdk.tls.ephemeralDHKeySize=2048</code>
        which protects against weak Diffie-Hellman keys. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        When running on Java 7, exclude DHE ciphers from the default cipher list
        for JSSE connectors since they use weak 768 bit DH keys and cannot be
        configured to use more secure keys. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>58970</bug>: Fix a connection counting bug in the NIO connector
        that meant some dropped connections were not removed from the current
        connection count. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59289</bug>: Do not recycle upgrade processors in unexpected close
        situations. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Use <code>Locale.toLanguageTag()</code> to construct
        the <code>Content-Language</code> HTTP header to ensure the locale is
        correctly represented. Patch provided by zikfat. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59295</bug>: Add support for using pem encoded certificates with
        JSSE SSL. Submitted by Emmanuel Bourg with additional tweaks. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Make the TLS certificate chain available to clients when using
        JSSE+OpenSSL with the certificate chain stored in a Java KeyStore.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Work around <a herf="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/issues/188">a
        known issue in OpenSSL</a> that does not permit the TLS handshake to be
        failed if the ALPN negotiation fails. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59421</bug>: Add direct HTTP/2 connection support. (remm)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Correctly handle a call to <code>AsyncContext.complete()</code> from a
        non-container thread when non-blocking I/O is being used. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59451</bug>: Correct Javadoc for <code>MessageBytes</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59450</bug>: Correctly handle the case where the
        <code>LegacyCookieProcessor</code> is configured with
        <code>allowHttpSepsInV0</code> set to <code>false</code> and
        <code>forwardSlashIsSeparator</code> set to <code>true</code>. Patch
        provided by Kyohei Nakamura. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        When scanning JARs for TLDs, correctly handle the (rare) case where a
        JAR has been exploded into <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> and the web
        application is deployed as a packed WAR. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59640</bug>: NPEs with not found TLDs. (remm)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59189</bug>: Explicitly release the native memory held by the
        <code>Inflater</code> and <code>Deflater</code> when using
        PerMessageDeflate and the WebSocket session ends. Based on a patch by
        Henrik Olsson. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Return back a container specific extension to the WsServerContainer
        to allow frameworks to more easily dispatch requests to WebSocket
        endpoints. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix a regression caused by the connector refactoring and ensure that the
        thread context class loader is set to the to the web application
        classloader when processing WebSocket messages on the server. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Ensure that a client disconnection triggers the error handling for the
        associated WebSocket end point. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make WebSocket client more robust when handling errors during the close
        of a WebSocket session. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59210</bug>: Server push example has to use
        <code>o.a.catalina.connector.RequestFacade</code> when obtaining
        <code>o.a.catalina.core.ApplicationPushBuilder</code>. Patch is
        provided by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59218</bug>: Correct the path to <code>jaspic-providers.xml</code>
        in Jaspic How-To. Patch is provided by Tatsuya Bessho. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove button that has accidentally been added to the host manager.
        Submitted by Coty Sutherland. (remm)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Update in the documentation the link to the maven repository where
        Tomcat snapshot artifacts are deployed. (markt/violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Clarify in the documentation that calls to
        <code>ServletContext.log(String, Throwable)</code> or
        <code>GenericServlet.log(String, Throwable)</code> are logged at the
        SEVERE level. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct a typo in SSL/TLS Configuration How-To.
        Issue reported via comments.apache.org. (violetagg)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE when a proxy node failed to retrieve a backup entry. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add log of when received an unexpected messages. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the flag indicating that member is a localMember. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Fix potential NPE that depends on the setting order of attributes of
        static member when using the static cluster. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to
        <code>ChannelInterceptor</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        As with the multicast cluster environment, in the static cluster
        environment, the local member inherits properties from the cluster
        receiver. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add get/set method for the channel that is related to each Channel
        services. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add name to channel in order to identify channels. In tomcat cluster
        environment, it is set the cluster name + "-Channel" as default value.
        (kfujino)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add the channel name to the thread which is invoked by channel services
        in order to identify the associated channel. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that clear the channel instance from channel services when
        stopping channel. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Implement map state in the replication map. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Ensure that the ping is not executed during the start/stop of the
        replication map. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        In ping processing in the replication map, send not the
        <code>INIT</code> message but the newly introduced <code>PING</code>
        message. (kfujino)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>59209</bug>: Remove <code>honorCipherOrder=false</code> attribute
        from the connector example in server.xml. When the block is uncommented
        the connector will use the default value for this attribute which is
        <code>false</code>. If one needs to enable it, one can add it
        explicitly to the connector definition. Use of this feature requires
        Java 8 or later. Patch is provided by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>59211</bug>: Add hamcrest to Eclipse classpath. Patch is provided
        by Huxing Zhang. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <bug>59280</bug>: Update the NSIS Installer used to build the
        Windows Installers to version 2.51. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update the packaged version of the Tomcat Native Library to 1.2.7 to
        pick up the Windows binaries that are based on OpenSSL 1.0.2h and APR
        1.5.2. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.5.0" rtext="2016-03-24">
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        The Tomcat 8.5.x branch was created from the Tomcat 9.0.0.M4 tag.
        Changes were applied to restore Java 7 compatibility and to align the
        specification APIs with Servlet 3.1, JSP 2.3, EL 3.0, WebSocket 1.1 and
        JASPIC 1.1.
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
