<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="remm@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <author email="fhanik@apache.org">Filip Hanik</author>
    <author email="rjung@apache.org">Rainer Jung</author>
    <author email="kkolinko@apache.org">Konstantin Kolinko</author>
    <author email="pero@apache.org">Peter Rossbach</author>
    <title>Changelog</title>
  </properties>

<body>
<section name="Tomcat 7.0.0 (markt)">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update Servlet support to the Servlet 3.0 specification. (all)
      </update>
      <update>
        Improve and document VirtualWebappLoader. (rjung)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>43642</bug>: Add prestartminSpareThreads attribute for Executor. (jfclere)
      </add>
      <update>
        Switch from AnnotationProcessor to InstanceManager. Patch provided by
        David Jecks with modifications by Remy. (remm/fhanik)
      </update>
      <update>
        <rev>620845</rev> and <rev>669119</rev>. Make shutdown address
        configurable. (jfclere)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <rev>651977</rev> Add some missing control checks to
        <code>ThreadWithAttributes</code>. (markt) 
      </fix>
      <add>
        <rev>677640</rev> Add a startup class that does not require any
        configuration files. (costin)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <rev>700532</rev> Log if temporary file operations within the CGI
        servlet fail. Make sure header Reader is closed on failure. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <rev>708541</rev> Delete references to DefaultContext which was removed
        in 6.0.x. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <rev>709018</rev> Initial implementation of an asynchronous file handler
        for JULI. (fhanik)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Give session thisAccessedTime and lastAccessedTime clear semantics.
        (rjung)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Expose thisAccessedTime via Session interface. (rjung)
      </add>
      <add>
        Provide a log format for JULI that provides the same information as the
        default but on a single line. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <rev>723889</rev> Provide the ability to configure the Executor job
        queue size and a timeout for adding jobs to the queue. (fhanik) 
      </add>
      <add>
        Add support for aliases to StandardContext. This allows content from other
        directories and/or WAR files to be mapped to paths within the context.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        Provide clearer definition of Lifecycle interface, particularly start
        and stop, and align components that implement Lifecycle with this
        definition. (markt)  
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>48662</bug>: Provide a new option to control the copying of context
        XML descriptors from web applications to the host's xmlBase. Copying of
        XMl descriptors is now disabled by default. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Move comet classes from the org.apache.catalina package to the
        org.apache.catalina.comet package to allow comet to work under a
        security manager. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Port SSLInsecureRenegotiation from mod_ssl. This requires
        to use tomcat-native 1.2.21 that have option to detect this
        support from OpenSSL library. (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
        Allow bigger AJP packets also for request bodies and responses
        using the packetSize attribute of the Connector. (rjung)
      </update>
      <update><rev>703017</rev> Make Java socket options consistent between NIO
        and JIO connector. Expose all the socket options available on
        <code>java.net.Socket</code> (fhanik)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>46051</bug>: The writer returned by <code>getWriter()</code> now
        conforms to the <code>PrintWriter</code> specification and uses platform
        dependent line endings rather than always using <code>\r\n</code>.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Use tc-native 1.2.x which is based on APR 1.3.3+ (mturk)
      </update>
      <update>
        <rev>724239</rev> NIO connector now always uses an Executor. (fhanik)
      </update>
      <update>
        <rev>724393</rev> Implement keepAliveCount for NIO connector in a thread
        safe manner. (fhanik)
      </update>
      <update>
        <rev>724849</rev> Implement keep alive timeout for NIO connector.
        (fhanik)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <update>
        Update JSP support to the JSP 2.2 specification. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update EL support to the EL 2.2 specification. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        <rev>787978</rev> Use "1.6" as the default value for compilerSourceVM and compilerTargetVM
        options of Jasper. (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>48358</bug>: Add support for limiting the number of JSPs that are
        loaded at any one time. Based on a patch by Isabel Drost. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>48689</bug>: Access TLD files through a new JarResource interface
        to make extending Jasper simpler, particularly in OSGi environments.
        Patch provided by Jarek Gawor. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="High Availability">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Add support for UDP and secure communication to tribes. (fhanik)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add versioning to the tribes communication protocol to support future
        developments. (fhanik)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add a demo on how to use the payload. (fhanik)
      </add>
      <add>
        Started to add JMX support to the cluster implementation. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <rev>609778</rev> Minor fixes to the throughput interceptor and the
        NIO receiver. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <rev>630234</rev> Additional checks for the NIO receiver. (fhanik)
      </fix>
      <update>
        <rev>671650</rev> Improve error message when multicast is not enabled.
        (fhanik)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
     <changelog>
      <update>
        <rev>631321</rev> Update changelog to support the &lt;rev&gt; element
        in the documentation. (fhanik)
      </update>
      <add>
        A number of additional roles were added to the Manager and Host Manager
        applications to separate out permissions for the HTML interface, the
        text interface and the JMX proxy. (markt) 
      </add>
      <add>
        CSRF protection was added to the Manager and Host Manager applications.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        List array elements in the JMX proxy output of the Manager application.
        (rjung)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Extras">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        A new JmxRemoteLifecycleListener that can be used to fix the ports used
        for remote JMX connections, eg when using JConsole. (markt)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Modules">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <rev>691359</rev> Added in a Bayeux protocol implementation built on top
        of the Tomcat CometProcessor interface. (fhanik)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Numerous code clean-up changes including the use of generics and
        removing unused imports, fields, parameters and methods. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        All deprecated internal code has been removed. <b>Warning:</b> If you
        have custom components for a previous Tomcat version that extend
        internal Tomcat classes and override deprecated methods it is highly
        likely that they will no longer work. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Parameterize version number throughout build scripts and source. (rjung)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
