<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tomcat-docs.xsl"?>
<document url="changelog.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>Changelog</title>
    <no-comments />
  </properties>

<body>
<!--
  Subsection ordering:
  General, Catalina, Coyote, Jasper, Cluster, WebSocket, Web applications,
  Extras, Tribes, Other

  Item Ordering:

  Fixes having an issue number are sorted by their number, ascending.

  There is no ordering by add/update/fix.

  Other fixed issues are added to the end of the list, chronologically.
  They eventually become mixed with the numbered issues. (I.e., numbered
  issues to not "pop up" wrt. others).
-->
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.4 (markt)">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Restore the ability to use the <code>addURL()</code> method of the
        web application class loader to add external resources to the web
        application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve the robustness of web application undeployment based on some
        code analysis triggered by the report for <bug>54315</bug>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56125</bug>: Correctly construct the URL for a resource that
        represents the root of a JAR file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Generate a valid root element for the effective web.xml for a web
        application for all supported versions of web.xml. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Make it easier for applications embedding and/or extending Tomcat to
        modify the <code>javaseClassLoader</code> attribute of the
        <code>WebappClassLoader</code>. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Add missing support for <code>&lt;deny-uncovered-http-methods&gt;</code>
        element when merging web.xml files. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Improve merging process for web.xml files to take account of the
        elements and attributes supported by the Servlet version of the merged
        file. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid <code>NullPointerException</code> in resource cache when making an
        invalid request for a resource outside of the web application. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove an unnecessary null check identified by FindBugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        In WebappClassLoader, when reporting threads that are still running
        while web application is being stopped, print their stack traces to
        the log. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56190</bug>: The response should be closed (i.e. no further output
        is permitted) when a call to <code>AsyncContext.complete()</code> takes
        effect. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56236</bug>: Enable Tomcat to work with alternative Servlet and
        JSP API JARs that package the XML schemas in such as way as to require
        a dependency on the JSP API before enabling validation for web.xml.
        Tomcat has no such dependency. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56244</bug>: Fix MBeans descriptor for WebappClassLoader MBean.
        (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add a work around for validating XML documents (often TLDs) that use
        just the file name to refer to refer to the JavaEE schema on which they
        are based. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Add methods of get the idle time from last client access time to
        <code>org.apache.catalina.Session</code>. (kfujino)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56246</bug>: Fix NullPointerException in MemoryRealm when
        authenticating an unknown user. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56248</bug>: Allow the deployer to update an existing WAR file
        without undeploying the existing application if the update flag is set.
        This allows any existing custom context.xml for the application to be
        retained. To update an application and remove any existing context.xml
        simply undeploy the old version of the application before deploying the
        new version. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56253</bug>: When listing resources that are provided by a JAR, fix
        possible <code>StringIndexOutOfBoundsException</code>s. Add some unit
        tests for this and similar scenarios and fix the additional issues those
        unit tests identified. Based on a patch by Larry Isaacs. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In some circumstances asynchronous requests could time out too soon.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56172</bug>: Avoid possible request corruption when using the AJP
        NIO connector and a request is sent using more than one AJP message.
        Patch provided by Amund Elstad. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Add experimental NIO2 connector. Based on code developed by
        Nabil Benothman. (remm)
      </add>
      <fix>
        Improve processing of chuck size from chunked headers. Avoid overflow
        and use a bit shift instead of a multiplication as it is marginally
        faster. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct regression introduced in 8.0.0-RC2 as part of the Servlet 3.1
        non-blocking IO support that broke handling of requests with an explicit
        content length of zero. (markt/kkolinko)  
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change the default compiler source and compiler target versions to 1.7
        since Tomcat 8 requires a minimum of Java 7. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56179</bug>: Fix parsing of EL expressions that contain unnecessary
        parentheses. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56177</bug>: Handle dependency tracking for TLDs when using JspC
        with a tag library JAR that is located outside of the web application.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Remove an unnecessary null check identified by FindBugs. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56199</bug>: Restore validateXml option for JspC which determines
        if web.xml will be parsed with a validating parser. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56223</bug>: Throw an <code>IllegalStateException</code> if a call
        is made to <code>ServletContext.setInitParameter()</code> after the
        ServletContext has been initialized. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Avoid a possible deadlock when one thread is shutting down a connection
        while another thread is trying to write to it. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Avoid NPE when flushing batched messages. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web Applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        <bug>56093</bug>: Add the SSL Valve to the documentation web
        application. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>56217</bug>: Improve readability by using left alignment for the
        table cell containing the request information on the Manager application
        status page. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fixed <code>java.lang.NegativeArraySizeException</code> when using
        "Expire sessions" command in the manager web application on a
        context where the session timeout is disabled. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Add support for <code>LAST_ACCESS_AT_START</code> system property to
         Manager web application. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Add definition of <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.FindLeaksTask</code>.
         (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <fix>
         Implement <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.VminfoTask</code>,
         <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.ThreaddumpTask</code> and
         <code>org.apache.catalina.ant.SslConnectorCiphersTask</code>. (kfujino)
      </fix>
      <add>
         Add the option to ignore the constraint of the first line of the
        response message that must be "OK -". Default is false. (kfujino)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56115</bug>: Expose the <code>httpusecaches</code> property of
        Ant&apos;s <code>get</code> task as some users may need to change the
        default. Based on a suggestion by Anthony. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56143</bug>: Improve <code>service.bat</code> so that it can be
        launched from a non-UAC console. This includes using a single call to
        <code>tomcat8.exe</code> to install the Windows service rather than
        three calls, and using command line arguments instead of environment
        variables to pass the settings. (markt/kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Simplify Windows *.bat files: remove %OS% checks, as current java does
        not run on ancient non-NT operating systems. (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Align options between <code>service.bat</code> and <code>exe</code>
        Windows installer. For <code>service.bat</code> the changes are in
        --Classpath, --DisplayName, --StartPath, --StopPath. For
        <code>exe</code> installer the changes are in --JvmMs, --JvmMx options,
        which are now 128 Mb and 256 Mb respectively instead of being empty.
        Explicitly specify --LogPath path when uninstalling Windows service,
        avoiding default value for that option. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56137</bug>: Explicitly use NIO connector in SSL example in
        server.xml so it doesn't break if APR is enabled. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56139</bug>: Avoid a web application class loader leak in some unit
        tests when running on Windows. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Correct build script to avoid building JARs with empty packages. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Allow to limit JUnit test run to a number of selected test case
        methods. (kkolinko)
      </add>
      <update>
        Update Commons Pool 2 to 2.2. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to the 2.0 release. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>56189</bug>: Remove used file cpappend.bat from the distribution.
        (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56204</bug>: Remove unnecessary dependency between tasks in the
        build script. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.3 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-02-11">
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Fix build of Apache Commons DBCP2 classes. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to snapshot 170 dated 07 Feb 2014. This enables
        DBCP to work with a SecurityManager such that only DBCP needs to be
        granted the necessary permissions to communicate with the database.
        (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.2 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56082</bug>: Fix a concurrency bug in JULI&apos;s LogManager
        implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>56085</bug>: <code>ServletContext.getRealPath(String)</code> should
        return <code>null</code> for invalid input rather than throwing an
        <code>IllegalArgumentException</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix WebDAV support that was broken by the refactoring for the new
        resources implementation. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Simplify Catalina.initDirs(). (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>56096</bug>: When the attribute <code>rmiBindAddress</code> of the
        JMX Remote Lifecycle Listener is specified it's value will be used when
        constructing the address of a JMX API connector server. Patch is
        provided by Jim Talbut. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        When environment entry with one and the same name is defined in the web
        deployment descriptor and with annotation then the one specified in the
        web deployment descriptor is with priority. (violetagg)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        Fix passing the value of false for <code>xmlBlockExternal</code> option
        of Context to Jasper, as the default was changed in 8.0.1. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Enable non-blocking reads to take place on non-container threads.
        (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Simplify the code of
        <code>o.a.c.ha.tcp.SimpleTcpCluster.createManager(String)</code>.
        Remove unnecessary class cast. (kfujino)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        In Manager web application improve handling of file upload errors.
        Display a message instead of error 500 page. Simplify. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        <bug>56104</bug>: Correct the version number on the welcome page of the
        Windows installer. (markt)
      </fix>
      <update>
        Update Commons DBCP 2 to snapshot 168 dated 05 Feb 2014. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        Fix CVE-2014-0050, a denial of service with a malicious, malformed
        Content-Type header and multipart request processing. Fixed by merging
        latest code (r1565159) from Commons FileUpload. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.1 (markt)" rtext="beta, 2014-02-02">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change default value of <code>xmlBlockExternal</code> attribute of
        Context. It is <code>true</code> now. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Correct regression in the fix for <bug>55996</bug> that meant that
        asynchronous requests might timeout too early. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Change default value of the <code>blockExternal</code> attribute of
        JspC task. The default value is <code>true</code>. Add support for
        <code>-no-blockExternal</code> switch when JspC is run as a
        standalone application. (kkolinko)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="WebSocket">
    <changelog>
      <fix>
        Do not return an empty string for the
        <code>Sec-WebSocket-Protocol</code> HTTP header when no sub-protocol has
        been requested or no sub-protocol could be agreed as RFC6455 requires
        that no <code>Sec-WebSocket-Protocol</code> header is returned in this
        case. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat 8.0.0 (markt)" rtext="not released">
  <subsection name="Catalina">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 340 - Servlet 3.1. The JSR 340 implementation includes
        contributions from Nick Williams and Jeremy Boynes. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 245 MR2 - JSP 2.3. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 341 - Unified Expression Language 3.0. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        Implement JSR 356 - WebSockets. The JSR 356 implementation includes
        contributions from Nick Williams, Rossen Stoyanchev and Niki Dokovski.
        (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        <bug>46727</bug>: Refactor default servlet to make it easier to
        sub-class to implement finer grained control of the file encoding. Based
        on a patch by Fred Toth. (markt)
      </update>
      <add>
        <bug>45995</bug>: Align Tomcat with Apache httpd and perform MIME type
        mapping based on file extension in a case insensitive manner. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        Remove duplicate code that converted a Host&apos;s appBase attribute to
        a canonical file. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        <bug>51408</bug>: Replace calls to <code>Charset.defaultCharset()</code>
        with an explicit reference to the ISO-8859-1 Charset. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Refactor initialization code to use a single, consistent approach to
        determining the Catalina home (binary) and base (instance) directories.
        The search order for home is <code>catalina.home</code> system property,
        parent of current directory if boootstrap.jar is present and finally
        current working directory. The search order for Catalina base is
        <code>catalina.base</code> system property falling back to the value for
        Catalina home. (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        <bug>52092</bug>: JULI now uses the <code>OneLineFormatter</code> and
        <code>AsyncFileHandler</code> by default. (markt)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>52558</bug>: Refactor <code>CometConnectionManagerValve</code> so
        that it does not prevent the session from being serialized in when
        running in a cluster. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>52767</bug>: Remove reference to MySQL specific autoReconnect
        property in <code>JDBCAccessLogValve</code>. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Make the Mapper type-safe. Hosts, Contexts and Wrappers are no
        longer handled as plain objects, instead they keep their type.
        Code using the Mapper doesn't need to cast objects returned by
        the mapper. (rjung)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Move Manager, Loader and Resources from Container to Context since
        Context is the only place they are used. The documentation already
        states (and has done for some time) that Context is the only valid
        location for these nested components. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Move the Mapper from the Connector to the Service since the Mapper is
        identical for all Connectors of a given Service and it is common for
        there to be multiple Connectors for a Service (http, https and ajp).
        This means there is now only ever one Mapper per Service rather than
        possibly multiple identically configured Mapper objects. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove the per Context Mapper objects and use the Mapper from the
        Service. This removes the need to maintain two copies of the mappings
        for Servlets and Filters. (markt)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Implement a new Resources implementation that merges Aliases,
        VirtualLoader, VirtualDirContext, JAR resources and external
        repositories into a single framework rather than a separate one for each
        feature. (markt)
      </add>
      <add>
        URL rewrite valve, similar in functionality to mod_rewrite. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        Port storeconfig functionality, which can persist to server.xml and
        context.xml runtime container configuration changes. (remm)
      </add>
      <add>
        <bug>54095</bug>: Add support to the Default Servlet for serving
        gzipped versions of static resources directly from disk as an
        alternative to Tomcat compressing them on each request. Patch by
        Philippe Marschall. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>54708</bug>: Change the name of the working directory for the ROOT
        application (located under $CATALINA_BASE/work by default) from _ to
        ROOT. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Change default configuration so that a change to the global web.xml file
        will trigger a reload of all web applications. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55101</bug>: Make BASIC authentication more tolerant of whitespace.
        Patch provided by Brian Burch. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>55166</bug>: Move JSP descriptor and tag library descriptor schemas
        to servlet-api.jar to enable relative references between the schemas to
        be correctly resolved. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor the descriptor parsing code into a separate module that can be
        used by both Catalina and Jasper. Includes patches provided by Jeremy
        Boynes. (violetagg/markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        <bug>55246</bug>: Move TLD scanning to a ServletContainerInitializer
        provided by Jasper. Includes removal of TldConfig lifecycle listener and
        associated Context properties. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <add>
        <bug>55317</bug>: Facilitate weaving by allowing ClassFileTransformer to
        be added to WebppClassLoader. Patch by Nick Williams. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55620</bug>: Enable Tomcat to start when either $CATALINA_HOME
        and/or $CATALINA_BASE contains a comma character. Prevent Tomcat from
        starting when $CATALINA_HOME and/or $CATALINA_BASE contains a semi-colon
        on Windows. Prevent Tomcat from starting when $CATALINA_HOME and/or
        $CATALINA_BASE contains a colon on Linux/FreeBSD/etc. (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Initialize the JSP runtime in Jasper's initializer to avoid need for a
        Jasper-specific lifecycle listener. <code>JasperListener</code> has been
        removed. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        Change ordering of elements of JMX objects names so components are
        grouped more logically in JConsole. Generally, components are now
        grouped by Host and then by Context. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        Context listener to allow better EE and framework integration. (remm)
      </add>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Coyote">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Experimental support for SPDY. Includes contributions from Sheldon Shao.
        (costin)
      </add>
      <scode>
        The default connector is now the Java NIO connector even when specifying
        HTTP/1.1 as protocol (fhanik)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Update default value of pollerThreadCount for the NIO connector. The new
        default value will never go above 2 regardless of available processors.
        (fhanik)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>54010</bug>: Remove some unnecessary code (duplicate calls to
        configure the scheme as https for AJP requests originally received over
        HTTPS). (markt)
      </fix>
      <scode>
        Refactor char encoding/decoding using NIO APIs. (remm)
      </scode>
      <update>
        Change the default URIEncoding for all connectors from ISO-8859-1 to
        UTF-8. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Jasper">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Simplify API of <code>ErrorDispatcher</code> class by using varargs.
        (kkolinko)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Update Jasper to use the new common web.xml parsing code. Includes
        patches by Jeremy Boynes. (markt/violetagg)
      </scode>
      <add>
        Create test cases for JspC. Patch by Jeremy Boynes. (markt)
      </add>
      <scode>
        <bug>55246</bug>: TLD scanning is now performed by JasperInitializer
        (a ServletContainerInitializer) removing the need for support within the
        Servlet container itself. The scan is now performed only once rather than
        in two passes reducing startup time. (jboynes)
      </scode>
      <fix>
        <bug>55251</bug>: Do not allow JspC task to fail silently if the web.xml
        or web.xml fragment can not be generated. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Cluster">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove unused JvmRouteSessionIDBinderListener and SessionIDMessage.
        (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Modify method signature in ReplicationValve. Cluster instance is not
        necessary to argument of method. (kfujino)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove unused <code>expireSessionsOnShutdown</code> attribute in
        <code>org.apache.catalina.ha.session.BackupManager</code>. (kfujino)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Web applications">
    <changelog>
      <add>
        Extend the diagnostic information provided by the Manager web
        application to include details of the configured SSL ciphers suites for
        each connector. (markt)
      </add>
      <update>
        <bug>48550</bug>: Update examples web application to use UTF-8. (markt)
      </update>
      <update>
        <bug>55383</bug>: Improve the design and correct the HTML markup of
        the documentation web application. Patches provided by Konstantin
        Preißer. (markt)
      </update>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Tribes">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Refactor <code>AbstractReplicatedMap</code> to use generics. A key
        side-effect of this is that the class now implements
        <code>Map&lt;K,V&gt;</code> rather than extends
        <code>ConcurrentMap</code>. (markt)
      </scode>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Other">
    <changelog>
      <scode>
        Remove unused, deprecated code. (markt)
      </scode>
      <scode>
        Remove static info String and associated getInfo() method where present.
        (markt)
      </scode>
      <update>
        (<rev>1353242</rev>, <rev>1353410</rev>):
        Remove Ant tasks <code>jasper2</code> and <code>jkstatus</code>.
        The correct names are <code>jasper</code> and <code>jkupdate</code>.
        (kkolinko)
      </update>
      <fix>
        <bug>53529</bug>: Clean-up the handling of
        <code>InterruptedException</code> throughout the code base. (markt)
      </fix>
      <add>
        <bug>54899</bug>: Provide an initial implementation of NetBeans support.
        Patch provided by Brian Burch. (markt)
      </add>
      <fix>
        <bug>55166</bug>: Move the JSP descriptor and tag library descriptor
        schema defintion files from jsp-api.jar to servlet-api.jar so relative
        includes between the J2EE, Servlet and JSP schemas are correctly
        resolved. (markt)
      </fix>
      <fix>
        <bug>55372</bug>: When starting Tomcat with the <code>jpda</code> option
        to enable remote debugging, by default only listen on localhost for
        connections from a debugger. Prior to this change, Tomcat listened on
        all known addresses. (markt)
      </fix>
    </changelog>
  </subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
