<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="graal.html">

    &project;

  <properties>
    <title>GraalVM support</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc/>
</section>

  <section name="Introduction">

  <p>
    Tomcat supports using the GraalVM/Mandrel Native Image tool to produce
    a native binary including the container. This documentation page
    describes the build process of such an image.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Setup">

  <p>
    The native image tool is much easier to use with single JARs, as a result
    the process will use the Maven shade plugin JAR packaging (fat JAR). The
    idea is to produce a single JAR that contains all necessary classes from
    Tomcat, the webapps and all additional dependencies. Although Tomcat has
    received compatibility fixes to support native images, any library
    may not be compatible and may require replacement code (the GraalVM
    documentation has more details about this).
  </p>

  <p>
    Download and install GraalVM or Mandrel.
  </p>

  <p>
   If using GraalVM, the first step is then to add the Native Image tool.
   <source>export JAVA_HOME=/absolute...path...to/graalvm-ce-javaX-x.y.z
cd $JAVA_HOME/bin
./gu install native-image</source>
   Mandrel already includes the Native Image tool ready to use, so this
   step can be skipped. Only JAVA_HOME must be set to the folder which
   contains the bin folder with the JVM binaries, such as:
   <source>export JAVA_HOME=/absolute...path...to/mandrel-javaXX-platform-x.x.x.x/mandrelJDK</source>
  </p>

  <p>
    Download the Tomcat Stuffed module from
    https://github.com/apache/tomcat/tree/master/modules/stuffed and place
    all the files in a folder <code>stuffed</code> in this documentation.
    <source>export TOMCAT_STUFFED=/absolute...path...to/stuffed</source>
    The build process now requires both Ant and Maven.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Packaging and Building">

  <p>
    Inside the tomcat-stuffed folder, the directory structure is the same as for
    regular Tomcat. The main configuration files are placed in the conf folder,
    and if using the default server.xml the webapps are placed in the webapps
    folder.
  </p>

  <p>
    The first step is to build the fat Tomcat JAR with all dependencies.
    Any JSP in the webapp must all be precompiled and packaged.
    <source>cd $TOMCAT_STUFFED
mvn package
ant -Dwebapp.name=somewebapp -f webapp-jspc.ant.xml</source>
    Dependencies for the webapp should now be added to the main pom.xml,
    following with building the complete fat JAR.
    <source>mvn package</source>
  </p>

  <p>
    As it is best to avoid using reflection whenever possible with Ahead of
    Time compilation, it can be a good idea to generate and compile Tomcat
    Embedded code out of the main server.xml configuration as well as the
    context.xml files used to configure the contexts.
    <source>$JAVA_HOME/bin/java\
        -Dcatalina.base=. -Djava.util.logging.config.file=conf/logging.properties\
        -jar target/tomcat-stuffed-1.0.jar --catalina -generateCode src/main/java
mvn package</source>
    The rest of the process described here will assume this step was done and
    the <code>--catalina -useGeneratedCode</code> arguments are added to the
    command lines. If this was not the case, they should be removed.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Native image configuration">

  <p>
    Native images do not support any form of dynamic classloading or
    reflection unless it is defined explicitly in descriptors. Generating
    them uses a tracing agent from the GraalVM, and needs additional manual
    configuration in some cases.
  </p>

  <p>
    Run the GraalVM substrate VM using the trace agent:
    <source>$JAVA_HOME/bin/java\
        -agentlib:native-image-agent=config-output-dir=$TOMCAT_STUFFED/target/\
        -Dorg.graalvm.nativeimage.imagecode=agent\
        -Dcatalina.base=. -Djava.util.logging.config.file=conf/logging.properties\
        -jar target/tomcat-stuffed-1.0.jar --catalina -useGeneratedCode</source>
  </p>

  <p>
    Now all paths from the webapp that lead to dynamic classloading
    (ex: Servlet access, websockets, etc) need to be accessed using a script
    that will exercise the webapp. Servlets may be loaded on startup
    instead of needing an actual access. Listeners may also be used to load
    additional classes on startup.
  </p>

  <p>
    The descriptors have now been generated in the agent output directory.
    At this point, further configuration must be made to add items that are
    not traced, including: base interfaces, resource bundles, BeanInfo based
    reflection, etc. Please refer to the Graal documentation for more
    information on this process.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Building the native image">

  <p>
    If everything has been done properly, the native image can now be built
    using the native-image tool.
    <source>$JAVA_HOME/bin/native-image --no-server\
        --allow-incomplete-classpath --enable-https\
        --initialize-at-build-time=org.eclipse.jdt,org.apache.el.parser.SimpleNode,jakarta.servlet.jsp.JspFactory,org.apache.jasper.servlet.JasperInitializer,org.apache.jasper.runtime.JspFactoryImpl\
        -H:+JNI -H:+ReportUnsupportedElementsAtRuntime\
        -H:+ReportExceptionStackTraces -H:EnableURLProtocols=http,https,jar,jrt\
        -H:ConfigurationFileDirectories=$TOMCAT_STUFFED/target/\
        -H:ReflectionConfigurationFiles=$TOMCAT_STUFFED/tomcat-reflection.json\
        -H:ResourceConfigurationFiles=$TOMCAT_STUFFED/tomcat-resource.json\
        -H:JNIConfigurationFiles=$TOMCAT_STUFFED/tomcat-jni.json\
        -jar $TOMCAT_STUFFED/target/tomcat-stuffed-1.0.jar</source>
    The additional <code>--static</code> parameter enables static linking of
    glibc, zlib and libstd++ in the generated binary.
  </p>

  <p>
    Running the native image is then:
    <source>./tomcat-stuffed-1.0 -Dcatalina.base=. -Djava.util.logging.config.file=conf/logging.properties --catalina -useGeneratedCode</source>
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Compatibility">

  <p>
    Servlets, JSPs, EL, websockets, the Tomcat container, tomcat-native, HTTP/2
    are all supported out of the box in a native image.
  </p>

  <p>
    At the time of writing this documentation, JULI is not supported as the
    log manager configuration property is not supported by Graal, in addition
    to some static initializer problems, and the regular java.util.logging
    loggers and implementation should be used instead.
  </p>

  <p>
    If using the default server.xml file, some Server listeners have
    to be removed from the configuration as they are not compatible with native
    images, such as a JMX listener (JMX is unsupported) and leak prevention
    listeners (use of internal code that does not exist in Graal).
  </p>

  <p>
    Missing items for better Tomcat functionality:
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://github.com/oracle/graal/issues/460">Java
        serialization</a>: Clustering and session persistence are not
        functional</li>
      <li><a href="https://github.com/oracle/graal/issues/2103">JMX</a>:
        The usual monitoring and management is not usable</li>
      <li>java.util.logging LogManager: Configuration through a system property
        is not implemented, so standard java.util.logging must be used instead
        of JULI</li>
      <li>Static linking configuration: tomcat-native cannot be statically
        linked</li>
    </ul>
  </p>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
