    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
    -->
    <!DOCTYPE document [
    <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "file:///usr/share/tomcat/project.xml">
    ]>
    <document url="global_attributes.html">
    <body>
    <table class="detail-table">
    <tr>
    <th>Attribute</th>
    <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.deploy.alt_dd"</td>
    <td>The servlet context attribute under which we store the alternate deployment 
    descriptor for this web application</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.ASYNC_SUPPORTED"</td>
    <td />
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"catalina.base"</td>
    <td>Name of the system property containing the tomcat instance installation 
    path</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"catalina.home"</td>
    <td>Name of the system property containing the tomcat product installation 
    path</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.X509Certificate"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the array of X509Certificate 
    objects representing the certificate chain presented by our client, if any.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.cipher_suite"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the name of the cipher suite 
    being used on an SSL connection (as an object of type String).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.jsp_classpath"</td>
    <td>The servlet context attribute under which we store the class path for our 
    application class loader (as an object of type String), delimited with the 
    appropriate path delimiter for this platform.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"application/x-www-form-urlencoded"</td>
    <td />
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.CredentialHandler"</td>
    <td>ServletContext attribute under which we store the context Realm's 
    CredentialHandler (if both the Realm and the CredentialHandler exist).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"Catalina"</td>
    <td>Default domain for MBeans if none can be determined</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.core.DISPATCHER_REQUEST_PATH"</td>
    <td>Request dispatcher path.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.core.DISPATCHER_TYPE"</td>
    <td>Request dispatcher state.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.realm.GSS_CREDENTIAL"</td>
    <td />
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.jasper.XML_BLOCK_EXTERNAL"</td>
    <td>ServletContext init-param that determines if the JSP engine will block 
    external entities from being used in *.tld, *.jspx, *.tagx and tagplugin.xml 
    files.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.jasper.XML_VALIDATE_TLD"</td>
    <td>ServletContext init-param that determines if the JSP engine should validate 
    *.tld files when parsing them.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.key_size"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the key size being used for this 
    SSL connection (as an object of type Integer).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.NAMED"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the servlet name on a named 
    dispatcher request.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.remoteAddr"</td>
    <td>The request attribute set by the RemoteIpFilter, RemoteIpValve (and may be 
    set by other similar components) that identifies for the connector the remote IP
    address claimed to be associated with this request when a request is received 
    via one or more proxies.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.filters.RemoteIpFilter.secure"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that is set to the value of Boolean.TRUE if 
    RemoteIpFilter determines that this request was submitted via a secure 
    channel.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.request.forwarded"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that is set to the value of Boolean.TRUE by the 
    RemoteIpFilter, RemoteIpValve (and other similar components) that identifies a 
    request which been forwarded via one or more proxies.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.resources"</td>
    <td>The WebResourceRoot which is associated with the context.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.secure_protocol"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the name of the security protocol
    (e.g. TLSv1.3) being used on a secured connection (as an object of type 
    String).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.sendfile.end"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that can be used by a servlet to pass to the connector
    the end offset (not including) of the part of a file that is to be served by 
    sendfile.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.sendfile.start"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that can be used by a servlet to pass to the connector
    the start offset of the part of a file that is to be served by sendfile.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.sendfile.filename"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that can be used by a servlet to pass to the connector
    the name of the file that is to be served by sendfile.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.tomcat.sendfile.support"</td>
    <td>The request attribute that is set to the value of Boolean.TRUE if connector 
    processing this request supports use of sendfile.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.ssl_session_id"</td>
    <td>The request attribute under which we store the session id being used for 
    this SSL connection (as an object of type String).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"jakarta.servlet.request.ssl_session_mgr"</td>
    <td>The request attribute key for the session manager.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>org.apache.catalina.STRICT_SERVLET_COMPLIANCE</td>
    <td>The flag which controls strict servlet specification compliance. Setting 
    this flag to true will change the defaults for other settings.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"javax.security.auth.subject"</td>
    <td>The subject under which the AccessControlContext is running.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
    <td>"org.apache.catalina.webappVersion"</td>
    <td>Name of the ServletContext attribute under which we store the web 
    application version string (the text that appears after ## when parallel 
    deployment is used).</td>
    </tr>
    </table>
    </body>
    </document>