<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="http.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author email="yoavs@apache.org">Yoav Shapira</author>
    <title>The HTTP Connector</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>HTTP Connector</strong> element represents a
  <strong>Connector</strong> component that supports the HTTP/1.1 protocol.
  It enables Catalina to function as a stand-alone web server, in addition
  to its ability to execute servlets and JSP pages.  A particular instance
  of this component listens for connections on a specific TCP port number
  on the server.  One or more such <strong>Connectors</strong> can be
  configured as part of a single <a href="service.html">Service</a>, each
  forwarding to the associated <a href="engine.html">Engine</a> to perform
  request processing and create the response.</p>

  <p>If you wish to configure the <strong>Connector</strong> that is used
  for connections to web servers using the AJP protocol (such as the
  <code>mod_jk 1.2.x</code> connector for Apache 1.3), see
  <a href="ajp.html">here</a> instead.</p>

  <p>Each incoming request requires
  a thread for the duration of that request.  If more simultaneous requests
  are received than can be handled by the currently available request
  processing threads, additional threads will be created up to the
  configured maximum (the value of the <code>maxThreads</code> attribute).
  If still more simultaneous requests are received, they are stacked up
  inside the server socket created by the <strong>Connector</strong>, up to
  the configured maximum (the value of the <code>acceptCount</code>
  attribute.  Any further simultaneous requests will receive "connection
  refused" errors, until resources are available to process them.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

  <p>All implementations of <strong>Connector</strong>
  support the following attributes:</p>

  <attributes>
 
    <attribute name="allowTrace" required="false">
      <p>A boolean value which can be used to enable or disable the TRACE
      HTTP method. If not specified, this attribute is set to false.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="emptySessionPath" required="false">
      <p>If set to <code>true</code>, all paths for session cookies will be set
      to <code>/</code>. This can be useful for portlet specification implementations,
      but will greatly affect performance if many applications are accessed on a given
      server by the client.
      If not specified, this attribute is set to <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="enableLookups" required="false">
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want calls to
      <code>request.getRemoteHost()</code> to perform DNS lookups in
      order to return the actual host name of the remote client.  Set
      to <code>false</code> to skip the DNS lookup and return the IP
      address in String form instead (thereby improving performance).
      By default, DNS lookups are enabled.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxPostSize" required="false">
      <p>The maximum size in bytes of the POST which will be handled by
      the container FORM URL parameter parsing. The limit can be disabled by
      setting this attribute to a value less than or equal to 0.
      If not specified, this attribute is set to 2097152 (2 megabytes).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxSavePostSize" required="false">
      <p>The maximum size in bytes of the POST which will be saved/buffered by
      the container during FORM or CLIENT-CERT authentication. For both types
      of authentication, the POST will be saved/buffered before the user is
      authenticated. For CLIENT-CERT authentication, the POST is buffered for
      the duration of
 the SSL handshake and the buffer emptied when the request
      is processed. For FORM authentication the POST is
 saved whilst the user
      is re-directed to the login form and is retained until the user
      successfully authenticates or the session associated with the
      authentication request expires. The limit can be disabled by setting this
      attribute to -1. Setting the attribute to
 zero will disable the saving of
      POST data during authentication
. If not
 specified, this attribute is set
      to
 4096 (4 kilobytes).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="protocol" required="false">
      <p>
        Sets the protocol to handle incoming traffic.
        The default value is <code>HTTP/1.1</code> and configures the 
        <code>org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11Protocol</code>. This is the blocking Java connector.<br/>
        If the <code>PATH(Windows)</code> or <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH(on most unix system)</code>  
        environment variables contain the Tomcat native library, the APR connector
        will automatically be configured. Please be advised that the APR connector has different
        settings for HTTPS than the default Java connector.<br/>
        Other values for this attribute are, but not limited to:<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11Protocol</code> - same as HTTP/1.1<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11NioProtocol</code> - non blocking Java connector<br/>
        <code>org.apache.coyote.http11.Http11AprProtocol</code> - the APR connector.<br/>
        Take a look at our <a href="#Connector Comparison">Connector Comparison</a> chart.
        The configuration for both Java connectors are identical, both for http and https. <br/>
        For more information on the APR connector and APR specific SSL settings please 
        visit the <a href="../apr.html">APR documentation</a>
        
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="proxyName" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is being used in a proxy
      configuration, configure this attribute to specify the server name
      to be returned for calls to <code>request.getServerName()</code>.
      See <a href="#Proxy Support">Proxy Support</a> for more
      information.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="proxyPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is being used in a proxy
      configuration, configure this attribute to specify the server port
      to be returned for calls to <code>request.getServerPort()</code>.
      See <a href="#Proxy Support">Proxy Support</a> for more
      information.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="redirectPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is supporting non-SSL
      requests, and a request is received for which a matching
      <code>&lt;security-constraint&gt;</code> requires SSL transport,
      Catalina will automatically redirect the request to the port
      number specified here.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="SSLEnabled" required="false">
      <p>
      Use this attribute to enable SSL traffic on a connector.
      To turn on SSL handshake/encryption/decryption on a connector
      set this value to <code>true</code>.
      The default value is <code>false</code>.
      When turning this value <code>true</code> you will want to set the 
      <code>scheme</code> and the <code>secure</code> attributes as well
      to pass the correct <code>request.getScheme()</code> and 
      <code>request.isSecure()</code> values to the servlets
      See <a href="#SSL Support">SSL Support</a> for more information.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="scheme" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to the name of the protocol you wish to have
      returned by calls to <code>request.getScheme()</code>.  For
      example, you would set this attribute to "<code>https</code>"
      for an SSL Connector.  The default value is "<code>http</code>".
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="secure" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> if you wish to have
      calls to <code>request.isSecure()</code> to return <code>true</code>
      for requests received by this Connector. You would want this on an
      SSL Connector or a non SSL connector that is receiving data from a 
      SSL accelerator, like a crypto card, a SSL appliance or even a webserver.
      The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="URIEncoding" required="false">
      <p>This specifies the character encoding used to decode the URI bytes,
      after %xx decoding the URL. If not specified, ISO-8859-1 will be used.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="useBodyEncodingForURI" required="false">
      <p>This specifies if the encoding specified in contentType should be used
      for URI query parameters, instead of using the URIEncoding. This
      setting is present for compatibility with Tomcat 4.1.x, where the
      encoding specified in the contentType, or explicitely set using
      Request.setCharacterEncoding method was also used for the parameters from
      the URL. The default value is <code>false</code>.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="useIPVHosts" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> to cause Tomcat to use
      the IP address that the request was recieved on to determine the Host
      to send the request to.  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="xpoweredBy" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> to cause Tomcat to advertise
      support for the Servlet specification using the header recommended in the
      specification.  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>
    
   


  </attributes>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

  <p>
  HTTP supports the following additional attributes (in addition to the
  common attributes listed above):</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="acceptCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum queue length for incoming connection requests when
      all possible request processing threads are in use.  Any requests
      received when the queue is full will be refused.  The default
      value is 10.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="address" required="false">
      <p>For servers with more than one IP address, this attribute
      specifies which address will be used for listening on the specified
      port.  By default, this port will be used on all IP addresses
      associated with the server.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="bufferSize" required="false">
      <p>The size (in bytes) of the buffer to be provided for input
      streams created by this connector.  By default, buffers of
      2048 bytes will be provided.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="compressableMimeType" required="false">
      <p>The value is a comma separated list of MIME types for which HTTP
      compression may be used.
      The default value is <code>text/html,text/xml,text/plain</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="compression" required="false">
      <p>The <strong>Connector</strong> may use HTTP/1.1 GZIP compression in
      an attempt to save server bandwidth. The acceptable values for the
      parameter is "off" (disable compression), "on" (allow compression, which
      causes text data to be compressed), "force" (forces compression in all
      cases), or a numerical integer value (which is equivalent to "on", but
      specifies the minimum amount of data before the output is compressed). If
      the content-length is not known and compression is set to "on" or more
      aggressive, the output will also be compressed. If not specified, this
      attribute is set to "off".</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="connectionLinger" required="false">
      <p>The number of milliseconds during which the sockets used by this
      <strong>Connector</strong> will linger when they are closed.
      The default value is -1 (socket linger is disabled).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="connectionTimeout" required="false">
      <p>The number of milliseconds this <strong>Connector</strong> will wait,
      after accepting a connection, for the request URI line to be
      presented.  The default value is 60000 (i.e. 60 seconds).</p>
    </attribute>
    
    <attribute name="executor" required="false">
      <p>A reference to the name in an <a href="executor.html">Executor</a> element.
         If this attribute is enabled, and the named executor exists, the connector will
         use the executor, and all the other thread attributes will be ignored.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keepAliveTimeout" required="false">
      <p>The number of milliseconds this <strong>Connector</strong> will wait for
       another HTTP request before closing the connection.
       The default value is to use the value that has been set for the
       connectionTimeout attribute.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="disableUploadTimeout" required="false">
      <p>This flag allows the servlet container to use a different, longer
      connection timeout while a servlet is being executed, which in the end
      allows either the servlet a longer amount of time to complete its
      execution, or a longer timeout during data upload. If not specified,
      this attribute is set to "true".</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxHttpHeaderSize" required="false">
      <p>The maximum size of the request and response HTTP header, specified
      in bytes.
      If not specified, this attribute is set to 4096 (4 KB).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxKeepAliveRequests" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of HTTP requests which can be pipelined until
      the connection is closed by the server. Setting this attribute to 1 will
      disable HTTP/1.0 keep-alive, as well as HTTP/1.1 keep-alive and
      pipelining. Setting this to -1 will allow an unlimited amount of
      pipelined or keep-alive HTTP requests.
      If not specified, this attribute is set to 100.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxThreads" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of request processing threads to be created
      by this <strong>Connector</strong>, which therefore determines the
      maximum number of simultaneous requests that can be handled.  If
      not specified, this attribute is set to 40. If an executor is associated
      with this connector, this attribute is ignored as the connector will 
      execute tasks using the executor rather than an internal thread pool.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="noCompressionUserAgents" required="false">
      <p>The value is a comma separated list of regular expressions matching
      user-agents of HTTP clients for which compression should not be used,
      because these clients, although they do advertise support for the
      feature, have a broken implementation.
      The default value is an empty String (regexp matching disabled).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="port" required="true">
      <p>The TCP port number on which this <strong>Connector</strong>
      will create a server socket and await incoming connections.  Your
      operating system will allow only one server application to listen
      to a particular port number on a particular IP address.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="restrictedUserAgents" required="false">
      <p>The value is a comma separated list of regular expressions matching
      user-agents of HTTP clients for which HTTP/1.1 or HTTP/1.0 keep alive
      should not be used, even if the clients advertise support for these
      features.
      The default value is an empty String (regexp matching disabled).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="server" required="false">
      <p>The Server header for the http response.
         Unless your paranoid, you won't need this feature.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="socketBuffer" required="false">
      <p>The size (in bytes) of the buffer to be provided for socket
      output buffering. -1 can be specified to disable the use of a buffer.
      By default, a buffers of 9000 bytes will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="tcpNoDelay" required="false">
      <p>If set to <code>true</code>, the TCP_NO_DELAY option will be
      set on the server socket, which improves performance under most
      circumstances.  This is set to <code>true</code> by default.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="threadPriority" required="false">
      <p>The priority of the request processing threads within the JVM.
      The default value is <code>java.lang.Thread#NORM_PRIORITY</code>.
      See the JavaDoc for the java.lang.Thread class for more details on
      what this priority means.
      </p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  </subsection>
  
    <subsection name="Nio Implementation">

    <p>The NIO connector exposes all the low level socket properties that can be used to tune the connector.
    Most of these attributes are directly linked to the socket implementation in the JDK so you can find out 
    about the actual meaning in the JDK API documentation.<br/>
    <strong>Note</strong>On some JDK versions, setTrafficClass causes a problem, a work around for this is to add 
    the <code>-Djava.net.preferIPv4Stack=true</code> value to your command line</p>

    <attributes>
      <attribute name="useSendfile" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Use this attribute to enable or disable sendfile capability.
           The default value is <code>true</code>
        </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="useExecutor" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Set to true to use the NIO thread pool executor. The default value is <code>true</code>.
        If set to false, it uses a thread pool based on a stack for its execution.
        Generally, using the executor yields a little bit slower performance, but yields a better
        fairness for processing connections in a high load environment as the traffic gets queued through a 
        FIFO queue. If set to true(default) then the max pool size is the <code>maxThreads</code> attribute
        and the core pool size is the <code>minSpareThreads</code>.
        This value is ignored if the <code>executor</code> attribute is present and points to a valid shared thread pool.
        </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="acceptorThreadCount" required="false">
        <p>(int)The number of threads to be used to accept connections. Increase this value on a multi CPU machine,
        although you would never really need more than <code>2</code>. Also, with a lot of non keep alive connections,
        you might want to increase this value as well. Default value is <code>1</code>.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="pollerThreadCount" required="false">
        <p>(int)The number of threads to be used to run for the polling events. Default value is <code>1</code>.
           Can't see a reason to go above that. But experiment and find your own results.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="pollerThreadPriority" required="false">
        <p>(int)The priority of the poller threads.
          The default value is <code>java.lang.Thread#NORM_PRIORITY</code>.
          See the JavaDoc for the java.lang.Thread class for more details on
          what this priority means.
        </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="acceptorThreadPriority" required="false">
        <p>(int)The priority of the acceptor threads. The threads used to accept new connections.
          The default value is <code>java.lang.Thread#NORM_PRIORITY</code>.
          See the JavaDoc for the java.lang.Thread class for more details on
          what this priority means.
        </p>
      </attribute>
      
      <attribute name="selectorTimeout" required="false">
        <p>(int)The time in milliseconds to timeout on a select() for the poller.
           This value is important, since connection clean up is done on the same thread, so dont set this 
           value to an extremely high one. The default value is <code>1000</code> milliseconds.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="useComet" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Whether to allow comet servlets or not, Default value is <code>true</code>.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="processCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)The protocol handler caches Http11NioProcessor objects to speed up performance.
           This setting dictates how many of these objects get cached.
           <code>-1</code> means unlimited, default is <code>200</code>. Set this value somewhere close to your maxThreads value.
        </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.directBuffer" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value, whether to use direct ByteBuffers or java mapped ByteBuffers. Default is <code>false</code>
           <br/>When you are using direct buffers, make sure you allocate the appropriate amount of memory for the 
                direct memory space. On Sun's JDK that would be something like <code>-XX:MaxDirectMemorySize=256m</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.rxBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The socket receive buffer (SO_RCVBUF) size in bytes. Default value is <code>25188</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.txBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The socket send buffer (SO_SNDBUF) size in bytes. Default value is <code>43800</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.appReadBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)Each connection that is opened up in Tomcat get associated with a read and a write ByteBuffer
           This attribute controls the size of these buffers. By default this read buffer is sized at <code>8192</code> bytes.
           For lower concurrency, you can increase this to buffer more data.
           For an extreme amount of keep alive connections, decrease this number or increase your heap size.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.appWriteBufSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)Each connection that is opened up in Tomcat get associated with a read and a write ByteBuffer
           This attribute controls the size of these buffers. By default this write buffer is sized at <code>8192</code> bytes.
           For low concurrency you can increase this to buffer more response data.
           For an extreme amount of keep alive connections, decrease this number or increase your heap size.
           <br/>
           The default value here is pretty low, you should up it if you are not dealing with tens of thousands
           concurrent connections.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.bufferPool" required="false">
        <p>(int)The Nio connector uses a class called NioChannel that holds elements linked to a socket.
           To reduce garbage collection, the Nio connector caches these channel objects.
           This value specifies the size of this cache.
           The default value is <code>500</code>, and represents that the cache will hold 500 NioChannel objects.
           Other values are <code>-1</code>. unlimited cache, and <code>0</code>, no cache.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.bufferPoolSize" required="false">
        <p>(int)The NioChannel pool can also be size based, not used object based. The size is calculated as follows:<br/>
        NioChannel <code>buffer size = read buffer size + write buffer size</code><br/>
        SecureNioChannel <code>buffer size = application read buffer size + application write buffer size + network read buffer size + network write buffer size</code><br/>
        The value is in bytes, the default value is <code>1024*1024*100</code> (100MB)
        </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.processorCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache SocketProcessor objects to reduce garbage collection.
           The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the cache at most.
           The default is <code>500</code>.
           Other values are <code>-1</code>. unlimited cache, and <code>0</code>, no cache.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.keyCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache KeyAttachment objects to reduce garbage collection.
           The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the cache at most.
           The default is <code>500</code>.
           Other values are <code>-1</code>. unlimited cache, and <code>0</code>, no cache.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.eventCache" required="false">
        <p>(int)Tomcat will cache PollerEvent objects to reduce garbage collection.
           The integer value specifies how many objects to keep in the cache at most.
           The default is <code>500</code>.
           Other values are <code>-1</code>. unlimited cache, and <code>0</code>, no cache.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.tcpNoDelay" required="false">
        <p>(bool)same as the standard setting <code>tcpNoDelay</code>. Default value is <code>false</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soKeepAlive" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the socket's keep alive setting (SO_KEEPALIVE). Default is <code>false</code>. </p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.ooBInline" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the socket OOBINLINE setting. Default value is <code>true</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soReuseAddress" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the sockets reuse address option (SO_REUSEADDR). Default value is <code>true</code></p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soLingerOn" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Boolean value for the sockets so linger option (SO_LINGER). Default value is <code>true</code>.
           This option is paired with the <code>soLingerTime</code> value.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soLingerTime" required="false">
        <p>(bool)Value in seconds for the sockets so linger option (SO_LINGER). Default value is <code>25</code> seconds.
           This option is paired with the soLinger value.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="socket.soTimeout" required="false">
        <p>(int)Value in milliseconds for the sockets read timeout (SO_TIMEOUT). Default value is <code>5000</code> milliseconds.</p>
      </attribute>      
      <attribute name="socket.soTrafficClass" required="false">
        <p>(byte)Value between <code>0</code> and <code>255</code> for the traffic class on the socket, <code>0x04 | 0x08 | 0x010</code></p>
      </attribute>      
      <attribute name="socket.performanceConnectionTime" required="false">
        <p>(int)The first value for the performance settings. Default is <code>1</code>, see <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a></p>
      </attribute>      
      <attribute name="socket.performanceLatency" required="false">
        <p>(int)The second value for the performance settings. Default is <code>0</code>, see <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a></p>
      </attribute>      
      <attribute name="socket.performanceBandwidth" required="false">
        <p>(int)The third value for the performance settings. Default is <code>1</code>, see <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/net/Socket.html#setPerformancePreferences(int,%20int,%20int)">Socket Performance Options</a></p>
      </attribute>      
      <attribute name="selectorPool.maxSelectors" required="false">
        <p>(int)The max selectors to be used in the pool, to reduce selector contention.
        Use this option when the command line <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared</code> value is set to false.
        Default value is <code>200</code>.</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="selectorPool.maxSpareSelectors" required="false">
        <p>(int)The max spare selectors to be used in the pool, to reduce selector contention.
        When a selector is returned to the pool, the system can decide to keep it or let it be GC:ed.
        Use this option when the command line <code>org.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared</code> value is set to false.
        Default value is <code>-1</code> (unlimited)</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="command-line-options" required="false">
        <p>The following command line options are available for the NIO connector:<br/>
        <code>-Dorg.apache.tomcat.util.net.NioSelectorShared=true|false</code> - default is <code>true</code>.
        Set this value to false if you wish to use a selector for each thread.
        the property. If you do set it to false, you can control the size of the pool of selectors by using the 
        selectorPool.maxSelectors attribute</p>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="oomParachute" required="false">
        <p>(int)The NIO connector implements an OutOfMemoryError strategy called parachute.
           It holds a chunk of data as a byte array. In case of an OOM,
           this chunk of data is released and the error is reported. This will give the VM enough room
           to clean up. The <code>oomParachute</code> represent the size in bytes of the parachute(the byte array).
           The default value is <code>1024*1024</code>(1MB).
           Please note, this only works for OOM errors regarding the Java Heap space, and there is absolutely no 
           guarantee that you will be able to recover at all.
           If you have an OOM outside of the Java Heap, then this parachute trick will not help.
        </p>
      </attribute>
    </attributes>
  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p>None at this time.</p>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">


  <subsection name="HTTP/1.1 and HTTP/1.0 Support">

  <p>This <strong>Connector</strong> supports all of the required features
  of the HTTP/1.1 protocol, as described in RFC 2616, including persistent
  connections, pipelining, expectations and chunked encoding.  If the client
  (typically a browser) supports only HTTP/1.0, the
  <strong>Connector</strong> will gracefully fall back to supporting this
  protocol as well.  No special configuration is required to enable this
  support. The <strong>Connector</strong> also supports HTTP/1.0
  keep-alive.</p>

  <p>RFC 2616 requires that HTTP servers always begin their responses with
  the highest HTTP version that they claim to support.  Therefore, this
  <strong>Connector</strong> will always return <code>HTTP/1.1</code> at
  the beginning of its responses.</p>

  </subsection>


  <subsection name="Proxy Support">

  <p>The <code>proxyName</code> and <code>proxyPort</code> attributes can
  be used when Tomcat is run behind a proxy server.  These attributes
  modify the values returned to web applications that call the
  <code>request.getServerName()</code> and <code>request.getServerPort()</code>
  methods, which are often used to construct absolute URLs for redirects.
  Without configuring these attributes, the values returned would reflect
  the server name and port on which the connection from the proxy server
  was received, rather than the server name and port to whom the client
  directed the original request.</p>

  <p>For more information, see the
  <a href="../proxy-howto.html">Proxy Support HOW-TO</a>.</p>

  </subsection>



  <subsection name="SSL Support">

  <p>You can enable SSL support for a particular instance of this
  <strong>Connector</strong> by setting the <code>secure</code> attribute to
  <code>true</code>.  In addition, you may need to configure the following
  attributes:</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="algorithm" required="false">
      <p>The certificate encoding algorithm to be used. This defaults to the Sun
      implementation (<code>SunX509</code>). For IBM JVMs you should use the
      value <code>IbmX509</code>. For other vendors, consult the JVM
      documentation for the correct value.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="clientAuth" required="false">
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want the SSL stack to require a
      valid certificate chain from the client before accepting a connection.
      Set to <code>want</code> if you want the SSL stack to request a client
      Certificate, but not fail if one isn't presented. A <code>false</code>
      value (which is the default) will not require a certificate chain
      unless the client requests a resource protected by a security
      constraint that uses <code>CLIENT-CERT</code> authentication. See the
      <a href="../ssl-howto.html">SSL HowTo</a> for an example.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keystoreFile" required="false">
      <p>The pathname of the keystore file where you have stored the
      server certificate to be loaded.  By default, the pathname is
      the file "<code>.keystore</code>" in the operating system home
      directory of the user that is running Tomcat.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keystorePass" required="false">
      <p>The password used to access the server certificate from the
      specified keystore file.  The default value is "<code>changeit</code>".
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keystoreType" required="false">
      <p>The type of keystore file to be used for the server certificate.
      If not specified, the default value is "<code>JKS</code>".</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="sslProtocol" required="false">
      <p>The version of the SSL protocol to use.  If not specified,
      the default is "<code>TLS</code>".</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="ciphers" required="false">
      <p>A comma seperated list of the encryption ciphers that may be used.
      If not specified, then any available cipher may be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="keyAlias" required="false">
      <p>The alias used to for the server certificate in the keystore. If not
      specified the first key read in the keystore will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="truststoreFile" required="false">
      <p>The TrustStore file to use to validate client certificates.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="truststorePass" required="false">
      <p>The password to access the TrustStore. This defaults to the value
      of <code>keystorePass</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="truststoreType" required="false">
      <p>Add this element if your are using a different format for the
      TrustStore then you are using for the KeyStore.</p>
     </attribute>

  </attributes>

  <p>For more information, see the
  <a href="../ssl-howto.html">SSL Configuration HOW-TO</a>.</p>

  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Connector Comparison">

    <p>Below is a small chart that shows how the connectors differentiate.</p>
    <source>
                  Java Blocking Connector       Java Nio Blocking Connector       APR Connector
    Classname         Http11Protocol                  Http11NioProtocol         Http11AprProtocol
    Tomcat Version   3.x 4.x 5.x 6.x                       6.x                     5.5.x 6.x
    Support Polling         NO                             YES                        YES
    Polling Size           N/A                   Unlimited - Restricted by mem        Unlimited
    Read HTTP Request     Blocking                     Non Blocking                   Blocking
    Read HTTP Body        Blocking                     Blocking                       Blocking
    Write HTTP Response   Blocking                     Blocking                       Blocking
    SSL Support           Java SSL                     Java SSL                       OpenSSL
    SSL Handshake         Blocking                     Non blocking                   Blocking
    Max Connections       maxThreads                   See polling size               See polling size
    
    
    </source>

  </subsection>
</section>


</body>

</document>
