<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="resources.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <title>The Resources Component</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Table of Contents">
<toc />
</section>

<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>Resources</strong> element represents all the resources
  available to the web application. This includes classes, JAR files, HTML, JSPs
  and any other files that contribute to the web application. Implementations
  are provided to use directories, JAR files and WARs as the source of these
  resources and the resources implementation may be extended to provide support
  for files stored in other forms such as in a database or a versioned
  repository.</p>

  <p>Resources are cached by default. Caching may be controlled by configuring
  the appropriate caching attributes on the containing <a href="context.html">
  Context</a>.</p>

  <p><strong>Note: Running a webapp with non-filesystem based
  Resources implementations is only possible when the webapp does not
  rely on direct filesystem access to its own resources, and uses the methods
  in the ServletContext interface to access them.</strong></p>

  <p>A Resources element MAY be nested inside a
  <a href="context.html">Context</a> component.  If it is not included,
  a default filesystem based Resources will be created automatically,
  which is sufficient for most requirements.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

    <p>All implementations of <strong>Resources</strong>
    support the following attributes:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="className" required="false">
        <p>Java class name of the implementation to use. This class must
        implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.WebResourceRoot</code>
        interface. If not specified, the standard value (defined below) will be
        used.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>


  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

    <p>The standard implementation of <strong>Resources</strong> is
    <strong>org.apache.catalina.webresources.StandardRoot</strong>, and
    is configured by its parent Context element.</p>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p>A web application&apos;s main resources are defined by the
  <strong>docBase</strong> defined for the <a href="context.html">Context</a>.
  Additional resources may be made available to the web application by defining
  one or more nested components.</p>

  <h3>PreResources</h3>

  <p>PreResources are searched before the main resources. They will be searched
  in the order they are defined. To configure PreResources, nest a
  &lt;PreResources&gt; element inside the &lt;Resources&gt; element with the
  following attributes:</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="base" required="true">
      <p>Identifies where the resources to be used are located. This attribute
      is required by the <code>org.apache.catalina.WebResourceSet</code>
      implementations provided by Tomcat and should specify the absolute path to
      the file, directory or JAR where the resources are located. Custom
      implementations may not require it.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="className" required="true">
      <p>Java class name of the implementation to use. This class must
      implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.WebResourceSet</code> interface.
      Tomcat provides three standard implementations:
      <code>org.apache.catalina.webresources.DirResourceSet</code>,
      <code>org.apache.catalina.webresources.FileResourceSet</code> and
      <code>org.apache.catalina.webresources.JarResourceSet</code>. Custom
      implementations may also be used.
      </p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="internalPath" required="false">
      <p>Identifies the path within the <strong>base</strong> where the
      resources are to be found. This is typically only used with JAR files when
      the resources are not located at the root of the JAR as is the case with
      resource JARs. This attribute is required by the
      <code>org.apache.catalina.WebResourceSet</code> implementations provided
      by Tomcat. Custom implementations may not require it. If not specified,
      the default value of the empty string will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="webAppMount" required="false">
      <p>Identifies the path within the web application that these resources
      will be made available. This attribute is required by the
      <code>org.apache.catalina.WebResourceSet</code> implementations provided
      by Tomcat. Custom implementations may not require it. If not specified,
      the default value of the empty string will be used.</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  <h3>JAR resources</h3>

  <p>JarResources are searched after the main resources but before the
  PostResources. They will be searched in the order they are defined. To
  configure JarResources, nest a &lt;JarResources&gt; element inside the
  &lt;Resources&gt; element. The configuration attributes are the same as for
  <strong>PreResources</strong>.
  </p>

  <h3>Post-resources</h3>

  <p>PostResources are searched after the resource JARs. They will be searched
  in the order they are defined. To configure PostResources, nest a
  &lt;PostResources&gt; element inside the &lt;Resources&gt; element. The
  configuration attributes are the same as for <strong>PreResources</strong>.
  </p>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">

  <p>No special features are associated with a <strong>Resources</strong>
  element.</p>

</section>


</body>


</document>
